Acknowledgments

Thanks to Susan Duncan, Dean of the University of Louisville Louis D. Brandeis School of Law and to University of Louisville for institutional support in preparing this edition.

Thanks to Elaine Shoben for suggesting Ann McGinley as coauthor beginning with the 5th edition.

To Kea Middleton and Rita Siegwald for their administrative assistance in preparing the manuscript, to Julia Irzyk and Lisa Goldberg for their research support.

To Charles B. Craver, Freda H. Alverson Professor of Law at George Washington University, for encouraging and supporting publication of the first edition of this book.

To Joe Smith, Bonnie Tucker, Lex Frieden, Wendy Wilkinson, Peg Nosek, Laurie Gerken Redd, the late Kathleen DeSilva, and the late Gretchen George, my thanks for challenging me to think about these issues from their unique perspectives. A similar thanks to all of the students with disabilities who have helped me to consider how to address the challenges they face in new and creative ways.

To the late Paul Steven Miller, Jan Sheldon Sherman, Ilene Shane, Elaine Roberts, Rud Turnbull, Michael Perlin, Robert Silverstein, Peter Blanck, Chai Feldblum, Larry Gostin, Scott Lissner, Jim Kessler, and John Wodatch for their positive influence, in my work on disability law.

To my former colleagues Mary Anne Bobinski, Ron Turner, Mary Anderlik, and Bill Winslade for their insights.

To my current colleague, Sam Marcosson, thanks for engaging in thought provoking discussions about disability law.

Special acknowledgements to Stanley Herr, a law professor at the University of Maryland, who died in 2001. Stan had been involved in several important disability rights issues, including special education, deinstitutionalization, mental health histories for professional licensing, and prohibition of execution of individuals with intellectual disabilities. And to Adam Milani, a law professor at Mercer University, who died in 2005. Adam and I shared an interest in writing about sports and disability law, and a mutual respect for each other's work. Their advocacy and intellect are missed, but their work has enabled others to build on the foundations they have laid.

Additional special acknowledgement to my friend, the late H. Joan Ehrlich, who served in leadership positions within the EEOC until she died in December 2008. Her proactive approach to educating and informing everyone about employment discrimination was extremely valuable and is greatly missed.

In summer 2009, the world lost the great Senator Edward Kennedy. His constant, unfailing and effective leadership is responsible for most of the major legislation providing protection and rights for individuals with disabilities. He inspired many to make sure that the “dream lives on.”

And finally, as always, I thank my parents, Dorothy Friesen and the late Eric J. Friesen, for their constant support and example; to my daughters, Julia and Lisa for their patience; and to Mark, my husband and colleague for his valuable contributions and suggestions on issues of employment, genetics, and privacy.

Laura Rothstein

Thanks to Dean Dan Hamilton, current dean of the William S. Boyd School of Law, University of Nevada, Las Vegas, and Chancellor John White, former dean of the William S. Boyd School of Law and current Chancellor of the Nevada System of Higher Education, for supporting this project.

Thanks also to Jeanne Price, Associate Dean for Academic Affairs, Professor of Law, and Director of the Wiener-Rogers Law Library at Boyd School of Law, UNLV, who supported this project wholeheartedly. Thanks also to David McClure, Associate Director of the Wiener-Rogers Law Library, and to library faculty Chad Schatzle, and Jennifer Gross and to Boyd law students for their excellent and very quick research.

Thanks to my colleagues at UNLV, Boyd School of Law for supporting this project, especially Elaine Shoben, Terry Pollman, Linda Edwards, and Jeff Stempel.

Thanks to Nettie Mann, our amazing administrative assistant, who has worked on this book and so many other projects at UNLV Boyd School of Law.

Thanks to those students, friends, and family members who live with disabilities and have helped me understand the difficulties they face and the important and creative role that law and understanding can play in helping them live and soar with those disabilities.

Special thanks go to my mother, Mary McGinley, who turned ninety-seven years old as I was preparing this manuscript, and who never wavered in her support, to my late father, Paul McGinley, a lawyer's lawyer who gave me courage as a child to be what I wanted to be, to my brother and sisters, Paul, Laurie and Ellin, who are always supportive of my projects.

Special thanks to Jeff Stempel, my colleague and husband, for his valuable contributions, especially on issues of insurance and disabilities, and to my children, Ryan, Shanen, and Reed for helping me understand what young adults need in order to learn.

Both of us thank Keith Moore and Sean Caldwell of Carolina Academic Press for their timely and considerable efforts and support.

Finally, thank you to Laura Rothstein, my amazing, knowledgeable coauthor. It is a pleasure to work with you.

Ann McGinley

Chapter 8

Housing and Independent Living

A. Introduction

In this chapter, nondiscrimination protections for individuals with disabilities are addressed in the context of housing and independent living. Nondiscrimination provisions apply to both the sale and rental of housing. Until 1988, there was no comprehensive protection against housing discrimination on the basis of disability status. There were many state laws, but these varied a great deal in application and effectiveness. Federally funded housing was covered as of 1973 under Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act, 29 U.S.C. §794, but this applies to only a small segment of housing.

There were two federal statutes in existence before 1973 that primarily provided benefits, rather than nondiscrimination protection. Section 202 of the federal Housing Act of 1959, 12 U.S.C. §1701q(a)(2), is a loan program to enable nonprofit, limited-profit, or public agencies to build low cost housing. Recipients are required to provide services to facilitate independent living for their tenants. Only elderly tenants or those with disabilities are eligible for Section 202 housing. The types of disabilities include physical disabilities, mental impairments, and developmental disabilities. The definition under Section 202 refers to individuals whose disability is expected to be long-term and of indefinite duration, who are substantially impeded in the ability to live independently, and whose situation could be improved by more suitable housing conditions. 12 U.S.C. §1701q(d)(4). Under this program, landlords receive rent subsidies for housing vouchers for individuals with low incomes and those with disabilities. 42 U.S.C. §1437f(t); 24 C.F.R. §5.403. This makes Section 8 subject to Section 504 nondiscrimination mandates.

In 1988, Congress amended the Fair Housing Act, which up until that time had prohibited housing discrimination only on the basis of race, color, sex, religion, and national origin. The 1988 amendments added familial status and handicap^1 as protected classifications. The definition of handicap under the amendment is virtually identical to the Rehabilitation Act definition. 42 U.S.C. §§3601 et seq.

The Fair Housing Act covers most issues related to housing discrimination against individuals with disabilities, with the Rehabilitation Act providing additional coverage for federally supported housing.

Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act, 42 U.S.C. §§12131 et seq., also plays a role because of the application to the oversight of state and local agencies in land use regulation, including zoning. Under the amendments, discrimination on the basis of disability refers not only to acts and practices such as refusal to rent and charging higher rent, but also requires new multiunit construction to meet specific accessibility guidelines for barrier-free design. Modifications to practices and policies as reasonable accommodations also are required. Title III of the ADA applies to hotel accommodations, which are specifically not covered under the Fair Housing Act.

Elimination of discrimination, including barrier removal and reasonable accommodations, is an important beginning for individuals with disabilities to ensure mainstream participation in society. For many individuals with disabilities, there is a need for supportive services, such as home health care for individuals with certain health impairments, supervision for individuals with some mental disabilities, and attendant care for individuals with mobility impairments. Without funding support for these services, discrimination laws alone will not ensure the right to live in the community.

B. Overview

This chapter focuses on the application of the major federal statutes that protect individuals with disabilities from discrimination on that basis, including indirect discrimination that has disparate impact and adverse actions that result from the failure to provide reasonable accommodations. This chapter will present through case excerpt decisions, problems, and textual reference the following concepts:

Discrimination against individuals with disabilities resulting from negative attitudes based on myths, stereotypes, and prejudice. This discrimination applies particularly disabilities involving HIV and those involving mental illness and intellectual disabilities.
Discrimination that is more indirect because of neutral practices or conduct such as parking rules and assignments, zoning rules and private deed restrictions, and rules regarding presence of animals in various housing settings. This discrimination would be addressed by modification of policies as a reasonable accommodation.
Discrimination primarily affecting individuals with mobility impairments that results from structural design and other architectural barriers. The readings will highlight how different kinds of housing are subject to different design standards.
Discrimination primarily affecting individuals with disabilities that have in the past resulted in their living in very restrictive institutional or hospital type settings and how policies since the 1970s have provided a principle of mainstreaming and independent living.
Basic introductory background on the procedures and remedies available in various settings under the major statutes to ensure protection against discrimination.

The following are some key terms for reference in learning about individuals with disabilities in the context of housing issues.

Associational status

Both the FHA and ADA protect individuals who are associated with individuals who meet the definition of handicap/disability. For example, an individual whose landlord evicted that tenant because he/she worked in a medical facility treating individuals with HIV on that basis would be protected.

Community living

This concept is an evolution of the deinstitutionalization movement that is intended to ensure that individuals with disabilities are able to live in a community rather than in isolation in a hospital type institution.

Deinstitutionalization

This refers to a movement that began in the 1950s and had significant momentum in the early 1970s where advocacy groups brought litigation under constitutional theories and Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act and state laws seeking to move individuals with mental illness and intellectual disabilities (and some physical impairments) from institutional restrictive settings into the mainstream of society by moving them into the communities. While the legal theories supported this change, the resources in the community have often been lacking or the funding mechanism to pay for services in the least restrictive community setting are not set up.

Design standards

Refers to the design requirements included in various federal regulations related to the specifications of physical facilities for aspects such as ramp incline ratios, turning radius on landings and in bathrooms, and grab bars in bathrooms, and parking specifications.

Discriminatory impact

Policies that are neutral on their face, but which adversely affect individuals with disabilities in a disparate way, may be evidence of discrimination, depending on the situation. For example, a policy prohibiting pets might have a discriminatory impact on individuals who need service or emotional support animals for their disabilities.

Documentation

For an individual to be protected under nondiscrimination laws, the person must meet the definition of disability. This might require appropriate documentation of the condition. In the case of housing, that would generally be a physician's evaluation of the condition, its impact, and the relationship of the requested accommodation to the condition.

Group home

In order to provide effective services for individuals with significant impairments requiring extensive services in the community, group homes have been set up as one mechanism to provide these individuals housing in a community setting. Such homes often have between four and 12 individuals with support staff that either live in or provide staff support for the residence. Group homes often face opposition in communities as not being consistent with zoning or deed restriction requirements defining single-family residences.

Handicapped/disability

(1) a physical or mental impairment which substantially limits one or more of such person's major life activities, (2) a record of having such an impairment, or (3) being regarded as having such an impairment, but such term does not include current, illegal use of or addiction to a controlled substance

Most federal statutes use “disability” as the preferred term, but the Fair Housing Act continues to use “handicap.”

Independent living

Independent living refers to policies that allow for individuals with disabilities to live in their own homes (or in group homes) with support services to do so. Such services might be assistance with dressing, eating, and other daily living activities.

Least restrictive environment

A general concept of all federal disability discrimination law is the philosophy that individuals with disabilities should be able to function in the least restrictive appropriate environment.

Private deed restrictions

These work similarly to zoning restrictions in that homeowners' associations and similar common interest communities often have restrictions regarding structural design and animals. When a disability could be accommodated by modifying or waiving such a restriction, it must be considered as a possible accommodation.

Service and emotional support animals

Service animals are those that perform a task, while comfort or emotional support animals are those that provide support for an individual with an emotional or mental impairment. The federal requirements for these types of animals varies depending on the setting: a public place, an employer's place of business, or housing.

Structural barrier

Refers to an architectural or other design barrier that affects the ability of an individual with a disability to access a facility. In the housing context, the most common barriers are steps, steep ramps, lack of elevators, heavy doors, counter heights, door widths, location and design of parking spaces, and turning areas.

Zoning restrictions

Zoning restrictions generally have been upheld as constitutional under the police powers to regulate health, safety, welfare, and morals. The application of such standards to specific properties has been addressed in numerous cases. For purposes of housing, the zoning issues that arise generally relate to waiver or variance of zoning requirements as a reasonable accommodation for a disability. Common examples in the housing context would involve exterior architectural features (e.g., allowing a carport or a ramp at the front entrance); permitting variances to animal restrictions (e.g., allowing pit bull dogs as service animals in communities where they are ordinarily restricted); and allowing group homes in areas restricted to single family residences.

—————

The single problem in this chapter provides a context for reviewing many of the concepts noted above. Specific statutory and regulatory requirements do not clearly resolve the questions, so judicial interpretation must be relied on to provide guidance.

Hypothetical Problem 8.1

The Transitional Rehabilitation Access Veterans Equal Living (TRAVEL) Organization is a nonprofit social service provider whose mission is to provide transitional services for military veterans who have served in the military and who have been injured during that service. TRAVEL is funded through a combination of federal and state grants, private contributions, and the veterans themselves. One of TRAVEL's major programs is to provide transitional group housing in cities where veterans' rehabilitation hospitals are located to allow individuals who have ongoing medical and rehabilitation needs to live near the hospitals until they can return to their own homes.

TRAVEL accomplishes this goal by purchasing or renting homes in residential neighborhoods that can accommodate eight to ten residents (plus a staff member) with a range of conditions. The average period of residence is generally twelve to eighteen months. The veterans who seek this housing generally have some type of mobility impairments resulting from lost limbs or paralysis. Many have additional mental health needs such as post-traumatic stress disorder. Some have become addicted to drugs or use alcohol, which began as a result of their combat experiences and injuries. One of the goals of TRAVEL is drug and alcohol rehabilitation.

TRAVEL is seeking to rent two adjacent homes (one for men, one for women) in a residence near the Springfield V.A. hospital and has begun negotiations with the owner of two similar large single-family dwellings with five bedrooms. The owner had originally lived in one home and had allowed adult children to live in the adjacent home. All have relocated to another area of the country. The neighborhood is middle income and has both private deed restrictions and zoning requirements regarding architectural and other issues. The home in question is ideally suited not only for its proximity to the V.A. hospital but also its proximity to the metro bus stop, which would allow residents to travel easily to the hospital and to other areas of Springfield for shopping and recreation. Having the male and female housing adjacent to each other will allow for economies of scale for transportation, home health care services, and other services. There is very little suitable rental housing available in this neighborhood.

The private deed restrictions prohibit carports and front entrance ramps because of their appearance and the goal of uniform aesthetic architecture. Zoning restrictions related to occupancy require that housing in the neighborhood should be single-family housing and any variances must be approved by the zoning commission. Zoning restrictions also provide that occupancy levels must ensure that for each resident there be at least 600 square feet of living space. The homes at issue each have 4,500 square feet, which would only accommodate seven total occupants within the zoning requirements. Basement areas are not counted in the zoning regulations, although the houses in question have finished basements with an additional 1,000 square feet (including a finished full bathroom). For reasons of economic viability, TRAVEL seeks to have at least eight veterans plus one staff member live at each residence. There is a zoning and private deed restriction limiting the number of pets to three per residence and requiring that all animals be domesticated. Additional zoning restrictions prohibit “group homes” from being located within three blocks of each other.

TRAVEL has met the following problems in its efforts to locate the home at the desired location. The owner, who was eager to rent, initially has learned of TRAVEL's request to make some renovations in the house (lowering some light switches and adding reinforcements and grab bars in all bathrooms and some bedrooms, adding a temporary carport adjacent to the back entrance so that wheelchairs will not be damaged during inclement weather, and adding a ramp to the front entrance). TRAVEL is requesting a three-year renewable lease and has promised to return the homes to their original condition after the lease ends. The goal is to continue to operate the homes so long as there is need and funding. The owner is reluctant to allow these changes and has advised TRAVEL that even if he would allow them, the homeowners' association would have to approve the front ramp and the carport and these variances would be unlikely because other residents would be concerned about the impact on their home value.

Initial discussions with the zoning board have raised concerns about the occupancy levels, the fact that two such residences would be located next to each other, and potential parking problems. Both the homeowner's association and the zoning officials have serious concerns with TRAVEL's indication that occasionally there might be monkeys trained to assist with manual tasks and that there might be more than three animals on site. Both have raised concerns that at the very least, they would expect notification of the identity of any residents with drug abuse problems or mental health problems and a right to veto their occupancy.

The legal counsel for TRAVEL has been consulted about the best course of action, both in terms of legal rights in this situation and the feasibility and difficulty and strategic decisions of proceeding further.

—————

C. Discrimination

Most disability discrimination in housing probably results from unintentional practices, such as barriers in architectural design or policies that have a disparate adverse impact on individuals with disabilities. The most common type of discrimination that results from negative attitudes occurs in cases involving group homes for individuals with disabilities such as HIV, drug and alcohol histories, and intellectual disabilities or mental illness. The manifestation of this discriminatory attitude results in denials of special use permits required for zoning variances for group homes or from enforcement of restrictive covenants in a discriminatory manner. The Supreme Court decision in City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Ctr., 473 U.S. 432 (1985), challenged such discriminatory conduct by applying constitutional equal protection and due process principles. The Court applied the rational basis test in striking down the denial of a special use permit by a municipal zoning board as being based on unfounded prejudices against individuals with mental illness or intellectual disabilities.

Challenges to discriminatory conduct under the Constitution are only viable where there is state action. Thus, much private housing discrimination would not be prohibited. For this reason, the Fair Housing Act Amendments of 1988 provide a much more viable alternative for attacking discrimination in housing on the basis of disability.

In 2015, the Supreme Court in Texas Department of Housing and Community Affairs v. Inclusive Communities Project, Inc., 135 S. Ct. 2507, 51 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶85 (2015), confirmed that the disparate impact test could be used under the Fair Housing Act. The facts of the case involved a state agency tax credit scoring system that disparately impacted white applicants.

The following case sets out the Fair Housing Act Amendment requirements in the context of a case involving a group home permit request. In this case, the group home was intended to be a hospice for HIV-positive, homeless individuals, in the later stages of the disease. This case arose during the time that the HIV epidemic first occurred and there was a lack of understanding about HIV and its transmission. Decisions about employment, housing, and health care for people with HIV were based on unfounded fears.

Baxter v. City of Belleville

720 F. Supp. 720 (N.D. Ill. 1989)

STIEHL, DISTRICT JUDGE:

On March 27, 1989, Baxter filed an application with the Belleville Zoning Board for a special use permit for a residence he desires to establish in the City of Belleville to provide housing for AIDS infected persons. On April 27, 1989, the Zoning Board voted to recommend that Baxter's request be denied. That recommendation was then presented to the Belleville City Council at its May 15, 1989 meeting. Baxter's request for a special use permit was denied by a 9 to 7 vote of the Council.

[The residence in question was for a one-year lease for a hospice for terminally ill patients.]

The Zoning Board hearing was held on April 27, 1989. Baxter's counsel made a lengthy presentation to the Board including traffic and parking impact, availability of local medical facilities, current zoning of the property and a description of the location. She told the Board that no one in the area opposed the special use request. Copies of an exchange of letters between Hospice of Southern Illinois and Baxter were presented to the Board with respect to the use of the term “hospice.” However, not until the end of the presentation to the Zoning Board was it revealed that the residents of Our Place would be AIDS patients.

The Board members asked Baxter a number of questions, including whom he intended to house in the facility. Baxter told the Board that he would be housing AIDS patients. The majority of the questions asked of Baxter concerned the members' fear of AIDS. The questions included: how potential residents would be screened; supervision of the residents; effect on the junior high school across the street; how Baxter would handle sanitation, including disposal of body fluids; why he chose Belleville for the residence; needs in Belleville for such a residence; and, whether Baxter, himself, was homosexual or had tested positive for the Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV).

Baxter informed the Board of his extensive history of providing in-home care for critically ill patients, including AIDS patients in the final stages of their disease. He spoke of three persons in Belleville who were HIV-infected and homeless and of Red Cross statistics to the effect that there are 3000 HIV-positive cases in Madison and St. Clair Counties. He also told the Board that he personally had spoken with the Superintendent of Schools about his plans for Our Place, and that the Superintendent had said that he had no problem with the residence plans. Baxter told the Board that AIDS persons deserved to live with dignity so that they could die with dignity.

Our Place is located in the 6th Ward, and both 6th Ward aldermen were present at the hearing. No opposition was raised by any member of the audience. The Board voted unanimously to recommend to the Board of Aldermen that Baxter's request for special use permit be denied.

The City designated Frank Heafner, one of the members of the Zoning Board, to testify on behalf of the Zoning Board. He testified that one of the important reasons the Board recommended denial of the permit was that Our Place would be close to a junior high school. The Board was also concerned with the potential change in property values in the area, and that people might stay away from that part of Belleville. He also stated that the Board was concerned with Baxter's lack of qualifications and they were uncertain how he was going to accomplish his plans. Heafner testified that it was the belief of the Board that Baxter would need more training, although he was not able to say exactly what training would be necessary to satisfy the Board's concerns. The Board members also expressed concern about the potential spread of AIDS through residents who might be intravenous drug users and homosexuals.

The Belleville City Council considered Baxter's request for a special use permit at its regular meeting held May 15, 1989. Alderman Koeneman of the 6th ward, where 301 South Illinois is located, made a motion to overturn the recommendation of the Zoning Board. The motion was seconded by Alderman Seibert, of the same ward.

Because there were a number of questions from the aldermen, Mayor Brauer requested and received permission from the Council for Baxter to respond to the questions. (No member of the public is permitted to speak at a Council meeting without formal approval by the Council.) Thomas Mabry, a Belleville alderman, was designated by the City to testify on behalf of the City Council. He stated that the majority of the questions from the aldermen were addressed to how the facility would be run and concerns of the aldermen about AIDS. He also testified that the City Council was concerned with the fact that Our Place would affect property values; that many of the residents would be intravenous drug users; and that the facility is located across the street from a junior high school.

Mabry stated that the main factors in his voting to refuse the special use permit were: (1) Baxter did not convince him that Baxter had the ability to run or fund the facility; (2) Baxter did not have sufficient medical or counseling background to run the facility; (3) Baxter did not have a plan for proper sanitation, specifically, disposal of items that would come into contact with the AIDS virus; and, (4) his major concern was the location of the residence—in a commercial area, in close proximity to both a junior high school and a grade school.

He also testified that he understood Baxter's intent to be to establish a residence for seven HIV-infected persons, but that during the meeting Baxter changed the number of prospective residents to four, of whom only two could be in the critical stages of the disease. Mabry admitted that he did not know of Baxter's medical background.

Mabry has served on both the City Council and the Zoning Board. He stated that the Council generally votes unanimously, and if the two aldermen for the ward in which the applicant property is located vote in favor of a variance, special use permit, or other zoning change, the other aldermen will vote with them. Mabry further testified that he could not recall an instance in which a request that was supported by the two aldermen of the ward in which the property was located had been denied by the Council.

Arthur Baum, Belleville City Clerk, testified that he was present at the City Council meeting, and confirmed Mabry's testimony as to the nature of the questions asked by the aldermen, and their concerns. Baum understood Baxter's intended use of the facility to be for the housing of terminally ill AIDS patients in the last stages of their disease. He stated that no one on the Council referred to any medical authorities or experts, and that to his knowledge none were consulted by the Council. He further testified that there was no specific determination by the Council as to the health and safety issues, although the vote indicated the Council's position. Baum testified that the aldermen made it clear that they were concerned about and feared the spread of HIV into the community if Our Place were allowed to open.

Baum testified that he has been City Clerk for ten years, and that he does not know of any other instance during that time when the Council voted against a request supported by the two aldermen of the ward in which the property was located.

[Baxter's background and experience as a home healthcare provider and in caring for individuals with AIDS is long and extensive.]

Plaintiff's expert, Robert L. Murphy, M.D., testified at length and in great detail as to the genesis, transmission and physiological development of the Human Immunodeficiency Virus, commonly referred to as “HIV.” The Court finds that Dr. Murphy is qualified as an expert in the field of sexually transmitted diseases.

The City did not attempt to refute or rebut Dr. Murphy's testimony by offering its own expert.

[Medical findings omitted.]

Based on the conclusive medical evidence presented, the Court finds that persons who are HIV-positive pose no risk of its transmission to the community at large.

It is evident from Baxter's testimony that his intention for Our Place, has, from its inception, been to offer housing to persons who are HIV-positive, homeless, and in the later stages of the disease, but still able to care for themselves. However, throughout the evidentiary hearing the parties used the terms “AIDS” and “HIV-positive” interchangeably, although it is clear from the medical evidence before the Court that not all persons who are HIV-positive have progressed to the AIDS stage of the disease. In an effort to minimize confusion with respect to the Court's discussion of this deadly disease, it will be referred to as HIV, understanding AIDS to be included in that term.

(a) Fair Housing Act

Sections 3601, et seq. of the FHA are amendments to the Act which became effective March 12, 1989. Among the stated purposes for the amendments were the Congressional interest in expanding the Act to allow private litigants the right to challenge alleged discriminatory housing practices, and including handicapped persons among those protected by the Act.

Plaintiff asserts that his rights under §3604(f)(1) and §3617 have been violated by the City's refusal to grant him a special use permit and thereby allow him to open the residence to house up to seven persons with AIDS.

Section 3604(f)(1) makes it unlawful:

To discriminate in the sale or rental, or to otherwise make unavailable or deny, a dwelling to any buyer or renter because of a handicap of—(A) that buyer or renter; (B) a person residing in or intending to reside in that dwelling after it is so sold, rented, or made available; or (C) any person associated with that buyer or renter.

Section 3617 provides:

It shall be unlawful to coerce, intimidate, threaten, or interfere with any person in the exercise or enjoyment of, or on account of his having exercised or enjoyed, or on account of his having aided or encouraged any other person in the exercise or enjoyment of, any right granted or protected by section 3603, 3604, 3605, or 3606 of this title. This section may be enforced by appropriate civil action.

Because Baxter's claims under both §3604 and §3617 are founded on the same conduct or acts of the City, under the holding in Arlington Heights, for Baxter to have standing under §3617, the Court must first be persuaded that he has standing under §3604. Accordingly, the Court will first look to Baxter's standing to sue under §3604(f)(1). The main thrust of section (f)(1) is to prohibit discrimination in housing based upon handicap. Therefore, the Court must determine whether persons infected with HIV are handicapped within the meaning of the statute.

(i) Determination of Handicap Under the Act

Section 3602(h) defines handicap as follows:

(h) “Handicap” means, with respect to a person—(1) a physical or mental impairment which substantially limits one or more of such person's major life activities, (2) a record of having such an impairment, or (3) being regarded as having such an impairment, but such term does not include current, illegal use of or addiction to a controlled substance as defined in section 802 of Title 21.

The 1988 amendments to the FHA were modeled on the Rehabilitation Act of 1973.

It is clear from its legislative history that Congress intended to include among handicapped persons those who are HIV-positive. The Fair Housing Amendments [sic] Act, like Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, as amended, is a clear pronouncement of a national commitment to end the unnecessary exclusion of persons with handicaps from the American mainstream. It repudiates the use of stereotypes and ignorance, and mandates that persons with handicaps be considered as individuals. Generalized perceptions about disabilities and unfounded speculations about threats to safety are specifically rejected as grounds to justify exclusion.... People with Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) and people who test positive for the AIDS virus have been evicted because of an erroneous belief that they pose a health risk to others. All of these groups have experienced discrimination because of prejudice and aversion—because they make non-handicapped people uncomfortable. H.R. 1158 clearly prohibits the use of stereotypes and prejudice to deny critically needed housing to handicapped persons. The right to be free from housing discrimination is essential to the goal of independent living. Although Congress spoke in terms of persons with AIDS and “people who test positive for the AIDS virus,” notwithstanding the problems with nomenclature, the legislative history supports a finding that Congress intended to include persons with HIV within the definition of handicapped.

In School Board of Nassau County v. Arline, 480 U.S. 273 (1987), the Supreme Court declined to determine whether a carrier of AIDS, that is an HIV-positive person, would fall within the definition of handicap under the Rehabilitation Act. The plaintiff in Arline was a tuberculosis victim, and not HIV-positive. Subsequent courts, however, have addressed the application of the Rehabilitation Act to persons with HIV, and have found that those with ARC and AIDS are handicapped under the Act.

[T]he inability to reside in a group residence due to the public misapprehension that HIV-positive persons cannot interact with non-HIV-infected persons adversely affects a major life activity. The Court therefore finds that persons who are HIV-positive are handicapped within the meaning of the FHA.

(b) Application of §3604(f)(1)

In light of the evidence adduced at the hearing, it cannot be said that Baxter is, himself, infected with HIV. Therefore, §3604(f)(1)(A) is not applicable in this action.

[The court addresses whether Baxter has standing because he does not have HIV. The court determined that because Baxter demonstrated economic injury, he met the injury in fact requirement. As a further policy matter, the court noted that Baxter had standing, because it is unlawful to interfere with protected rights under the FHA. The court then addresses the application of the discriminatory impact/effect test.]

There are two methods of showing a violation of §3604. The first method is commonly referred to as an “intent” case. That is, plaintiff need only show that the handicap of the potential residents at Our Place, a protected group under the FHA, was in some part the basis for the City's action.

The evidence adduced at the hearing supports plaintiff's claim that irrational fear of AIDS was at least a motivating factor in the City's refusal to grant Baxter's special use permit. Furthermore, due to that fear, the City's actions were both intentional and specifically designed to prevent persons with HIV from residing at Our Place. Therefore, plaintiff has established a sufficient likelihood of success on the merits with respect to his “intent” case to entitle him to injunctive relief.

In addition, Baxter is likely to succeed on the alternative showing of a §3604 violation. In Arlington Heights, the Seventh Circuit set out a four-pronged test for review of §3604 causes of action in which the conduct produced a discriminatory effect, but was taken without discriminatory intent. This is known as an “impact” analysis. Although the Arlington Heights court was faced with racial discrimination under the FHA, the analysis therein is equally applicable to the 1988 handicap amendments to the FHA, and will be applied by this Court in its review of Baxter's claims. The court held:

Four critical factors are discernible from previous cases. They are: (1) how strong is the plaintiff's showing of discriminatory effect; (2) is there some evidence of discriminatory intent, though not enough to satisfy the constitutional standard of Washington v. Davis, 426 U.S. 229 (1976); (3) what is the defendant's interest in taking the action complained of; and (4) does the plaintiff seek to compel the defendant to affirmatively provide housing for members of minority groups or merely to restrain the defendant from interfering with individual property owners who wish to provide such housing.

The court divided the first prong into two kinds of discriminatory effects which can be produced in a facially neutral housing decision. “The first occurs when that decision has a greater adverse impact on one [FHA protected] group than on another. The second is the effect which the decision has on the community involved....” In this action only the first kind of discriminatory effect is applicable. It is evident that the actions of the City adversely impacted handicapped individuals, persons who are HIV-positive, more than non-handicapped individuals. The intent of Baxter was to open a residence for homeless HIV-positive persons. This group of persons has been adversely impacted each day the residence remains unopened. This form of discrimination is strong because all of the persons adversely affected, with the exception of Baxter, himself, are members of an FHA protected group of handicapped individuals.

The second prong is the discriminatory intent present in the conduct. The court noted, however, that this factor is the least important of the four in an impact determination. As previously discussed, it is evident from the testimony of the City's own witnesses that fear of AIDS and a desire to keep persons with HIV out of the Belleville community were, at least, compelling factors in the City's actions.

The third prong is the interest of the defendant in taking the action which produced the alleged discriminatory impact. The City has asserted that it acted pursuant to its legitimate interest in zoning, particularly land use and public health and safety. In support thereof, the City asserts that Baxter failed to demonstrate that he had the background to operate this facility or that he had a firm plan or program for operating the facility.

The Court acknowledges the City's stated concerns, but finds them to have been a pretext. If the City's true concerns were with Baxter's qualifications or his lack of a firm program or plan, it could have continued the Zoning Board or Council hearings, or both, and given Baxter an opportunity to respond to these concerns. The evidence, however, was substantial that both the Zoning Board and the City Council focused on the perceived threat of HIV and voted accordingly. That the City's actions were based on fear of HIV, and not a legitimate zoning interest, is further supported by the fact that although the two 6th ward aldermen were in favor of the special use permit and moved for its passage, they were out-voted by the Council. The City's witnesses, Baum and Mabry, both testified that they could not recall that ever happening before. Furthermore, no zoning ordinance was cited by the City as a basis for its action.

The final prong of the Arlington Heights analysis is the nature of the relief which the plaintiff seeks. Baxter is not seeking to compel the City to build public housing for HIV-positive persons, he seeks to be allowed to use available housing provided by him exclusively for a residence for this handicapped group.

Under the Arlington Heights analysis, the Court finds that plaintiff is likely to succeed on the merits of his impact claim.

4. Exclusion Pursuant to §3604(f)(9)

The City asserts that its actions did not violate the FHA because they were made in accordance with the provisions of §3604(f)(9). That section provides: “(9) Nothing in this subsection requires that a dwelling be made available to an individual whose tenancy would constitute a direct threat to the health or safety of other individuals or whose tenancy would result in substantial physical damage to the property of others.” The City contends that Our Place constitutes a direct threat to the health or safety of others. In support thereof the City cites the fact that 301 South Illinois is across the street from a junior high school and near a grade school. In addition, the City focuses on the fact that HIV can be transmitted by illegal drug users, a group specifically excluded from the definition of handicap under §3602(h).

The Court has found that the scientific and medical authority is that HIV-positive persons pose no risk of transmission to the community at large. The City has asserted that the risk of secondary infections, to which the HIV-infected individual is subject, pose a substantial health risk. However, of the secondary infections, only MAI [microbacterium avian intracellular, which is related to tuberculosis] is transmissible to the community at large. Standing alone, this is an insufficient health concern to warrant the City's refusal to allow Baxter's special use under the exclusion of §3604(f)(9). Furthermore, the fear that intravenous drug users would pose a threat to the community, under the facts of this case, is unfounded. Baxter testified that he would, through a screening process, not accept current illegal drug users as residents at Our Place. Therefore, the Court finds that the exclusions of §3604(f)(9) do not support the City's actions.

Conclusions

1. The defendant, City of Belleville, is hereby preliminarily RESTRAINED and ENJOINED from refusing to issue to plaintiff, Charles Baxter, a special use permit for the residence at 301 South Illinois Street as a residence for HIV-infected persons.

2. The City of Belleville may establish reasonable restrictions as related to the issues of sanitation and non-admission of current illegal drug users as residents as conditions of said special use permit.

Notes

The previous case demonstrated how the Fair Housing Act applies generally to overt discrimination. After the deinstitutionalization movement, myths and stereotypes about individuals with disabilities who were moving into community arrangements such as group homes also resulted in some attitudinal discrimination. This took the form of denying special use permits for such properties. This issue is discussed to a greater extent in Section E later in this chapter.

Problems

1. Associational Disabilities: In Chapter 2, which sets out the major requirements for protection under the major substantive statutes, it is noted that individuals who are associated with someone with a disability are protected against discrimination under the Fair Housing Act. In fact, the Baxter decision involved associational disability protection. Would it violate the FHA to discriminate against gay men because it is believed that they are likely to be HIV positive? Poff v. Caro, 228 N.J. Super. 380, 549 A.2d 900 (1987).

2. Danger to Others: The Baxter case illustrates that the Fair Housing Act does not provide protection for individuals who pose a direct threat to the health or safety of others or whose tenancy would result in substantial physical damage to the property of others. 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(9). This case illustrates the general judicial consensus that discrimination in housing based on HIV status is impermissible because generally there is no risk. Would it be permissible for an apartment complex owner to prohibit individuals with HIV from using the apartment complex swimming pool? James Robinson, Houstonian with AIDS Files Federal Fair Housing Complaint, HOUSTON CHRONICLE, Aug. 3, 1994, at A23.

3. Alcohol and Drug Use: Individuals who are currently illegally using or addicted to controlled substances are not considered “handicapped” within the FHA. Housing specifically designed for recovering drug addicts and alcoholics, however, would be treated differently. Would it be legal for a private apartment complex to require prospective tenants to submit to drug tests? What about a governmental agency? M.R. Kropko, Tenants Must Submit to Drug Tests, HOUSTON CHRONICLE, Aug. 3, 1994, at A5.

4. Disclosure Requirements. Would a state law requiring realtors and sellers or lessors of housing to disclose any material fact that they know or should know about housing mean that the prior realtor, seller, or lessor must disclose that the prior occupant had HIV? Would such a law violate the Fair Housing Act? See Ralph Bivins, Realtors Seeking Relief From Thorny AIDS Issue, HOUSTON CHRONICLE, March 11, 1988, at A32.

5. HIV and AIDS and the Definition of “Handicap/Disability.” The Baxter case does not dwell on whether the residents meet the definition of “handicap” under the Fair Housing Act, noting that “it is clear from its legislative history that Congress intended to include ... those who are HIV-positive.” The Sutton Court analysis, narrowing the definition under the ADA, could have been applied in housing cases, although it was more often applied in employment cases after 1999. The ADA Amendments Act of 2008, which returned the broader definition, would probably mean that HIV would today still be considered a “handicap” under the Fair Housing Act and under the ADA and Section 504 as they apply to housing. Would the conditions (such as post traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) and drug and alcohol addiction) in the Hypothetical Problem be covered, even under the 2008 amendments?

6. Greater Awareness About HIV. The Baxter case was decided in 1989 at an early point in the public awareness of AIDS and HIV and their transmissibility. Is it more likely today that there would be less stereotype and prejudice in a case like this?

D. Reasonable Accommodation

Like the Rehabilitation Act and the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Fair Housing Act contemplates within its nondiscrimination prohibition that those entities subject to the Fair Housing Act provisions shall make reasonable accommodations. 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(3)(A) & (B). This may mean waiver of certain rules or adjustment of requirements. The following cases illustrate some of the types of accommodations the courts have considered in the context of housing.

[1] Parking

Shapiro v. Cadman Towers, Inc.

844 F. Supp. 116 (E.D.N.Y. 1994)

SIFTON, DISTRICT JUDGE:

Background

Plaintiff, Phyllis Shapiro, is a guidance counselor at Middle School 88 in Brooklyn and a resident of Cadman Towers, a residential complex located on the edge of the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn, New York. In 1975, plaintiff was diagnosed as suffering from multiple sclerosis. Multiple sclerosis is a chronic, progressive disease of the central nervous system, which primarily affects young women. The cause of multiple sclerosis and its cure remain unknown. Its symptoms include physical weakness, difficulty in walking, loss of balance and coordination, visual disturbance, fatigue, loss of stamina and severe headaches. Through the years and at different times, plaintiff has displayed a number of these symptoms, particularly those relating to her motor skills. The onset of these symptoms, their frequency, and severity are unpredictable, although there are some warnings of their onset. In plaintiff's case, the illness has followed a “relapsing progressive” course, meaning a pattern of progressive deterioration which in the course of time will likely totally disable her.

[The court describes the challenges the plaintiff has with bladder control because of her condition and the serious consequences of either living with incontinence or facing surgery if she is not able to park near her apartment. ]

Although plaintiff's condition is slowly deteriorating, the regularity and intensity of her symptoms fluctuate. During good periods, plaintiff is able to walk by herself for short distances on level ground. At other times, however, she can only walk with the assistance of a cane or a wheelchair. In her workplace, plaintiff utilizes a motorized scooter, particularly as she tires in the afternoon. Like other multiple sclerosis patients, plaintiff's condition is aggravated by emotional stress and by extreme temperatures occurring during winter or summer. Also like other patients, plaintiff is periodically subject to episodes in which she experiences near or total paralysis, which so far do not last long.

Plaintiff employs her own car, a present from her mother, to get to work. Her attempts to use public transportation have been unsuccessful. She relies exclusively on her car for transportation beyond the immediate proximity of her apartment, except during such episodes when she cannot drive, when she uses a car service. In July of 1992, plaintiff received a special handicapped parking identification from the New York City Department of Transportation, which allows her to park at parking meters without paying and exempts her from the City's alternate side of the street parking rules.

Plaintiff currently parks her car on the street in Brooklyn Heights. Because plaintiff's apartment building is on the edge of residential Brooklyn Heights, next to the downtown commercial area, plaintiff must, at least until late evening, compete with both residential and nonresidential car owners to find a space. She must then walk from the parking place on the street to her apartment building with greater or lesser difficulty depending on the weather, time of day, whether the walk is uphill or downhill and the distance. At the moment, in New York's most severe recent winter, the dangers of the walk are aggravated due to icy conditions. Until recently, plaintiff's best hope of a spot was on a one block street named Monroe Place just south of her apartment building where she can take advantage of her exemption from alternate side of the street parking rules. However, other drivers, including officials employed at or visiting the courthouse on Monroe Place of the Appellate Division, Second Department, who also enjoy exemption from the City's parking rules, compete with her for this space until they leave in the evening. Moreover, the parking is adjacent to one- and two-family brownstones, one resident of which, plaintiff credibly testified, has threatened her with reprisals if she continues to interfere with the street cleaning schedule of his neighborhood. As a result of these problems, it has, on occasion, taken plaintiff as much as forty-five minutes to find a parking space, and her incontinence has forced her to relieve herself on the street or in the car. On other occasions, as both plaintiff and an employee of her building's security service called by the defendants testified, she has arrived at the building lobby in such distress as to have to use a lavatory in the lobby to relieve herself. Once plaintiff reaches her apartment she describes herself as feeling on occasion “like a prisoner,” since the problems of losing her spot and having to find another at a late hour are too daunting to face.

Cadman Towers consists of two buildings located around the corner from each other—one at 101 Clark Street (“101 Clark”) and the other at 10 Clinton Street (“10 Clinton”). There are approximately half as many parking spaces in the complex as there are apartments. 101 Clark has 302 apartments and 64 indoor parking spaces, and 10 Clinton has 121 apartments and 136 indoor parking spaces. The parking rate at either location at Cadman Towers is approximately $90 a month plus tax, whereas the nearest commercial parking in the neighborhood is $275 a month.

Due to the disparity in numbers between apartments and parking spaces, the cooperative has in the past generally allocated spaces on a first come/first served basis and required users of parking spaces to live in one of the two buildings and residents to enjoy no more than one parking space per apartment. There are, however, exceptions to this general policy. Six shareholders have two spaces. The explanation for this given by the Board's president is that the six got these spaces during a period when there was low demand. At least one elderly resident is allowed to let her son, who does not live with her, use her space, apparently because she does not drive and her son, on occasion, does errands for her. In the past, a resident with severe emphysema was given a parking space without regard for the waiting list and then accommodated to the extent of being allowed to offer a $1,000 reward for a space closer to his apartment in contravention of the usual policy prohibiting the sale of parking spaces. Also excepted from the first come/first served, residents-only policy are three spaces given without charge to building employees as part of the employees' compensation.

When the first come/first served policy is followed, the resident's name is placed on a waiting list, and when a parking space is awarded, the resident may use the space until he or she vacates the apartment. To obtain a spot on the waiting list, residents are required to communicate their desire to be placed on such list in writing and are placed on the list as of the date their letter is received.... The restrictions and the procedure to be followed in requesting a space are spelled out in a building guide, the Cadman Towers Handbook, which is supposed to be provided free to all residents upon taking up residency.

In September of 1989, plaintiff applied to buy an apartment in the complex. At the time, she informed the building management and Board that she suffered from multiple sclerosis and further checked a box on the application form indicating that she would be seeking a parking space. Plaintiff claims not to have been informed that there was a waiting list for these spaces and does not recall receiving the building guide containing the parking space application procedures. Defendants do not consider the application to buy an apartment, even when completed as plaintiff completed it, to be an application to be placed on the waiting list for a parking space.

In June of 1990, plaintiff purchased her apartment at 101 Clark and has resided there since that time. On two occasions in February and March of 1992, plaintiff called the property manager for the complex and requested a parking space in 101 Clark due to her handicap. Plaintiff was informed that she would not be given a space and that her name would have to go on the waiting list. On March 25, 1992, plaintiff renewed her request for an immediate parking space by letter. The letter was written by plaintiff's brother, a lawyer, and contained information regarding plaintiff's handicap. Defendants again denied plaintiff's request. On April 14, plaintiff submitted another letter, this time written by her present counsel. The Board denied this request as well.

At the hearing before the undersigned, defendant Levy testified that the principal reason for denying plaintiff's application was the Board's concern with maintaining the integrity of the waiting lists which the Board felt would be threatened by any type of exception. In addition, it appears clear that the Board was suspicious of plaintiff's handicap. This suspicion remained unexamined, that is, no request for additional medical information or physical examination was made by the Board or any of its members, and Board members, like a number of building residents who testified at trial, confined themselves to remarking that they had not noticed that plaintiff had difficulty walking. (A witness at trial testified that “she seemed normal to me.” Plaintiff, in an unrelated response to cross-examination by defendants' counsel at the hearing, gave the appropriate answer to these comments: that discrimination against the handicapped often begins with the thought that she looks just like me—that she's normal—when in fact the handicapped person is in some significant respect different. Prejudice, it bears recalling, includes not just mistreating another because of the difference of her outward appearance but also assuming others are the same because of their appearance, when they are not.) Another ground for the Board's suspicions and for issues raised about plaintiff's credibility at the hearing were questions about her candor in asking for a two-bedroom apartment in her initial application because of a need for a 24-hour-a-day attendant as a result of her progressive disease. So far plaintiff has had an attendant with her only when suffering from near or total paralysis. Given the dire prognosis plaintiff has been given by her doctors, it is not at all incredible that she has and will face the need for a round-the-clock companion, and in fact a companion will undoubtedly in the future be called upon more and more regularly to share plaintiff's living space.

After receiving the letter from plaintiff's brother and after consulting with their own counsel, the Board took the position that any duty to accommodate plaintiff's disability would only come into being at the time she was awarded a parking space, and not before. As expressed by defendant Levy, the Board's position was and remains that no reasonable accommodation is due plaintiff at the waiting list stage and that she must wait the same number of years as a nonhandicapped tenant before she obtains a space. When she is awarded a space, the Board then appears to have in mind considering whether existing spaces should be rearranged so as to place plaintiff's space in 101 Clark rather than in 10 Clinton.

Discussion

42 U.S.C. §3613(c) provides that, in a civil action under the provisions of the FHAA, the court may grant as relief any permanent or temporary injunction “or other such order (including an order enjoining the defendants from engaging in such practice or ordering such affirmative action as may be appropriate).”

In order for a preliminary injunction to issue, plaintiff must demonstrate (1) irreparable harm and (2) either (a) a likelihood of success on the merits or (b) sufficiently serious questions going to the merits to make them fair ground for litigation and a balance of hardships tipping decidedly toward the party requesting the preliminary relief. Irreparable harm must be shown to be imminent, not remote or speculative, and the injury must be such that it cannot be fully remedied by monetary damages.

Plaintiff easily meets the first requirement for a preliminary injunction, namely, the likelihood of irreparable harm should the injunction not issue. As a patient suffering from multiple sclerosis, plaintiff is subject to an incurable disease that gradually and progressively saps her strength and interferes with her balance and bodily functions. Without a parking space in her building, plaintiff is subjected to risks of injury, infection, and humiliation substantially different in kind and magnitude from the inconveniences the nonhandicapped driver faces in finding parking on the City's streets. Plaintiff's disease makes her a candidate for accidental loss of balance, particularly during the winter season when her condition is aggravated. In addition, her urinary dysfunction results in episodes of embarrassing humiliation and discomfort which could be significantly reduced were she allowed to park indoors. The inconvenience suffered by a typical city resident forced to deice the car after a winter snowstorm is mild when compared to the discomfort, stress, and ensuing fatigue experienced by plaintiff when faced with the same task. Under these situations, it is clear that plaintiff has met her task of demonstrating a likelihood of irreparable harm were her exclusion from parking in the building allowed to continue during the pendency of this litigation.

An analysis of plaintiff's likelihood of success on the merits requires a preliminary discussion of the statutory framework within which plaintiff brings her action. The FHAA was passed by Congress in 1988 with the stated purpose of (1) creating an administrative system to enforce the nation's housing discrimination laws, (2) extending the principle of equal opportunity to handicapped individuals, and (3) extending these civil rights protections to families with children.... Section 3604(f)(2) forbids discriminat[ion] against any person in the terms, conditions, or privileges of sale or rental of a dwelling, or in the provision of services or facilities in connection with such dwelling, because of a handicap of ... that person.... Section 3604(f)(3) further defines discrimination as including

a refusal to make reasonable accommodations in rules, policies, practices, or services, when such accommodations may be necessary to afford such person equal opportunity to use and enjoy a dwelling....

Under the 1988 amendments, a person believing herself to be the target of a discriminatory practice under the Fair Housing Act is entitled to file a complaint with the Secretary of HUD. Upon receiving the complaint, the Secretary is to conduct an investigation, and to attempt conciliation. If a conciliation cannot be attained, the Secretary is to make a determination as to whether reasonable cause exists to believe that a discriminatory housing practice has occurred. If the Secretary believes that discrimination has occurred, he is instructed to issue a charge on behalf of the aggrieved party. Such a finding and charge have been issued in this case. The parties then have the option to elect to bring the proceeding before an administrative judge or commence an action in a federal district court. In this case, plaintiff elected to have her case heard in this Court. [T]he Secretary then authorizes the Attorney General to commence a proceeding on the aggrieved individual's behalf.

42 U.S.C. §3613(a)(1) also allows an aggrieved person to commence a civil action in an appropriate United States district court or state court no later than two years after the occurrence of the discriminatory housing practice. Because of plaintiff's need for immediate relief, she has filed this action without waiting for the Attorney General to commence hers. The Justice Department filed its action shortly thereafter.

[There is not] much question that defendants' first come/first served policy is a rule, policy, or practice within the meaning of the FHAA and that indoor parking is part of the services and facilities provided at plaintiff's building.

In a case such as this, plaintiff's need to show a likelihood of success on the merits would usually translate into demonstrating that defendants had a duty to reasonably accommodate her request for a parking space and that no such reasonable accommodation was made. In the present case, however, defendants have conceded that they made no attempt at an accommodation, and the central issue for resolution remains only the existence of defendants' duty.

Defendants appear to make the argument that, because plaintiff has not yet made it to the top of the list, when she would be entitled to a parking space under the building's existing regulations, indoor parking is not yet part of the services and facilities provided “in connection with plaintiff's dwelling.” Such an argument, however, ignores the fact that parking space at Cadman Towers is something all shareholders, including Ms. Shapiro, own and control in common as members of the cooperative corporation. The first come/first served policy is not, in other words, a creature of the lease to Ms. Shapiro's apartment or her contract of sale but of the building's rules and regulations which may be changed by the appropriate vote of all the members of the cooperative under the building's by-laws.

The fact that the rules and regulations are longstanding does not exempt them from the FHAA....

Defendants also appear to argue that the fact that there are fewer parking spaces than apartments or “dwellings” also somehow severs the connection between the dwellings and the parking spaces. Although the House Report was correct in noting that the phrase “reasonable accommodation” has been much written about in connection with other types of discrimination and discrimination against the handicapped in other areas, there is remarkably little authority on its meaning and requirements in a housing situation such as the one faced here, involving the allocation of a scarce good among handicapped and nonhandicapped individuals. Nevertheless, it seems common sense that in a situation of scarcity each individual has a connection with the scarce good.

Case law interpreting the “reasonable accommodation” language in the provisions of the FHAA has analogized the language to similar provisions in the Federal Rehabilitation Act.

As with other agencies under the Rehabilitation Act, HUD was given the power to promulgate regulations instituting the provisions of the Fair Housing Act. 24 C.F.R. §100.204(b) was the regulation specifically promulgated by HUD to implement the “reasonable accommodation” requirements of section 3604. After restating the language of the statute, the regulation proceeds to give two examples of a reasonable accommodation. The first involves a blind applicant for rental housing who wished to keep her seeing eye dog in a building with a “no pets” policy. The example states that allowing the handicapped individual to keep her dog would be a “reasonable accommodation” within the meaning of the regulation.

The second example given in section 100.204 involves a handicapped resident of a building in need of a specific parking space. Given the similarities between the example and the current case, the example is reproduced here in its entirety:

Progress Gardens is a 300 unit apartment complex with 450 parking spaces which are available to tenants and guests of Progress Gardens on a first come first served basis. John applies for housing in Prospect Gardens. John is mobility impaired and is unable to walk more than a short distance and therefore requests that a parking space near his unit be reserved for him so he will not have to walk very far to get to his apartment. It is a violation of §100.204 for the owner or manager to refuse to make this accommodation. Without a reserved space, John might be unable to live in Progress Gardens at all or, when he has to park in a space far from his unit, might have difficulty getting from his car to his apartment unit. The accommodation therefore is necessary to afford John an equal opportunity to use and enjoy a dwelling. The accommodation is reasonable because it is feasible and practical under the circumstances.

In their brief, defendants point out that the example in section 100.204 and [a] decision by the ALJ both deal with situations where there are sufficient parking spaces for all the residents of the building so that the only issue was how best to apportion the spaces. They argue that in this case, by way of contrast, there is a condition of scarcity with insufficient spaces for all residents.

Although there are clear differences between the example given in the CFR and the present fact situation, these are differences of degree rather than of kind. It is not correct to state that the current problem deals with the allocation of scarce goods, whereas the situation in the CFR does not. The CFR example also clearly deals with a scarce good, namely, the valued parking spaces nearest the apartments. Giving the best spaces to handicapped individuals will clearly inconvenience those nonhandicapped individuals who also prize them. However, for the nonhandicapped individuals the prime parking spaces are a convenience, whereas for the handicapped they are instrumental to living as close to normal lives as possible.

In the situation at bar the good whose distribution is at issue is the parking space itself, not the best parking spaces. Although defendants correctly point out that the good in question here is more prized by the nonhandicapped than the good in the CFR example (i.e., nonhandicapped individuals value a parking space over no parking space far more than they value a prime parking space over a bad one), this is, in terms of the existence of a duty to accommodate, irrelevant as the handicapped will have the same preferences as the nonhandicapped, only of a far more intense degree due to their acute need (and not simple desire) for the spots. In other words, the fact that the stakes are higher in this situation is beside the point, as they are higher for everyone. Everyone has, as a result of his or her membership in the cooperative, a connection with the building's parking space which interests each to a different degree.

Defendants' only legal support for their position is found in cases involving seniority rights established under collective bargaining agreements between management and labor. Those cases are distinguishable both factually and legally. Factually, defendants' first come/first served policy is not a creature of contract. Nor does it fulfill any national goal recognized by statute. In a Title VII case involving allegations of religious discrimination, the Court refused to disturb the seniority system and force some workers to work for others on religious holidays on the ground that “[c]ollective bargaining, aimed at effecting workable and enforceable agreements between management and labor, lies at the core of our national policy, and seniority provisions are universally included in these contracts.” The Court further noted that Title VII itself provides that a bona fide seniority system will not be unlawful under its provisions.

In another representative case, an asthmatic employee of the post office sued under the Rehabilitation Act, claiming that the post office refused to accommodate his handicap by giving him “permanent light duty” jobs. The court noted that the language of the Rehabilitation Act only prohibits discrimination against the individual when he is “otherwise qualified.” The court held that under the seniority system embodied in the collective bargaining agreement, plaintiff had not worked the number of years that would qualify him for the position and that he was, thus, not “otherwise qualified” for the position.

Accordingly, based on the statute, the legislative history, case law, and regulations promulgated by HUD and mindful of the fact that this chapter “is to be construed generously to ensure the prompt and effective elimination of all traces of discrimination within the housing field,” I conclude that a “reasonable accommodation” of plaintiff's needs by reason of her handicap will in all probability require modification of defendants' first come/first served policy. In insisting that the policy of first come/first served remain inviolable whatever plaintiff's handicap and needs, defendants display the frame of mind which Congress sought to alter by requiring reasonable accommodations of the needs of the handicapped.

Although plaintiff has demonstrated a clear likelihood of success in establishing that defendants violated the FHAA, it would be inappropriate at this early point in the litigation to determine in any detail the manner in which defendants should accommodate those of its residents who are handicapped. Such a finding at this point would be an unnecessary judicial intrusion into the affairs of a private entity, despite the fact that defendants up to now appear to have given this aspect of its affairs little thought. As noted, defendants up to now have refused to make any accommodation. It is expected that this ruling will stimulate them to consider the available options by which they may fulfill their statutory duties.

Although this Court will not at this point determine what measures may ultimately prove necessary to accommodate plaintiff's handicap in a reasonable fashion, this is not an obstacle to ruling that plaintiff must in the interim be given the space she requires until such time as the trial of this matter is concluded or another reasonable accommodation is worked out. Defendants have not suggested that plaintiff, as one out of over 400 members of her cooperative, is making a demand out of line with the ratio of handicapped to nonhandicapped drivers in New York City. Nor have they suggested that she must compete with other handicapped drivers for the space or that she is not entitled to priority among them. Defendants have failed to propose other solutions, and plaintiff's irreparable harm outweighs any harm to defendants in meeting plaintiff's immediate needs.

Accordingly, plaintiff's motion for a preliminary injunction is granted, and defendants are hereby enjoined from refusing to provide plaintiff with a parking space on the lobby/ground floor of Cadman Towers' garage at 101 Clark Street in Brooklyn, New York, in reasonable proximity to the building lobby.

Notes and Questions

1. The facts in the previous case indicate that the Board was “suspicious of plaintiff's handicap.” This highlights the challenge of “hidden” disabilities. A person who does not look like there is a disability may not seem to need accommodations. This can be true for mental illness, diabetes, epilepsy, fibromyalgia, and other conditions. What kinds of documentation should Phyllis Shapiro be required to present to verify that she has a disability entitling her to protection under the Fair Housing Act, including reasonable accommodations? Is she more likely to be covered today than before the ADA Amendments Act of 2008?

2. The Casey Martin case in Chapter 4 also involves a case where documentation of his condition would probably be required because he is seeking a significant exception to the rule, as is the case with the Shapiro situation. To what extent might decision makers be denying accommodations or exceptions because they are concerned about opening the floodgates? In the case of golf tournaments, will the golfer with a mild heart condition now want a cart for a local tournament that does not allow them? If Cadman Towers gives Phyllis Shapiro a parking space (and one close to the entrance) are there concerns that many other residents will now ask for exceptions? In what situations might these concerns be legitimate? Does the potential for others to seek the same accommodation affect whether it would be unduly burdensome to grant an exception?

3. Parking issues particularly in urban areas can be an issue in housing settings. The issues that have been raised in cases include priority parking (as addressed in Shapiro), the location of parking spaces, and even issues related to parking fees. A number of judicial decisions have addressed these issues. Consistent in these rulings is the importance of making individualized decisions based on the facts. For example, in Jankowski Lee & Associates v. Cisneros, 91 F.3d 891 (7th Cir. 1996), an FHA violation was found when an apartment complex did not investigate the extent of the tenant's disability and denied the request for a close parking space. One decision found that parking spaces constituted facilities, not a service, and the request to provide an accessible space should be treated as a modification of a facility, not a request for an accommodation. Com. ex rel. Fair Housing Bd. v. Windsor Plaza Condominium Ass'n, Inc., 289 Va. 34, 768 S.E.2d 79 (2014).

Problems

1. Should a city be required to allow residents to put paved parking spaces in front of their homes to facilitate access? Trovato v. City of Manchester, 992 F. Supp. 493 (D.N.H. 1997) (holding that failure to allow such an exemption violates the FHA).

2. Must parking ever be provided free of charge? Hubbard v. Samson Mgt. Corp., 994 F. Supp. 187 (S.D.N.Y. 1998) (FHA might required apartment complex that has free unreserved parking to provide some reserved spaces without charge); United States v. California Mobile Home Park Management Co., 29 F.3d 1413 (9th Cir. 1994) (requiring waiver of daily parking fee for frequent home health care aide who provided daily services for a child with a respiratory disease).

[2] Accommodating Mental Illness and Substance Abuse

The challenges for individuals with mental illness in housing settings are many. The cases that follow demonstrate some of the issues with respect to reasonable accommodations and discrimination. The challenge may be that where an individual does not have access to adequate mental health treatment (which may be due to unemployment because of mental illness), the behavior may become unacceptable. These individuals may be evicted from housing as a result. There is evidence that individuals with mental illness are disproportionately represented in the homeless population. For a discussion of the relationship of various laws, see Laura Rothstein, Protections for Persons with Mental Disabilities: Americans with Disabilities Act and Related Federal and State Law, Chapter 9 in LAW, MENTAL HEALTH, AND MENTAL DISORDER (Bruce D. Sales & Daniel W. Shuman eds., Brooks/Cole Publishing Co. 1996).

The following case demonstrates one court's approach to excusing misconduct related to mental illness.

City Wide Associates v. Penfield

409 Mass. 140, 564 N.E. 2d 1003 (1991)

O'CONNOR, JUSTICE:

[This case involved a 77-year-old tenant who suffered from a serious mental disability manifested by hearing voices from the walls of her apartment. The tenant hit the walls with a broom or stick, threw objects or water at the walls in response to these hallucinations. Some nicks and gouges and water damage have resulted in the amount of approximately $519. This is a federal housing project, so §504 of the Rehabilitation Act was applied.]

“The Supreme Court [has] struck a balance between the statutory rights of the handicapped to be integrated into society and the legitimate interests of federal grantees in preserving the integrity of their programs: while a grantee need not be required to make ‘fundamental’ or ‘substantial’ modifications to accommodate the handicapped, it may be required to make ‘reasonable’ ones.”

In this case, the judge was confronted with the question whether the landlord's obligation under §504 reasonably to accommodate the tenant's mental illness and resulting damage to the apartment required the landlord to permit the tenant to continue to occupy the apartment despite the tenant's violation of the lease provision prohibiting defacement or damaging of the dwelling unit. [The tenant had struck the walls with a broom.] The judge reasoned that “[b]ecause the tenant pleads unlawful discrimination as an affirmative defense the burden is on her to prove her claim. As with any other discrimination claim, the burden is on the tenant to prove a prima facie case of discrimination. The burden of production (but not the ultimate burden of persuasion) then shifts to the respondent to prove that the challenged act was not discriminatory.” Neither the landlord nor the tenant contests that allocation of the burdens of production of evidence and persuasion.

According to the judge's memorandum, the tenant met her burdens of production and persuasion by proposing a modification of her obligations under the tenancy agreement which the judge concluded would constitute a “reasonable accommodation” of the tenant's handicap and thus would entitle her to continued possession at least in the absence of further significant damage. The proposal was that the landlord would “forbear from further eviction steps (presumably, as long as the tenant's conduct does not change substantially) to give her an opportunity to pursue a program of outreach and counselling.” This, the judge concluded, was “a reasonable step as long as more substantial damage is not caused. The [landlord] has not shown that it would be greatly prejudiced by holding off further and giving the tenant further opportunity to find the assistance needed to address the problem.” In arriving at his conclusion that the tenant was “qualified” to remain in the unit “absent a substantial change in circumstances,” the judge expressly took into account the cost of the damage caused by the tenant due to her mental illness, which he characterized as “small” (less than one month's rent), the fact that, under the contract between the landlord and HAP, the landlord was entitled to reimbursement of up to two months rent for tenant-caused damage, and the lack of evidence that other tenants were affected by the defendant tenant's conduct.

Whether a tenant's proposed accommodation of a disability is “reasonable” within the meaning of the relevant decisions is not susceptible of precise measurement, but we are persuaded that the judge exercised proper judgment in this case. Indeed, the landlord's only argument that meets the requirements of [state law] is that the tenant failed to show that she would cooperate with any program involving counselling or medication or otherwise take steps to correct the mental condition that prompted her destructive conduct. Even so, given the superficiality of the damage, the reimbursement available to the landlord, as found by the judge, and the absence of evidence of adverse impact on other tenants, we agree with the judge that, in the absence of further significant damage, the tenant is “otherwise qualified” under §504, and that eviction on this record would be discriminatory and therefore unlawful.

Problems

1. Is it permissible for landlords to ask prospective tenants about prior drug use? What about prior criminal records that might relate to drugs? Campbell v. Minneapolis Pub. Hous. Auth., 175 F.R.D. 531 (D. Minn. 1997) (housing applicant could not be asked about prior drug use).

2. Mr. A suffers from manic depression and applies to rent an apartment at Pleasant Acres Apartment Complex in Big City, USA. His application noted his mental condition, and he had excellent references and a medical report stating that he could live in a socially responsible manner. His application, however, was denied. The apartment manager had learned of several criminal acts by Mr. A that had occurred over the four years preceding his application, including deflating a government official's car tires, spray-painting a police car, and making a bomb threat. Is the action by Pleasant Acres a violation of the FHA? Should the rental application be permitted to include questions about mental history? If it were found that such questions were impermissible under the FHA, would Mr. A be likely to win an injunction against denying his apartment rental? Quaker Hill Place v. Saville, 523 A.2d 947 (Del. Super. 1987).

[3] Accommodations for Assistance or Service Animals

Individuals with a range of disabilities often have an animal to assist or provide support in some other way. These situations can raise a variety of issues, including whether the individual has a disability (to be entitled to nondiscrimination or accommodation), whether the individual is otherwise qualified (including whether the animal presents a danger to safety or health or is disruptive in some way), and whether the modification of a policy is reasonable. The following case is one of the early decision addressing this issue.

Crossroads Apartments Ass'n v. LeBoo

152 Misc. 2d 830, 578 N.Y.S.2d 1004 (City Ct. 1991)

JOHN R. SCHWARTZ, JUDGE:

Factual Background

The tenant, Kenneth LeBoo, is a forty-nine year old male with a long history of mental illness dating back to the late 1960's. His mental condition has been diagnosed as panic disorder with agoraphobia, mixed personality disorder, and chronic anxiety with a history of episodic alcohol abuse. The landlord, Crossroads, is an apartment complex located within the City of Rochester, New York, which consists of 518 residential apartment units. 496 of these apartment units are subject to a federally-funded Section 8 Housing Assistance Payment Contract. LeBoo has been a tenant since 1978, pursuant to a written lease and receives Section 8 assistance. No real problems existed between the parties until LeBoo obtained the subject cat in the spring of 1990. Mr. LeBoo alleges he acquired the cat to help alleviate his intense feeling of loneliness, anxiety and depression, which are daily manifestations of his mental illness.

Upon discovering the cat in LeBoo's apartment, Crossroads commenced the instant proceeding. After brief discovery, both sides now move for summary judgment.

I.

New York Courts have long recognized the validity of “no-pet clauses” in leases, and harboring a pet when a lease contains a “no-pet clause” constitutes a substantial breach of the lease agreement. Acceptance of the rent over a period of time after discovery of the pet still does not render the “no-pet clause” unenforceable. Landlords may also selectively enforce the “no-pet clause.”

II.

LeBoo further urges this Court to determine as a matter of law that he has established that Crossroads has violated Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 and the Fair Housing Amendments Act of 1988. To support his claim, he submits three expert affidavits which state that LeBoo's cat is necessary for him to use and enjoy his apartment.

Crossroads, on the other hand, urges this Court to determine as a matter of law that LeBoo has not established even “prima facie” the necessity of his cat to assist him in coping with his mental illness. They also submit an affidavit of a psychiatrist.

To prove that Crossroads has violated both acts, LeBoo must demonstrate that: 1) he is handicapped; 2) he is otherwise qualified for the tenancy; 3) that because of his disability, it is necessary for him to keep the pet in order for him to use and enjoy the apartment; and 4) reasonable accommodations can be made to allow him to keep the pet.

First, LeBoo is a handicapped person. There is no dispute about that factual issue. Both parties' doctors diagnose him as having a mental illness that makes him disabled.

Second, he is an otherwise qualified person for tenancy except for the pet. “An otherwise qualified person is one who is able to meet all of the program's requirements in spite of his handicap.” LeBoo had lived at Crossroads twelve years without incident before he obtained his pet. Clearly, he meets all other criteria for tenancy, if not for the pet.

Third, LeBoo must prove that the pet is necessary for him to use and enjoy his apartment. To prevail on this issue, LeBoo must demonstrate that he has an emotional and psychological dependence on the cat which requires him to keep the cat in the apartment. To support his claim, LeBoo has submitted the affidavits of his treating psychiatrist, his clinical social worker, and a certified pet-assisted therapist. They all describe his mental illness, his course of treatment, and conclude that LeBoo receives therapeutic benefits from keeping and caring for his cat. Also, they conclude that the keeping of the cat assists him in his use and enjoyment of his apartment by helping him cope with the daily manifestations of his mental illness.

In opposition, Crossroads submits the affidavit of its psychiatrist who has seen LeBoo twice, examined all his relevant medical records, and concludes that there is “no significant clinical evidence that the cat is necessary or required for LeBoo to be able to fully use and enjoy his apartment.” He further concludes in his report that LeBoo was placed on the drug Prozac around the same time he acquired the cat and LeBoo's clinical course since taking Prozac has been slightly less tumultuous.

Based on these conflicting opinions, this is not an issue ripe for summary judgment. Genuine issues of fact exist as to whether this cat is necessary for LeBoo to use and enjoy his apartment. “If and when the Court reaches the conclusion that a genuine and substantial issue of fact is presented, such determination requires the denial of the application for summary judgment.” Here, there is a genuine triable issue of fact, namely, whether this cat is necessary for LeBoo to use and enjoy his apartment.

Fourth, can reasonable accommodations be made by Crossroads which would permit LeBoo to keep his cat? This also constitutes a question of fact. LeBoo alleges that allowing him to keep his cat would not result in any undue financial or operational hardship to Crossroads. He claims reasonable accommodations could be made to allow him to keep his cat.

However, accommodations which place “undue financial and administration burdens” on Crossroads would not be reasonable. The property manager of Crossroads, in her affidavit, states that the cat would cause an undue administrative burden, and would create health problems for other tenants. This affidavit creates a question of fact concerning this issue.

[The court denied the landlord's motion for summary judgment and struck the demand for jury trial.]

Problems

1. In LeBoo, documentation was presented to support the request for the accommodation. What kinds of documentation should be required both to demonstrate a covered “disability” and to justify the requested accommodation? How will this be addressed with respect to the concerns about the types and numbers of animals in Hypothetical Problem 8.1?

2. Would the courts be likely to allow pet deposits for assistance or support animals in an apartment complex that ordinarily does not permit pets? See, e.g., Intermountain Fair Housing Council v. CVE Falls Park, L.L.C., 2011 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 79144, 2011 WL 2945824 (D. Idaho 2011) (imposing security deposit for service animal impermissible under FHA); Fair Housing of the Dakotas, Inc. v. Goldmark Property Management, Inc., 778 F. Supp. 2d 1028 (D.N.D. 2011) (charging an animal fee without a clear explanation about when fees applied created triable issues about whether denial of fee waiver was pretext).

Notes

The issue of animals in housing as a disability accommodation received attention through Department of Justice regulations (for Title II and Title III) in 2010. Most housing is not subject to Title II (except in the context of zoning issues). The Department of Housing and Urban Development has not issued detailed regulations specific to animals in housing settings. There have, however, been a number of judicial decisions addressing the issue in a range of contexts. Under the ADA Titles II and III, the only animals required as accommodations are animals (only dogs and miniature horses) that are trained to perform a service. The documentation inquiries are quite limited.

The case law demonstrates that in the housing context, other animals would be allowed and these animals might be emotional support or comfort animals to help individuals cope with mental health challenges. In these cases, the courts have addressed a range of issues. All of the decisions demonstrate the expectation of an individualized assessment and a reluctance to accept blanket prohibitions. For example, prohibitions about animals' size or certain breeds such as pit bull dogs may require waivers on an individualized basis. See, e.g., Ajit Bhogaita v. Altamonte Heights Condominium Assn., Inc., 765 F.3d 1277 (11th Cir. 2014) (veteran with PTSD, chronic anxiety, and depression could pursue claim that modification of condo rule limiting pet size would affect his having an emotional support animal whose connection to the condition was documented by a physician); Chavez v. Aber, 51 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶34 (W.D. Tex. 2015) (allowing case to move forward when tenant requested pit bull dog as emotional support animal; lease had no-pets policy; landlord sought to evict her and denied lease renewal); Warren v. Delvista Towers Condominium Ass'n, Inc., 49 F. Supp. 3d 1082 (S.D. Fla. 2014) (denying motion to dismiss in case involving request to modify no pets policy; fact issues existed regarding direct threat to safety of others of emotional support dog and applying county ordinance banning pit bull dogs).

The courts have also addressed the issue of documentation to justify the accommodation. See, e.g., Anderson v. City of Blue Ash, 798 F.3d 338 (6th Cir. 2015) (miniature horse qualifies as service animal; was individually trained to do work and perform task of beneficial exercise in girl's backyard); DuBois v. Association of Apartment Owners of 2987 Kalakaua, 453 F.3d 1175 (9th Cir. 2006) (permissible to request additional medical information from condominium owner seeking exemption from no-pets rule; dog was permitted to live with owner temporarily); Meadowland Apartments v. Schumacher, 813 N.W.2d 618 (S.D. 2012) (tenant in federally subsidized apartment did not provide the information sufficient to request dog accommodation). One issue that would benefit from regulatory guidance is what training or certification can be required for animals as part of a request for an accommodation in a housing setting. See, e.g., In re Kenna Homes Co-op. Corp., 210 W. Va. 380, 557 S.E.2d 787 (2001) (cooperative housing project's regulation prohibiting animals except service animals provided such animals are properly trained, certified for the particular disability of the resident, and resident has certification of the disability from specializing doctor did not violate FHA as applied to residents seeking to keep dogs as a reasonable accommodation).

Even if the individual is to be allowed to have an animal as an accommodation, the owner must clean up after the animal, keep it under control, and ensure that it does not disturb others.

An issue that has arisen in the context of higher education is whether various types of campus housing are covered by the Fair Housing Act or only the ADA. The position of the Office of Housing and Urban Development is that most campus housing is subject to the FHA, but that has yet to be clearly resolved in the courts. The issue is important in terms of addressing what animals are to be allowed and what documentation can be required.

E. Structural Barriers

The Fair Housing Act incorporates two major requirements relating to structural modifications of premises. These relate to obligations with respect to existing facilities and those related to new construction. The requirements mandating that new construction meet certain specific design standards apply only to multifamily dwellings designed or constructed for first occupancy after March 13, 1991. 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(3)(C), (4)–(9); 24 C.F.R. §100.205. The specific design standards refer to features including entrances, common areas, doorways, environmental controls, bathrooms, and kitchens. Multifamily dwellings are those with four or more units. The applicable requirements depend on whether the structure has an elevator or not. Unlike the Rehabilitation Act and the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Fair Housing Act generally does not require the owner of an existing facility to do anything to retrofit to ensure physical access. In a landlord tenant setting, however, the FHA contemplates the requirement that the landlord allow the tenant to make alterations at the tenant's expense so long as the tenant will return the premises to their original condition after the tenancy.

Most judicial interpretation has arisen from the FHA requirements relating to structural modifications. Except for housing covered by some other federal or state statute, little is required by the FHA with respect to removing barriers in existing housing. The FHA, however, does require that individuals with disabilities be allowed to make their own structural modifications at their own expense in certain cases. The types of modifications usually are those relating to features such as ramps and railings for individuals with mobility impairments. As the following case illustrates, however, modifications for other types of conditions may be required. The following case also highlights the relationship of state law to these issues and the enforcement process.

Lincoln Realty Management Co. v. Pennsylvania Human Relations Commission

143 Pa. Commw. 54, 598 A.2d 594 (1991)

MCGINLEY, JUDGE:

Lincoln Realty Management Company (Lincoln), the manager of Audubon Court Apartments (Audubon), appeals an order of the Pennsylvania Human Relations Commission (Commission) issued August 28, 1990, as a result of a complaint filed with the Commission by Sally Atkinson (Atkinson), a tenant at Audubon. The Commission determined that Lincoln ejected Atkinson from her apartment solely because of her physical disability, and rejected any reasonable accommodations she proposed in violation of the provisions of the Pennsylvania Human Relations Act (Act).

Atkinson, who is extremely sensitive to a variety of chemicals and chemical products, entered into a one-year lease agreement for a unit in Audubon's Building C beginning in February, 1986. By letter dated May 6, 1986 Lincoln informed Atkinson that her lease would not be renewed for the upcoming year as Lincoln was unable to provide her with the special treatment and precautions her condition demanded. Atkinson did not vacate her apartment at the expiration of the lease term in February of 1987, and filed a complaint with the Commission. Additionally, on June 22, 1987, Atkinson obtained an injunction in the Montgomery County Court of Common Pleas enjoining Lincoln from using “any pest control substance, device or methodology not approved by [Atkinson], anywhere in the north side of building Unit C, and to provide 48 hours notice of any spray or ‘bomb’ application to any other building or grounds within 100 feet of building Unit C, until [Atkinson] no longer occupies her unit or 45 days from this date, whichever occurs first.” Lincoln has not repainted Building C and no pest control has been undertaken in the building since the commencement of Atkinson's tenancy.

A hearing was held before the Commission on June 14 and 15, 1990. At the hearing, Atkinson testified that she was diagnosed as suffering with multiple chemical sensitivity in June, 1984. Atkinson presented a letter from her physician which states that Atkinson is unable to tolerate the presence of various chemical compounds, including but not limited to certain pesticides and herbicides. Atkinson testified that conditions in Audubon were tolerable when she moved into her apartment.

The hearing examiner found that Atkinson is handicapped within the meaning of the Act, that she established a prima facie case of discrimination, and that Lincoln did not make reasonable accommodations for her, and that Lincoln did not demonstrate that making reasonable accommodations imposed an undue hardship. The hearing examiner set forth the following remedial measures:

1) Should Atkinson desire to do so, Lincoln shall permit Atkinson to install a kitchen ceiling fan in unit C-301 by a licensed electrician of her choice, subject to the approval of Lincoln, the cost to be borne by Atkinson, 2) Lincoln shall cause the dishwasher in unit C-301 to be removed and the pipes sealed to prevent odors from seeping into unit C-301, the cost to be borne by Lincoln. 3) Should Atkinson desire to do so, Lincoln shall permit Atkinson to install a washer and dryer in unit C-301, cost to be borne by Atkinson, 4) Lincoln shall install an exhaust fan in the laundry room of building C ... and install a control switch on the first floor level, the cost to be borne by Lincoln. 5) When deemed appropriate, Lincoln shall either paint or wallpaper the hallways of building C, and if painted, Lincoln shall use a less toxic paint product. Prior to painting, Lincoln shall discuss the choice of paint with Atkinson and allow Atkinson to submit the name of a recommended product for Lincoln's consideration. Any increased cost of a less toxic product or its application shall be borne by Lincoln. 6) Lincoln shall attempt pest control in and around building C by formatting a ... strategy which first strives to address any pest problem with the least toxic pesticide application possible. Lincoln shall discuss their plan with Atkinson well in advance of any actual treatments and give due consideration to any recommended course of action Atkinson may submit. Should either less toxic products or their application cost additional money, Lincoln shall bear the added costs. 7) Lincoln shall permit Atkinson to either cover her floors with tolerable floor coverings or leave them bare. The cost of personal floor coverings, if any are installed by Atkinson, shall be borne by Atkinson. When Atkinson vacates the unit, no additional cost shall be assessed by Lincoln for Atkinson's prior removal of carpeting. 8) Within 100 feet of building C, Lincoln shall attempt to implement an organic lawn care program, the cost thereof to be borne by Lincoln. 9) Lincoln shall provide to Atkinson at least two weeks notice of all pest treatments and lawn maintenance at Audubon which use toxic materials of any sort. Such notice shall include an accurate description of the scope of treatments and products to be used. 10) Lincoln shall continue to give Atkinson advance notice of all painting to be done in building C.

We now turn to the question of whether Lincoln did fail to reasonably accommodate Atkinson in the manner contemplated by federal law, and if so, whether the Commission's remedial order was proper. We note that the Commission derives its authority to order that reasonable accommodations be made after a finding of discrimination from Section 9(f) of the Act:

If, upon all the evidence at the hearing, the Commission shall find that a respondent has engaged in or is engaging in any unlawful discriminatory practice as defined in this act, the Commission shall state its findings of fact, and shall issue and cause to be served on such respondent an order requiring such respondent to cease and desist from such unlawful discriminatory practice and to take such affirmative action, including, but not limited to ... the making of reasonable accommodations ... as, in the judgement of the Commission, will effectuate the purposes of this act, and including a requirement for the report of the manner of compliance. Further, when fashioning an award, the Commission has broad discretion and its actions are entitled to deference by a reviewing court. The Commission's order will not be disturbed unless it can be shown that the order is a patent attempt to achieve ends other than can be fairly said to effectuate the policies of the Act.

The evidence adduced at the hearing reveals that Atkinson requested the following accommodations:

that she be allowed to have her carpets removed, that she be allowed to install a washer and dryer in her apartment at her own cost and with the agreement that she would restore the premises at the end of her tenancy, that she be allowed to install an exhaust fan in the laundry room at her own cost, the premises to be restored at the end of her tenancy, and that Lincoln paint with products that she could tolerate, with the understanding that she would make up the difference in the cost of the paint.

Atkinson also requested notification of painting and pesticide application and that Lincoln attempt use of the least toxic methodology of pest control. Atkinson presented a letter from Lincoln's attorney permitting Atkinson to remove the carpets provided Atkinson set up an escrow account in the amount equal to 50% of the replacement cost to facilitate restoring the apartment to its original condition. Atkinson also testified that Lincoln gave her permission to install an exhaust fan in her kitchen provided she used an electrician of Lincoln's choice, however, she decided not to have the fan installed after discovering that Lincoln's electrician charged more than the electricians she contacted. The testimony was contradictory on the point of whether Atkinson was notified of all painting and pesticide applications during her tenancy.

Lincoln asserts that it did not renew Atkinson's lease because Lincoln felt that it was unable to accommodate her. Norman Brodsky (Brodsky), President of Lincoln, testified that he considered Atkinson's letters requesting the use of least-toxic methods of pest control to be an attempt to “enter into the management realm of [the] complex.” Brodsky testified that he believed Atkinson was having a home built, and he decided that he “wouldn't do anything” until she was gone. Atkinson testified that Lincoln stopped treating for outdoor pests in the complex after she was harassed by one of the exterminators, but that this was not done at her request. Despite Lincoln's assertion of sympathy, Lincoln's policy amounted to sitting back and doing nothing. This is not the equivalent of making a reasonable accommodation. Lincoln did not work with Atkinson in making the reasonable accommodations which she did propose, as contemplated by the federal regulations.

However, the Commission's order directs Lincoln to make accommodations beyond those requested by Atkinson, at Lincoln's cost. Although the Commission has broad discretion in fashioning an award, and has the authority to order reasonable accommodations as set forth in Section 9(f) of the Act, it is unreasonable to expect Lincoln to make accommodations which Atkinson did not formally and reasonably request. In this regard certain necessary findings are absent from the record and, as a result, portions of the Commission's order are unsupported.

Certainly the portions of the order which direct Lincoln to give Atkinson notice of pesticide application and painting, proposed accommodations (9) and (10), fall within the spirit of the federal guidelines. Similarly, it is clear that if the federal guidelines are to apply, they require Lincoln to permit Atkinson to make modifications to her apartment at her own expense. This would include the directives that Atkinson be permitted to install a kitchen ceiling fan and a washer and dryer in the apartment at her own expense, proposed accommodations (1) and (3), both of which modifications she previously requested.

Concerning proposed accommodations (2), dishwasher removal, (4), laundry room exhaust fan, (5), painting, (6), pest control, and (8), organic lawn care, we vacate these portions of the Commission's order and remand for specific findings on whether Atkinson provided a reasonable description of these proposed modifications to Lincoln with any necessary assurances that modifications are to be made in a workmanlike manner, and whether Atkinson is willing to pay any increased costs resulting from these modifications, and if she is willing to restore the premises, reasonable wear and tear excepted.

As we have stated, 24 C.F.R. 100.203(a) permits the landlord to condition permission for a modification on a renter agreeing to restore the premises to the condition that existed before the modification, reasonable wear and tear excepted. The portion of the order dealing with carpet removal, proposed accommodation (7), is vacated and remanded for a determination of whether Lincoln's request that Atkinson escrow 50% of the replacement cost was actually for the restoration of the premises, taking reasonable wear and tear into account.

Finally, Lincoln contends that “attempting to keep Atkinson in a safe environment” has caused and will continue to cause undue hardship in the form of hazards to the other tenants and promote tenant unrest. Lincoln cites a letter received from a six-year tenant who declined to renew her lease because of insect infestation in her apartment. The record also reveals that this tenant's apartment was located in building J, which is unaffected by the order of the Commission. Although tenants in Atkinson's building have expressed dissatisfaction with the presence of insects, and lack of painting, the hearing examiner properly found this dissatisfaction to be a result of Lincoln's refusal to utilize any painting, pest control or lawn care procedures in Atkinson's building, not as a result of the adoption of a policy of reasonable accommodation.

The order of the Commission is affirmed in part, vacated in part, and the matter remanded for disposition consistent with the foregoing opinion.

Problems

1. The Lincoln Realty case discussed the concerns about tenant unrest and undue hardships for other tenants. Is this an instance of impermissible “cotenant preference” or is it a legitimate concern about the effect on other tenants? What if the other tenants were not inconvenienced, but just found her complaints to be annoying?

2. The court did not focus on whether Atkinson's sensitivity to a variety of chemicals was a disability. The hearing examiner had made that determination. If a tenant's sensitivity was only to a small number of chemicals, would that tenant qualify for protection? How would a court be likely to handle whether TRAVEL's clients with post-traumatic stress disorder are “disabled/handicapped” under the FHA? What if a tenant had a sensitivity or allergy to cats, and a tenant wanted an emotional support cat? How should a court handle dueling “disabilities”?

3. Landlady lives in and owns a large house which is divided into four apartments. She also owns an apartment building of twenty-five units next door. Mr. A, who is paraplegic and uses a wheelchair, wants to rent an apartment from Landlady and prefers to rent an apartment in the house. There is a vacancy in both the house and the apartment building. If Mr. A would live in either building, he would need ramps at the front entrance, lowered doorknobs and light switches, and added railings in the bathroom. What are Landlady's obligations in terms of renting space to Mr. A, making the needed changes, and payment for the needed changes under federal law?

—————

The following case highlights challenges of older buildings. In reading the case, consider what would be required of a three story apartment building constructed after the FHA effective date that did not have an elevator at all. Would that violate the FHA?

Congdon v. Strine

854 F. Supp. 355 (E.D. Pa. 1994)

DALZELL, DISTRICT JUDGE:

I. Factual Background

[The case involved residents who had lived in a fourth floor apartment for several years. The tenant used a wheelchair. Although there was an elevator, it had frequent breakdowns. After complaining to various governmental authorities, the tenants' month-to-month lease was not renewed. The landlord offered to move the tenants to a ground floor or another building, but they rejected that offer.]

Denial of Housing under 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(1)

This case differs from most Title VIII cases in that there was no actual denial of housing. It is undisputed that Strine continues to rent an apartment to the Congdons and that Linda Congdon has been living in the apartment since 1983. There is no evidence that Strine discriminated in renting to Mrs. Congdon or that she has been denied housing. The Congdons essentially claim that the threatened eviction and the refusal to provide reasonable accommodations violate §3604(f)(1). Thus, we must determine whether Strine's actions fall within the ambit of the “otherwise make unavailable or deny” language of §3604(f)(1).

While a threat of eviction should not be taken lightly, Strine and his agents made offers to rent other apartments to the Congdons, including an offer to rent her an apartment in the same building on the first floor. Strine took no further actions to enforce the eviction notice. Indeed, Strine never denied housing to the Congdons. To the contrary, Strine undisputedly offered the Congdons alternatives, albeit not to their taste.

Although the Congdons do not specify what reasonable accommodations they think Strine must provide, we infer that they want Strine to provide better repairs to the elevator, a new elevator, or another apartment that is acceptable to Mrs. Congdon's needs for accessibility and parking. Taking as true that defendant failed to provide a trouble-free elevator or another apartment to plaintiffs' liking, the Congdons still were not denied housing. There is no evidence that Mrs. Congdon was unable to return to her apartment and had to spend the night elsewhere. The Congdons only allege that Mrs. Congdon at times “miss[ed] appointments and other daily activities” because she was unable to leave the apartment, Although it appears that Mrs. Congdon was inconvenienced, we do not find that these actions fall within the meaning of “make unavailable” or “deny” in §3604(f)(1) any more than the occasional failure of the elevators in this courthouse “deny” courtrooms to litigants. Thus, we cannot find that defendant's conduct implicates §3604(f)(1) of Title VIII.

Discriminatory Provision of Services under 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(2)

We next consider whether the Congdons make out a claim for a violation of 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(2), which provides in relevant part that it is unlawful:

[t]o discriminate against any person in the terms, conditions, or privileges of sale or rental of a dwelling, or in the provision of services or facilities in connection with such dwelling, because of a handicap of—(A) that person; or (B) a person residing in ... that dwelling ...;

The Congdons do not allege that their terms, conditions or privileges of the rental differed from other tenants. In essence, the Congdons claim that Strine discriminated against them by providing poor elevator service. They allege that Strine's maintenance practices regarding the elevator were discriminatory because the breakdown of the elevator understandably created more hardships for Mrs. Congdon than it did to non-handicapped tenants.

“To make out a prima facie case under Title VIII, a plaintiff can show either discriminatory treatment ... or discriminatory effect alone, without proof of discriminatory intent ...” We shall consider the Congdons' “discriminatory treatment” and “discriminatory effect” theories separately.

For the Congdons to succeed on a “discriminatory treatment” claim, they need to show that Strine adopted and carried out his maintenance policies regarding the elevator with the intent to discriminate against Mrs. Congdon because of her disability. The Congdons have not submitted any facts to show that Strine had such a discriminatory motive with regard to the elevator maintenance policies.

Plaintiffs only generally allege that Strine was motivated by a discriminatory intent. They proffer no evidence that Strine acted differently in providing elevator services to Mrs. Congdon. The elevator's imperfections doubtless vexed all the tenants, not solely Mrs. Congdon. Strine thus did not stop providing elevator service exclusively to Mrs. Congdon.

Although we find no evidence of discriminatory treatment, plaintiffs need only show that Strine's policy regarding the elevator's maintenance had a discriminatory effect. In considering the scope of the FHAA, we agree with the Seventh Circuit's refusal “to conclude that every action which produces discriminatory effects is illegal.”

Our Court of Appeals has observed that the legislative history of Title VIII suggests that the statute should be read expansively in order to “eliminate the adverse discriminatory effects of past and present prejudice in housing.” With this breadth in mind, we will apply the factors set forth in Arlington Heights to guide our analysis. [Author's note: These factors are discussed in Baxter, reproduced at the beginning of this Chapter.]

The first factor looks at how strong is the plaintiffs' showing of discriminatory effect. The Congdons submit evidence alleging that the elevator often suffered mechanical problems or broke down completely. Mrs. Congdon avers that when the elevator broke down she “has been forced to remain in her apartment and to miss appointments and other daily activities.” Clearly, the elevator breakdowns affected Linda Congdon more severely than non-disabled tenants. There were times when she was unable to access her apartment without assistance or hardship, and was in general less able to enjoy her apartment. Therefore, we find that plaintiffs have made a showing of discriminatory effect in the provision of services to Linda Congdon. The first factor thus weighs in plaintiffs' favor.

With regard to the second factor, we must again look to see if there is evidence of discriminatory intent. The Congdons have proffered no facts supporting their allegation of discriminatory intent. In fact, Strine has offered Mrs. Congdon occupancy in other apartments and maintains a repair and servicing contract for the elevator. The Congdons have submitted no evidence that the defendant wilfully kept the elevator in a state of disrepair because of Mrs. Congdon's disability. Therefore, the second factor weighs in Strine's favor.

The third factor, which asks us to consider “defendant's interest in taking the action complained of,” also weighs in Strine's favor. Defendant has no business interest in having a faulty elevator that drives out frustrated tenants. Strine has a maintenance contract with an elevator servicing company precisely to serve his business interest of making it possible for all tenants to have elevator service. This company frequently serviced the offending elevator. We therefore can perceive no interest Strine would have in perpetuating faulty elevator service.

The fourth Metropolitan factor directs us to examine the relief plaintiffs seek, i.e., whether the Congdons want us to compel Strine affirmatively to provide services or whether they seek to restrain Strine from deliberately reducing the level of services he provides to Mrs. Congdon. This examination is predicated on the economic realities of affirmative relief: To require a defendant to appropriate money, utilize his land for a particular purpose, or take other affirmative steps toward integrated housing is a massive judicial intrusion on private autonomy.

The Congdons alternatively seek that this Court compel Strine to repair the elevator so that it always works properly, to replace the existing elevator with a new one, or to provide her with occupancy in another apartment. If the Congdons remain in their present unit (which seems to be their desire in view of their refusal to accept the alternatives proffered them), it seems that Strine would have to achieve the impossible to please them. Even a perfect landlord cannot maintain a completely problem-free elevator. Elevators are subject to malfunctioning like all mechanical devices.

The Congdons have not presented any facts which suggest that Strine is providing a level of services inferior to the level of services he provides to the other tenants in the building. Especially in view of the alternatives Strine has offered the Congdons, we find no basis in §3604(f)(2) that authorizes us to order Strine to install a new elevator or to assure that the present one is trouble-free.

“Reasonable Accommodations”

The Congdons claim that Strine did not make a “reasonable accommodation” of Mrs. Congdon's disability. Although it is not clear from the complaint, it appears that plaintiffs base their claim on their allegations that Strine did not keep the elevator in better working condition, did not replace the elevator, or offer the Congdons another apartment that would accommodate Mrs. Congdon's disabilities.

Strine argues that he did make reasonable accommodations for Mrs. Congdon's disability in that he had a regular elevator maintenance contract, and offered the Congdons a first floor apartment in the same building, as well as another apartment in a building with two elevators. Lastly, Strine argues that forcing him to install a new elevator in the building would impose an undue financial burden because a new elevator would cost sixty-five to seventy thousand dollars, and such an expenditure would not be a reasonable accommodation for a month-to-month tenant.

The Congdons have not submitted any evidence of requests for reasonable accommodations that they made and were refused other than for a new elevator and to make the existing elevator trouble-free.

We agree with Strine that forcing him to install a new elevator would constitute, in this context, “a massive judicial intrusion on private autonomy.” Such an intrusion would offend any decent respect for proportionality given that the Congdons seek a $65,000 capital expenditure when they are free to walk away from Strine on payment of only one month's rent. The Congdons' extravagant demand for such an “accommodation” thus cannot be deemed to be “reasonable.”

As we have previously mentioned, Strine has a contract with an elevator maintenance company, and he submits undisputed evidence that repairs were made regularly. Thus, it does not seem that Strine failed to make a reasonable accommodation in his elevator maintenance for Mrs. Congdon's disability.

We are further fortified in our conclusion because of Strine's good faith effort to accommodate Mrs. Congdon by offering her occupancy in other apartments. Thus, we do not find discrimination pursuant to §3604(f)(3).

Notes

1. The previous case illustrates the challenges with facilities built before the effective date for making new multi-unit housing accessible. Landlords are not required to make existing housing accessible. The FHA requires landlords to allow individuals to make structural modifications at their own expense, so long as the property can be restored to its original condition, less ordinary wear and tear. 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(3)(A). It even provides that an escrow account can be negotiated to ensure that the restoration will occur. How does that affect the situation for TRAVEL in the hypothetical problem? Does it make a difference that the lease is for three years?

2. Buildings constructed for occupancy after March 13, 1991, for multiunit dwellings must meet specific access requirements. 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(3)(C). If an apartment complex were built that did not meet the accessibility requirements, which parties would be liable—contractor, developer, architect, engineer? How would that be determined? What indemnification might be part of the arrangement? See, e.g., United States of America v. Gambone Brothers Development Co., 37 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶254 (E.D. Pa. 2008); Equal Rights Center v. Archstone Smith Trust, 28 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. 238 (D. Md. 2009); United States v. Shanrie Co, Inc., 37 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶255 (S.D. Ill. 2008).

Another issue that courts have grappled with where there are mixed results involves the standing of advocacy organizations to bring certain actions. See, e.g., Association for Retarded Citizens of Dallas v. Dallas County Mental Health & Mental Retardation Center Bd. of Trustees, 19 F.3d 241 (5th Cir. 1994) (allowing participating as an amicus, but not as a party); Louisiana Acorn Fair Housing Organization v. Jaffe, 2000 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13224, 2000 WL 1277599 (E.D. La. 2000) (housing organization utilizing independent contractor to make test call to landlord to test compliance with FHA lacked standing to bring suit because it suffered no injury in fact); Metropolitan St. Louis Equal Housing Opportunity Council v. Lighthouse Lodge, 39 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶106 (W.D. Mo. 2009); Equal Rights Center v. AvalonBay Communities, Inc., 38 Nat'l Disability L. Rep. ¶237 (D. Md. 2009); Disability Advocates Inc. v. Paterson, 598 F. Supp. 2d 289 (E.D.N.Y. 2009). Is TRAVEL an advocacy organization or is it more like the complainant in the Baxter case?

3. As is the case with other building construction cases under Title II and Title III of the ADA, there is a lack of clarity about liability for ensuring access of the owner and contractor and other parties for not complying with requirements for new construction. There has been little litigation on this issue to provide much guidance. See, e.g., Equal Rights Center v. Niles Bolton Associates, 602 F.3d 597 (4th Cir. 2010) (state law claims of indemnification against an architect for violations relating to apartment building designs are preempted by ADA and FHA); United States v. Gambone Bros. Development Co., 2008 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 73503, 2008 WL 4410093 (E.D. Pa. 2008) (summary judgment in favor of architecture and engineering firm; denying claim by development company and construction company for indemnification and contribution after finding of FHA violations in constructing apartment complexes); United States v. Shanrie Co., Inc., 610 F. Supp. 2d 958 (S.D. Ill. 2009), judgment entered, 2009 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 39655, 2009 WL 1309188 (S.D. Ill. 2009) (although engineers and architects were involved in apartment design, owners and developers do not have right of contribution or indemnity from engineers or architects).

F. Least Restrictive Environment and Independent Living

One of the major principles of the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act is the concept of least restrictive environment. This principle, of course, is intended to apply to where people with disabilities live. The courts focused substantial attention on this issue in relation to the movement to deinstitutionalize individuals with intellectual disabilities and mental illness in the 1970s and 1980s. The Supreme Court twice addressed the issue in the case of Pennhurst State School & Hospital v. Halderman, 465 U.S. 89 (1984) and 451 U.S. 1 (1981). The case was a class action of institutionalized individuals in Pennsylvania state institutions. They brought claims seeking a right to treatment and a right to treatment in the least restrictive environment. The advocates in the case sought relief under a number of legal theories, including constitutional equal protection and due process grounds, Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act, and state laws. The substantive issues remained unresolved for fifteen years, however, because the Court used a procedural basis to avoiding deciding these issues.

Deinstitutionalization began to take place as a social policy even without a definitive mandate from the Supreme Court. The goal was to place individuals who had previously been living in large institutions in community placements such as group homes, foster families, or independent living arrangements with supportive services. In addition, it became extremely unlikely that new placements in the large institutions would occur. A number of difficulties in implementing these policies, however, soon became apparent. These included inadequate resources (funding, placements, and trained staffing) in the communities, and zoning and other restrictions related to location of group homes and similar housing.

Economic challenges beginning in 2008 added to the difficulties of the deinstitutionalization movement. State and local governmental agencies that had been providers and funding sources for providing health care services to individuals with disabilities in their homes were facing funding shortfalls and seeking economies of scale. In some instances, they may have determined that it was only economically feasible to provide these services in a nursing home, although in many situations individuals receiving these services could live independently in the mainstream of society if only these services were provided. A number of cases have challenged this kind of delivery of service as violating the mainstreaming mandate of the FHA, the ADA, and Section 504. These decisions are just beginning to establish the standards for this issue.

The Court in Olmstead v. L.C., 527 U.S. 581 (1999), provided the assurance that the least restrictive environment principle was to be applied in placing individuals with disabilities. The excerpt from that opinion follows and clarifies the basis for this determination. Other cases in this section highlight the judicial response to some of the challenges to full implementation of community based placement and treatment for individuals with disabilities.

Olmstead v. L.C.

527 U.S. 581 (1999)

JUSTICE GINSBURG announced the judgment of the Court and delivered the opinion of the Court with respect to Parts I, II, and III-A, and an opinion with respect to Part III-B, in which O'CONNOR, SOUTER, AND BREYER, JJ., joined.

This case concerns the proper construction of the anti-discrimination provision contained in the public services portion (Title II) of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 U.S.C. §12132. Specifically, we confront the question whether the proscription of discrimination may require placement of persons with mental disabilities in community settings rather than in institutions. The answer, we hold, is a qualified yes. Such action is in order when the State's treatment professionals have determined that community placement is appropriate, the transfer from institutional care to a less restrictive setting is not opposed by the affected individual, and the placement can be reasonably accommodated, taking into account the resources available to the State and the needs of others with mental disabilities. In so ruling, we affirm the decision of the Eleventh Circuit in substantial part. We remand the case, however, for further consideration of the appropriate relief, given the range of facilities the State maintains for the care and treatment of persons with diverse mental disabilities, and its obligation to administer services with an even hand.

I

In the opening provisions of the ADA, Congress stated findings applicable to the statute in all its parts. Most relevant to this case, Congress determined that

“(2) historically, society has tended to isolate and segregate individuals with disabilities, and, despite some improvements, such forms of discrimination against individuals with disabilities continue to be a serious and pervasive social problem;

“(3) discrimination against individuals with disabilities persists in such critical areas as ... institutionalization ... :

....

“(5) individuals with disabilities continually encounter various forms of discrimination, including outright intentional exclusion, ... failure to make modifications to existing facilities and practices, ... [and] segregation....” 42 U.S.C. §§12101(a)(2), (3), (5).

Congress then set forth prohibitions against discrimination in employment, public services furnished by governmental entities, and public accommodations provided by private entities. The statute as a whole is intended “to provide a clear and comprehensive national mandate for the elimination of discrimination against individuals with disabilities.”

This case concerns Title II, the public services portion of the ADA. The provision of Title II centrally at issue reads:

“Subject to the provisions of this subchapter, no qualified individual with a disability shall, by reason of such disability, be excluded from participation in or be denied the benefits of the services, programs, or activities of a public entity, or be subjected to discrimination by any such entity.”

Title II's definition section states that “public entity” includes “any State or local government,” and “any department, agency, [or] special purpose district.” §§12131(1)(A), (B). The same section defines “qualified individual with a disability” as

“an individual with a disability who, with or without reasonable modifications to rules, policies, or practices, the removal of architectural, communication, or transportation barriers, or the provision of auxiliary aids and services, meets the essential eligibility requirements for the receipt of services or the participation in programs or activities provided by a public entity.”

On redress for violations of §12132's discrimination prohibition, Congress referred to remedies available under §505 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973

Congress instructed the Attorney General to issue regulations implementing provisions of Title II, including §12132's discrimination proscription. The Attorney General's regulations, Congress further directed, “shall be consistent with this chapter and with the coordination regulations ... applicable to recipients of Federal financial assistance under [§504 of the Rehabilitation Act].” 42 U.S.C. §12134(b). One of the §504 regulations requires recipients of federal funds to “administer programs and activities in the most integrated setting appropriate to the needs of qualified handicapped persons.” 28 CFR §41.51(d) (1998).

As Congress instructed, the Attorney General issued Title II regulations, see 28 CFR pt. 35 (1998), including one modeled on the §504 regulation just quoted; called the “integration regulation,” it reads:

“A public entity shall administer services, programs, and activities in the most integrated setting appropriate to the needs of qualified individuals with disabilities.” 28 CFR §35.130(d) (1998).

The preamble to the Attorney General's Title II regulations defines “the most integrated setting appropriate to the needs of qualified individuals with disabilities” to mean “a setting that enables individuals with disabilities to interact with non-disabled persons to the fullest extent possible.” 28 CFR pt. 35, App. A, p. 450 (1998). Another regulation requires public entities to “make reasonable modifications” to avoid “discrimination on the basis of disability,” unless those modifications would entail a “fundamenta[l] alter[ation]”; called here the “reasonable-modifications regulation,” it provides:

“A public entity shall make reasonable modifications in policies, practices, or procedures when the modifications are necessary to avoid discrimination on the basis of disability, unless the public entity can demonstrate that making the modifications would fundamentally alter the nature of the service, program, or activity.” 28 CFR §35.130(b)(7) (1998).

II

With the key legislative provisions in full view, we summarize the facts underlying this dispute. Respondents L.C. and E.W. are mentally retarded women; L.C. has also been diagnosed with schizophrenia, and E.W., with a personality disorder. Both women have a history of treatment in institutional settings. In May 1992, L.C. was voluntarily admitted to Georgia Regional Hospital at Atlanta (GRH), where she was confined for treatment in a psychiatric unit. By May 1993, her psychiatric condition had stabilized, and L.C.'s treatment team at GRH agreed that her needs could be met appropriately in one of the community-based programs the State supported. Despite this evaluation, L.C. remained institutionalized until February 1996, when the State placed her in a community-based treatment program.

E.W. was voluntarily admitted to GRH in February 1995; like L.C., E.W. was confined for treatment in a psychiatric unit. In March 1995, GRH sought to discharge E.W. to a homeless shelter, but abandoned that plan after her attorney filed an administrative complaint. By 1996, E.W.'s treating psychiatrist concluded that she could be treated appropriately in a community-based setting. She nonetheless remained institutionalized until a few months after the District Court issued its judgment in this case in 1997.

In May 1995, when she was still institutionalized at GRH, L.C. filed suit in the United States District Court for the Northern District of Georgia, challenging her continued confinement in a segregated environment. Her complaint invoked 42 U.S.C. §1983 and provisions of the ADA, §§12131–12134, and named as defendants, now petitioners, the Commissioner of the Georgia Department of Human Resources, the Superintendent of GRH, and the Executive Director of the Fulton County Regional Board (collectively, the State). L.C. alleged that the State's failure to place her in a community-based program, once her treating professionals determined that such placement was appropriate, violated, inter alia. Title II of the ADA. L.C.'s pleading requested, among other things, that the State place her in a community care residential program, and that she receive treatment with the ultimate goal of integrating her into the mainstream of society. E.W. intervened in the action, stating an identical claim.^4

[Lower court proceedings omitted.]

III

Endeavoring to carry out Congress' instruction to issue regulations implementing Title II, the Attorney General, in the integration and reasonable-modifications regulations, made two key determinations. The first concerned the scope of the ADA's discrimination proscription, 42 U.S.C. §12132; the second concerned the obligation of the States to counter discrimination. As to the first, the Attorney General concluded that unjustified placement or retention of persons in institutions, severely limiting their exposure to the outside community, constitutes a form of discrimination based on disability prohibited by Title II. Regarding the States' obligation to avoid unjustified isolation of individuals with disabilities, the Attorney General provided that States could resist modifications that “would fundamentally alter the nature of the service, program, or activity.” 28 CFR §35.130(b)(7) (1998).

The Court of Appeals essentially upheld the Attorney General's construction of the ADA. As just recounted, the appeals court ruled that the unjustified institutionalization of persons with mental disabilities violated Title II; the court then remanded with instructions to measure the cost of caring for L.C. and E.W. in a community- based facility against the State's mental health budget.

We affirm the Court of Appeals' decision in substantial part. Unjustified isolation, we hold, is properly regarded as discrimination based on disability. But we recognize, as well, the States' need to maintain a range of facilities for the care and treatment of persons with diverse mental disabilities, and the States' obligation to administer services with an even hand. In evaluating a State's fundamental-alteration defense, the District Court must consider, in view of the resources available to the State, not only the cost of providing community-based care to the litigants, but also the range of services the State provides others with mental disabilities, and the State's obligation to mete out those services equitably.

A

We examine first whether, as the Eleventh Circuit held, undue institutionalization qualifies as discrimination “by reason of ... disability.” The Department of Justice has consistently advocated that it does. Because the Department is the agency directed by Congress to issue regulations implementing Title II, its views warrant respect....

The State argues that L.C. and E.W. encountered no discrimination “by reason of” their disabilities because they were not denied community placement on account of those disabilities. Nor were they subjected to “discrimination,” the State contends, because “‘discrimination’ necessarily requires uneven treatment of similarly situated individuals,” and L.C. and E.W. had identified no comparison class, i.e., no similarly situated individuals given preferential treatment. We are satisfied that Congress had a more comprehensive view of the concept of discrimination advanced in the ADA.

The ADA stepped up earlier measures to secure opportunities for people with developmental disabilities to enjoy the benefits of community living. The Developmentally Disabled Assistance and Bill of Rights Act (DDABRA), a 1975 measure, stated in aspirational terms that “[t]he treatment, services, and habilitation for a person with developmental disabilities ... should be provided in the setting that is least restrictive of the person's personal liberty.” In a related legislative endeavor, the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, Congress used mandatory language to proscribe discrimination against persons with disabilities. Ultimately, in the ADA, enacted in 1990, Congress not only required all public entities to refrain from discrimination, see 42 U.S.C. §12132; additionally, in findings applicable to the entire statute, Congress explicitly identified unjustified “segregation” of persons with disabilities as a “for[m] of discrimination.”

Recognition that unjustified institutional isolation of persons with disabilities is a form of discrimination reflects two evident judgments. First, institutional placement of persons who can handle and benefit from community settings perpetuates unwarranted assumptions that persons so isolated are incapable or unworthy of participating in community life. Second, confinement in an institution severely diminishes the everyday life activities of individuals, including family relations, social contacts, work options, economic independence, educational advancement, and cultural enrichment. Dissimilar treatment correspondingly exists in this key respect: In order to receive needed medical services, persons with mental disabilities must, because of those disabilities, relinquish participation in community life they could enjoy given reasonable accommodations, while persons without mental disabilities can receive the medical services they need without similar sacrifice.

The State urges that, whatever Congress may have stated as its findings in the ADA, the Medicaid statute “reflected a congressional policy preference for treatment in the institution over treatment in the community.” The State correctly used the past tense. Since 1981, Medicaid has provided funding for state-run home and community-based care through a waiver program. Indeed, the United States points out that the Department of Health and Human Services (HHS) “has a policy of encouraging States to take advantage of the waiver program, and often approves more waiver slots than a State ultimately uses.”

We emphasize that nothing in the ADA or its implementing regulations condones termination of institutional settings for persons unable to handle or benefit from community settings. Title II provides only that “qualified individual[s] with a disability” may not “be subjected to discrimination.” 42 U.S.C. §12132. “Qualified individuals,” the ADA further explains, are persons with disabilities who, “with or without reasonable modifications to rules, policies, or practices, ... mee[t] the essential eligibility requirements for the receipt of services or the participation in programs or activities provided by a public entity.” §12131(2).

Consistent with these provisions, the State generally may rely on the reasonable assessments of its own professionals in determining whether an individual “meets the essential eligibility requirements” for habilitation in a community-based program. Absent such qualification, it would be inappropriate to remove a patient from the more restrictive setting. Nor is there any federal requirement that community-based treatment be imposed on patients who do not desire it. See 28 CFR §35.130(e)(1) (1998) (“Nothing in this part shall be construed to require an individual with a disability to accept an accommodation ... which such individual chooses not to accept.”); 28 CFR pt. 35, App. A, p. 450 (1998) (“[P]ersons with disabilities must be provided the option of declining to accept a particular accommodation.”). In this case, however, there is no genuine dispute concerning the status of L.C. and E.W. as individuals “qualified” for noninstitutional care: The State's own professionals determined that community-based treatment would be appropriate for L.C. and E.W., and neither woman opposed such treatment.^5

B

The State's responsibility, once it provides community-based treatment to qualified persons with disabilities, is not boundless. The reasonable-modifications regulation speaks of “reasonable modifications” to avoid discrimination, and allows States to resist modifications that entail a “fundamenta[l] alter[ation]” of the States' services and programs. 28 CFR §35.130(b)(7) (1998). The Court of Appeals construed this regulation to permit a cost-based defense “only in the most limited of circumstances,” and remanded to the District Court to consider, among other things, “whether the additional expenditures necessary to treat L.C. and E.W. in community-based care would be unreasonable given the demands of the State's mental health budget.”

The Court of Appeals' construction of the reasonable-modifications regulation is unacceptable for it would leave the State virtually defenseless once it is shown that the plaintiff is qualified for the service or program she seeks. If the expense entailed in placing one or two people in a community-based treatment program is properly measured for reasonableness against the State's entire mental health budget, it is unlikely that a State, relying on the fundamental-alteration defense, could ever prevail. Sensibly construed, the fundamental-alteration component of the reasonable-modifications regulation would allow the State to show that, in the allocation of available resources, immediate relief for the plaintiffs would be inequitable, given the responsibility the State has undertaken for the care and treatment of a large and diverse population of persons with mental disabilities.

When it granted summary judgment for plaintiffs in this case, the District Court compared the cost of caring for the plaintiffs in a community-based setting with the cost of caring for them in an institution. That simple comparison showed that community placements cost less than institutional confinements. As the United States recognizes, however, a comparison so simple overlooks costs the State cannot avoid; most notably, a “State ... may experience increased overall expenses by funding community placements without being able to take advantage of the savings associated with the closure of institutions.”

As already observed, the ADA is not reasonably read to impel States to phase out institutions, placing patients in need of close care at risk. Nor is it the ADA's mission to drive States to move institutionalized patients into an inappropriate setting, such as a homeless shelter, a placement the State proposed, then retracted, for E.W. Some individuals, like L.C. and E.W. in prior years, may need institutional care from time to time “to stabilize acute psychiatric symptoms.” For other individuals, no placement outside the institution may ever be appropriate.

To maintain a range of facilities and to administer services with an even hand, the State must have more leeway than the courts below understood the fundamental-alteration defense to allow. If, for example, the State were to demonstrate that it had a comprehensive, effectively working plan for placing qualified persons with mental disabilities in less restrictive settings, and a waiting list that moved at a reasonable pace not controlled by the State's endeavors to keep its institutions fully populated, the reasonable-modifications standard would be met.

For the reasons stated, we conclude that, under Title II of the ADA, States are required to provide community-based treatment for persons with mental disabilities when the State's treatment professionals determine that such placement is appropriate, the affected persons do not oppose such treatment, and the placement can be reasonably accommodated, taking into account the resources available to the State and the needs of others with mental disabilities. The judgment of the Eleventh Circuit is therefore affirmed in part and vacated in part, and the case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.

JUSTICE STEVENS, concurring in part and concurring in the judgment. [Omitted.]

JUSTICE KENNEDY, with whom JUSTICE BREYER joins as to Part I, concurring in the judgment.

I

Despite remarkable advances and achievements by medical science, and agreement among many professionals that even severe mental illness is often treatable, the extent of public resources to devote to this cause remains controversial. Knowledgeable professionals tell us that our society, and the governments which reflect its attitudes and preferences, have yet to grasp the potential for treating mental disorders, especially severe mental illness. As a result, necessary resources for the endeavor often are not forthcoming. During the course of a year, about 5.6 million Americans will suffer from severe mental illness. E. Torrey, Out of the Shadows 4 (1997). Some 2.2 million of these persons receive no treatment. Millions of other Americans suffer from mental disabilities of less serious degree, such as mild depression. These facts are part of the background against which this case arises. In addition, of course, persons with mental disabilities have been subject to historic mistreatment, indifference, and hostility.

Despite these obstacles, the States have acknowledged that the care of the mentally disabled is their special obligation. They operate and support facilities and programs, sometimes elaborate ones, to provide care. It is a continuing challenge, though, to provide the care in an effective and humane way, particularly because societal attitudes and the responses of public authorities have changed from time to time.

Beginning in the 1950's, many victims of severe mental illness were moved out of state-run hospitals, often with benign objectives. According to one estimate, when adjusted for population growth, “the actual decrease in the numbers of people with severe mental illnesses in public psychiatric hospitals between 1955 and 1995 was 92 percent.” This was not without benefit or justification. The so-called “deinstitutionalization” has permitted a substantial number of mentally disabled persons to receive needed treatment with greater freedom and dignity. It may be, moreover, that those who remain institutionalized are indeed the most severe cases. With reference to this case, as the Court points out, it is undisputed that the State's own treating professionals determined that community-based care was medically appropriate for respondents. Nevertheless, the depopulation of state mental hospitals has its dark side. According to one expert:

“For a substantial minority ... deinstitutionalization has been a psychiatric Titanic. Their lives are virtually devoid of ‘dignity’ or ‘integrity of body, mind, and spirit.’ ‘Self-determination’ often means merely that the person has a choice of soup kitchens. The ‘least restrictive setting’ frequently turns out to be a cardboard box, a jail cell, or a terror-filled existence plagued by both real and imaginary enemies.”

It must be remembered that for the person with severe mental illness who has no treatment the most dreaded of confinements can be the imprisonment inflicted by his own mind, which shuts reality out and subjects him to the torment of voices and images beyond our own powers to describe.

It would be unreasonable, it would be a tragic event, then, were the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (ADA) to be interpreted so that States had some incentive, for fear of litigation, to drive those in need of medical care and treatment out of appropriate care and into settings with too little assistance and supervision. The opinion of a responsible treating physician in determining the appropriate conditions for treatment ought to be given the greatest of deference. It is a common phenomenon that a patient functions well with medication, yet, because of the mental illness itself, lacks the discipline or capacity to follow the regime the medication requires. This is illustrative of the factors a responsible physician will consider in recommending the appropriate setting or facility for treatment. Justice Ginsburg's opinion takes account of this background. It is careful, and quite correct, to say that it is not “the ADA's mission to drive States to move institutionalized patients into an inappropriate setting, such as a homeless shelter....”

In light of these concerns, if the principle of liability announced by the Court is not applied with caution and circumspection, States may be pressured into attempting compliance on the cheap, placing marginal patients into integrated settings devoid of the services and attention necessary for their condition. This danger is in addition to the federalism costs inherent in referring state decisions regarding the administration of treatment programs and the allocation of resources to the reviewing authority of the federal courts. It is of central importance, then, that courts apply today's decision with great deference to the medical decisions of the responsible, treating physicians and, as the Court makes clear, with appropriate deference to the program funding decisions of state policymakers.

[Part II of the opinion, which relates to Justice Kennedy's opinion that the case should be remanded is omitted.]

[The dissent by Justice Thomas, joined by Chief Justice Rehnquist and Justice Scalia, is omitted.]

—————

As noted previously, there are a number of challenges to the location of group homes in residential areas. These include zoning restrictions of many types. The Supreme Court had addressed this in the case of City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Center, 473 U.S. 432 (1985), in Chapter 1, supra. In that case, the Court focused on the Constitutional test to be applied in the denial of a special use permit for a group home for individuals with intellectual disabilities. The plaintiffs used the Constitution because the Fair Housing Act had not yet been amended to cover individuals with disabilities, and the Americans with Disabilities Act had not yet been enacted. It is unusual today, for advocates to seek redress in the kinds of cases that follow, using constitutional theories, because the Fair Housing Act and/or the Americans with Disabilities Act is much more likely to provide the basis for relief.

The City of Belleville case, excerpted earlier in the Chapter, involved a denial of a special use permit apparently because of fears and stereotypes about individuals with HIV. The issue raised was direct threat. That case should be kept in mind when reviewing the following decisions, which address spacing requirements and occupancy levels.

The following case addresses the issue of dispersal of community based programs within zoning restrictions.

Familystyle v. City of St. Paul

923 F.2d 91 (8th Cir. 1991)

WOLLMAN, CIRCUIT JUDGE:

[The case involved a rehabilitative service program for individuals with mental illness and included a residential group home program that required special use permits for placement of the homes. Some were clustered, and the City Council sought more dispersal. The licensing process was part of the process that was challenged by the operator of the program.]

An integral part of the licensing process guarantees that residential programs are geographically situated, to the extent possible, in locations where residential services are needed, where they would be a part of the community at large, and where access to other necessary services is available. This licensing requirement reflects the goal of deinstitutionalization—a philosophy of creating a full range of community-based services and reducing the population of state institutions.

Minnesota's deinstitutionalization policy is formally acknowledged by its Comprehensive Adult Mental Health Act Housing Mission Statement, which requires that “the housing services provided as part of a comprehensive mental health service system ... allow all persons with mental illness to live in stable, affordable housing, in settings that maximize community integration and opportunities for acceptance.” Federal law affirms the deinstitutionalization philosophy in the Developmental Disabilities Assistance Act, in which Congress found that it is in the national interest to offer persons with developmental disabilities the opportunity, to the maximum extent feasible, to make decisions for themselves and to live in typical homes and communities where they can exercise their full rights and responsibilities as citizens. 42 U.S.C. §6000(a)(8).

Deinstitutionalization of the mentally ill is advanced in Minnesota by requiring a new group home to be located at least a quarter mile from an existing residential program unless the local zoning authority grants a conditional use or special use permit. The St. Paul zoning code similarly requires community residential facilities for the mentally impaired to be located at least a quarter of a mile apart.

Section 3615 of the Fair Housing Act invalidates “any law of a State, a political subdivision, or other such jurisdiction that purports to require or permit any action that would be a discriminatory housing practice under this subchapter.”

Familystyle argues that the Minnesota and St. Paul dispersal requirements are invalid because they limit housing choices of the mentally handicapped and therefore conflict with the language and purpose of the 1988 Amendments to the Fair Housing Act. We disagree. We perceive the goals of non-discrimination and deinstitutionalization to be compatible. Congress did not intend to abrogate a state's power to determine how facilities for the mentally ill must meet licensing standards. Minnesota's dispersal requirements address the need of providing residential services in mainstream community settings. The quarter-mile spacing requirement guarantees that residential treatment facilities will, in fact, be “in the community,” rather than in neighborhoods completely made up of group homes that re-create an institutional environment—a setting for which Familystyle argues. We cannot agree that Congress intended the Fair Housing Amendment Act of 1988 to contribute to the segregation of the mentally ill from the mainstream of our society. The challenged state laws and city ordinance do not affect or prohibit a retarded or mentally ill person from purchasing, renting, or occupying a private residence or dwelling.

The state plays a legitimate and necessary role in licensing services for the mentally impaired. We agree with the district court that the dispersal requirement as part of the licensure process is a legitimate means to achieve the state's goals in the process of deinstitutionalization of the mentally ill. Accordingly, we conclude that the Minnesota Human Services Licensing Act and the St. Paul zoning code do not violate the Fair Housing Amendments Act of 1988.

Familystyle argues that the state and city dispersal requirements result in a disparate impact on and discriminatory treatment of the mentally ill.

[I]n a Title VIII case brought against a public defendant, the plaintiff has the initial burden of presenting a prima facie case of the discriminatory effect of the challenged law. If the law is shown to have such an effect, the burden shifts to the governmental defendant to demonstrate that its conduct was necessary to promote a governmental interest commensurate with the level of scrutiny afforded the class of people affected by the law under the equal protection clause.

We conclude that the appropriate level of scrutiny is that announced in City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Center, 473 U.S. 432, 446, (1985), in which the Court held that persons suffering from mental retardation do not constitute a suspect class. The second question in the disparate impact analysis under Title VIII then becomes whether legislation which distinguishes between the mentally impaired and others is “rationally related to a legitimate governmental purpose.”

The district court found that although local and state dispersal requirements for group homes on their face limit housing choices for the mentally ill, the government's interest in deinstitutionalization sufficiently rebutted any discriminatory effect of the laws. Familystyle argues that the district court misapplied the factors relevant in evaluating the government's interest in dispersal requirements. We disagree.

The district court examined the reasons for the state and local law under the strict scrutiny standard. Although we believe that it is not necessary to evaluate the purposes so closely, we agree with the district court that the government's interests are valid. The state aims to integrate the mentally ill into the mainstream of society. One method to achieve that goal is to license group homes which advance the process of deinstitutionalization. Familystyle is a treatment facility that houses more than one hundred mentally ill patients. Further growth of the Familystyle treatment facility may well be counterproductive to the desegregation of the mentally ill.

Had the state or city intended to discriminate against the mentally ill, one sure way would be to situate all group homes in the same neighborhood—a situation for which Familystyle argues. The state's group home dispersal requirements are designed to ensure that mentally handicapped persons needing residential treatment will not be forced into enclaves of treatment facilities that would replicate and thus perpetuate the isolation resulting from institutionalization.

We are not persuaded that any intent to discriminate against the handicapped lies beneath the surface of the state and local dispersal requirements and the purposes of deinstitutionalization. We have been given no reason to believe that Familystyle is incapable of dispersing its group homes and integrating its clients into the community. Accordingly, we conclude that the goal of deinstitutionalization remains a valid and legitimate end that the State of Minnesota and the City of St. Paul are pursuing through legally acceptable means.

The district court's judgment is affirmed.

Notes

1. Balancing Fair Housing and Free Speech Rights: In August of 1994, the Department of Housing and Urban Development investigated a housing discrimination complaint alleging that a group of private citizens had violated the FHA by opposing plans to turn a motel into a low-income housing project for recovering alcoholics and drug abusers. Although HUD seemed to initially take the position that such opposition was an FHA violation, it backed off from that position when First Amendment supporters challenged the HUD position. In an opinion piece by Roberta Achtenberg, assistant secretary for fair housing and equal opportunity at HUD, the following was the explanation for the HUD position:

Congress has said ... that the First Amendment does not protect all forms of speech when it comes to housing discrimination. For example, the First Amendment does not protect a landlord or a neighbor who employs intimidation or verbal abuse to discourage someone from moving into housing because of his race, religion or disability. Fair housing rights were held paramount ... when an administrative law judge imposed a $300,000 fine on a Texas woman who engaged in a “relentless campaign of intimidation” to force African-American neighbors out of public housing....

....

First, people have a right to petition local officials for action, even though their motives may appear discriminatory. Where the efforts of neighbors or others appear primarily directed toward achieving a governmental decision—such as denial of a zoning variance—their behavior will most likely be considered protected free speech, no matter what their motives may be. Second, people have the right to protection from private actions aimed at denying them access to housing because of race, color, sex, religion, national origin, family status or disability. Where neighbors or others attempt to intimidate property owners into refusing to sell to someone because of his or her race, for example, or where disabled people are harassed so that they will not move into a neighborhood, such actions will likely be considered discriminatory activities not protected by the First Amendment.

Roberta Achtenberg, On Tightrope Between Fair Housing, Free Speech, HOUSTON CHRONICLE, Aug. 26, 1994, at A33.

2. For additional judicial opinions addressing the issue of spacing between group homes, see Horizon House Developmental Services, Inc. v. Township of Upper Southampton, 995 F.2d 217 (3d Cir. 1993) (ordinance requiring 1,000-foot spacing between group homes was facially discriminatory against disabled individuals, violates FHA and serves no legitimate purpose); Larkin v. State of Mich., 89 F.3d 285 (6th Cir. 1996) (no rational basis for statute that prevents licensing residential facilities for adults with intellectual disabilities within 1,500 feet of other similar institutions); Oconomowoc Residential Programs v. City of Milwaukee, 300 F.3d 775 (7th Cir. 2002) (zoning variance reasonable and necessary accommodation to provide individuals with disabilities equal opportunity to enjoy housing in residential community where city's system of permitting group homes in single family districts did not allow more than one such facility within 2,500 feet without variance); Ventura Village, Inc. v. City of Minneapolis, Minn., 419 F.3d 725 (8th Cir. 2005) (city did not violate FHA when waiving spacing ordinance for supportive housing facility); Harding v. City of Toledo, 433 F. Supp. 2d 867 (N.D. Ohio 2006) (upholding ordinance requiring 500-foot buffer between groups homes).

Problem

The Familystyle decision is a case where the court recognized the importance of balancing the integration principles of deinstitutionalization with the nondiscrimination principles of the Fair Housing Act. What would happen in a city where spacing requirements effectively preclude the addition of new group homes because, in certain neighborhoods where the spacing requirements would not be violated, it is not feasible to purchase or rent affordable housing?

If the Familystyle reasoning were applied to the case involving the TRAVEL hypothetical problem to have two transitional houses next to each other, what would be the likely result? Are the TRAVEL residences different from group homes for individuals with intellectual disabilities who would otherwise live in institutions? Does it matter that the TRAVEL residents are only going to live in the housing for a limited time and that they are in the process of transitioning into the mainstream of society?

—————

The following case involves the issue of whether, under the Fair Housing Act, a city may impose greater restrictions on the number of unrelated people than related people who may live in housing zoned for single-family dwellings. The Supreme Court in this opinion only addresses the question of whether such zoning ordinances are exempt from the Fair Housing Act. After reading the case, consider whether the application of the Fair Housing Act should operate to require accommodation in this case or to strike down the differentiation entirely as having a disparate discriminatory impact on group homes for individuals with disabilities.

City of Edmonds v. Oxford House, Inc.

514 U.S. 725 (1995)

JUSTICE GINSBURG delivered the opinion of the Court:

The Fair Housing Act (FHA or Act) prohibits discrimination in housing against, inter alios, persons with handicaps. Section 3607(b)(1) of the Act entirely exempts from the FHA's compass “any reasonable local, State, or Federal restrictions regarding the maximum number of occupants permitted to occupy a dwelling.” This case presents the question whether a provision in petitioner City of Edmonds' zoning code qualifies for §3607(b)(1)'s complete exemption from FHA scrutiny. The provision, governing areas zoned for single-family dwelling units, defines “family” as “persons [without regard to number] related by genetics, adoption, or marriage, or a group of five or fewer [unrelated] persons.” Edmonds Community Development Code (ECDC) §21.30.010 (1991).

The defining provision at issue describes who may compose a family unit; it does not prescribe “the maximum number of occupants” a dwelling unit may house. We hold that §3607(b)(1) does not exempt prescriptions of the family-defining kind, i.e., provisions designed to foster the family character of a neighborhood. Instead, §3607(b)(1)'s absolute exemption removes from the FHA's scope only total occupancy limits, i.e., numerical ceilings that serve to prevent overcrowding in living quarters.

I.

In the summer of 1990, respondent Oxford House opened a group home in the City of Edmonds, Washington for 10 to 12 adults recovering from alcoholism and drug addiction. The group home, called Oxford House-Edmonds, is located in a neighborhood zoned for single-family residences. Upon learning that Oxford House had leased and was operating a home in Edmonds, the City issued criminal citations to the owner and a resident of the house. The citations charged violation of the zoning code rule that defines who may live in single-family dwelling units. The occupants of such units must compose a “family,” and family, under the City's defining rule, “means an individual or two or more persons related by genetics, adoption, or marriage, or a group of five or fewer persons who are not related by genetics, adoption, or marriage.” Edmonds Community Development Code (ECDC) §21.30.010. Oxford House-Edmonds houses more than five unrelated persons, and therefore does not conform to the code.

Oxford House asserted reliance on the Fair Housing Act, which declares it unlawful “[t]o discriminate in the sale or rental, or to otherwise make unavailable or deny, a dwelling to any buyer or renter because of a handicap of ... that buyer or a renter.” The parties have stipulated, for purposes of this litigation, that the residents of Oxford House-Edmonds “are recovering alcoholics and drug addicts and are handicapped persons within the meaning” of the Act.

Discrimination covered by the FHA includes “a refusal to make reasonable accommodations in rules, policies, practices, or services, when such accommodations may be necessary to afford [handicapped] person[s] equal opportunity to use and enjoy a dwelling.” §3604(f)(3)(B). Oxford House asked Edmonds to make a “reasonable accommodation” by allowing it to remain in the single-family dwelling it had leased. Group homes for recovering substance abusers, Oxford urged, need 8 to 12 residents to be financially and therapeutically viable. Edmonds declined to permit Oxford House to stay in a single-family residential zone, but passed an ordinance listing group homes as permitted uses in multifamily and general commercial zones.

Edmonds sued Oxford House in the United States District Court for the Western District of Washington seeking a declaration that the FHA does not constrain the City's zoning code family definition rule. Oxford House counterclaimed under the FHA, charging the City with failure to make a “reasonable accommodation” permitting maintenance of the group home in a single-family zone. The United States filed a separate action on the same FHA-“reasonable accommodation” ground, and the two cases were consolidated....

The Ninth Circuit's decision [holding the exemption inapplicable] conflicts with an Eleventh Circuit decision declaring exempt under §3607(b)(1) a family definition provision similar to the Edmonds prescription.

II.

The sole question before the Court is whether Edmonds' family composition rule qualifies as a “restrictio[n] regarding the maximum number of occupants permitted to occupy a dwelling” within the meaning of the FHA's absolute exemption. 42 U.S.C. §3607(b)(1).^1 In answering this question, we are mindful of the Act's stated policy “to provide, within constitutional limitations, for fair housing throughout the United States.” §3601. We also note precedent recognizing the FHA's “broad and inclusive” compass, and therefore according a “generous construction” to the Act's complaint-filing provision. Accordingly, we regard this case as an instance in which an exception to “a general statement of policy” is sensibly read “narrowly in order to preserve the primary operation of the [policy].”

A.

Congress enacted §3607(b)(1) against the backdrop of an evident distinction between municipal land use restrictions and maximum occupancy restrictions.

Land use restrictions designate “districts in which only compatible uses are allowed and incompatible uses are excluded.” D. Mandelker, Land Use Law §4.16, pp. 113–114 (3d ed. 1993). These restrictions typically categorize uses as single-family residential, multiple-family residential, commercial, or industrial.

Land use restrictions aim to prevent problems caused by the “pig in the parlor instead of the barnyard.” Village of Euclid v. Ambler Realty Co., 272 U.S. 365, 388 (1926). In particular, reserving land for single-family residences preserves the character of neighborhoods, securing “zones where family values, youth values, and the blessings of quiet seclusion and clean air make the area a sanctuary for people.” Village of Belle Terre v. Boraas, 416 U.S. 1, 9 (1974). To limit land use to single-family residences, a municipality must define the term “family”; thus family composition rules are an essential component of single-family residential use restrictions.

Maximum occupancy restrictions, in contradistinction, cap the number of occupants per dwelling, typically in relation to available floor space or the number and type of rooms. These restrictions ordinarily apply uniformly to all residents of all dwelling units. Their purpose is to protect health and safety by preventing dwelling overcrowding.

We recognized this distinction between maximum occupancy restrictions and land use restrictions in Moore v. City of East Cleveland, 431 U.S. 494 (1977). In Moore, the Court held unconstitutional the constricted definition of “family” contained in East Cleveland's housing ordinance. East Cleveland's ordinance “select[ed] certain categories of relatives who may live together and declare[d] that others may not”; in particular, East Cleveland's definition of “family” made “a crime of a grandmother's choice to live with her grandson.” In response to East Cleveland's argument that its aim was to prevent overcrowded dwellings, streets, and schools, we observed that the municipality's restrictive definition of family served the asserted, and undeniably legitimate, goals “marginally, at best.” Another East Cleveland ordinance, we noted, “specifically addressed ... the problem of overcrowding”; that ordinance tied “the maximum permissible occupancy of a dwelling to the habitable floor area.” Justice Stewart, in dissent, also distinguished restrictions designed to “preserv[e] the character of a residential area,” from prescription of “a minimum habitable floor area per person,” in the interest of community health and safety.

Section 3607(b)(1)'s language—“restrictions regarding the maximum number of occupants permitted to occupy a dwelling”—surely encompasses maximum occupancy restrictions.^2 But the formulation does not fit family composition rules typically tied to land use restrictions. In sum, rules that cap the total number of occupants in order to prevent overcrowding of a dwelling “plainly and unmistakably,” fall within §3607(b)(1)'s absolute exemption from the FHA's governance; rules designed to preserve the family character of a neighborhood, fastening on the composition of households rather than on the total number of occupants living quarters can contain, do not.

B.

Turning specifically to the City's Community Development Code, we note that the provisions Edmonds invoked against Oxford House, ECDC §16.20.010 and 21.30.010, are classic examples of a use restriction and complementing family composition rule. These provisions do not cap the number of people who may live in a dwelling. In plain terms, they direct that dwellings be used only to house families. Captioned “USES,” ECDC §16.20.010 provides that the sole “Permitted Primary Us[e]” in a single-family residential zone is “[s]ingle-family dwelling units.” Edmonds itself recognizes that this provision simply “defines those uses permitted in a single family residential zone.”

A separate provision caps the number of occupants a dwelling may house, based on floor area: “Floor Area. Every dwelling unit shall have at least one room which shall have not less than 120 square feet of floor area. Other habitable rooms, except kitchens, shall have an area of not less than 70 square feet. Where more than two persons occupy a room used for sleeping purposes, the required floor area shall be increased at the rate of 50 square feet for each occupant in excess of two.” ECDC §19.10.000. This space and occupancy standard is a prototypical maximum occupancy restriction.

Edmonds nevertheless argues that its family composition rule, ECDC §21.30.010, falls within §3607(b)(1), the FHA exemption for maximum occupancy restrictions, because the rule caps at five the number of unrelated persons allowed to occupy a single-family dwelling. But Edmonds' family composition rule surely does not answer the question: “What is the maximum number of occupants permitted to occupy a house?” So long as they are related “by genetics, adoption, or marriage,” any number of people can live in a house. Ten siblings, their parents and grandparents, for example, could dwell in a house in Edmonds' single-family residential zone without offending Edmonds' family composition rule.

Family living, not living space per occupant, is what ECDC §21.30.010 describes. Defining family primarily by biological and legal relationships, the provision also accommodates another group association: five or fewer unrelated people are allowed to live together as though they were family. This accommodation is the peg on which Edmonds rests its plea for §3607(b)(1) exemption. Had the City defined a family solely by biological and legal links, §3607(b)(1) would not have been the ground on which Edmonds staked its case. It is curious reasoning indeed that converts a family values preserver into a maximum occupancy restriction once a town adds to a related persons prescription “and also two unrelated persons.”

Edmonds additionally contends that subjecting single-family zoning to FHA scrutiny will “overturn Euclidian zoning” and “destroy the effectiveness and purpose of single-family zoning.” This contention both ignores the limited scope of the issue before us and exaggerates the force of the FHA's antidiscrimination provisions. We address only whether Edmonds' family composition rule qualifies for §3607(b)(1) exemption. Moreover, the FHA antidiscrimination provisions, when applicable, require only “reasonable” accommodations to afford persons with handicaps “equal opportunity to use and enjoy” housing. §3604(f)(1)(A) and (f)(3)(B).

The parties have presented, and we have decided, only a threshold question: Edmonds' zoning code provision describing who may compose a “family” is not a maximum occupancy restriction exempt from the FHA under §3607(b)(1). It remains for the lower courts to decide whether Edmonds' actions against Oxford House violate the FHA's prohibitions against discrimination set out in §3604(f)(1)(A) and (f)(3)(B). For the reasons stated, the judgment of the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit is Affirmed.

Note

In 1996, the Eighth Circuit addressed the issue of whether the limitation on eight unrelated persons in a single family dwelling violated the Fair Housing Act. The group home involved provided a residence for recovering alcoholics and drug addicts. The opinion follows.

Oxford House-C v. City of St. Louis

77 F.3d 249 (8th Cir. 1996)

GAFF, CIRCUIT JUDGE.

Rather than discriminating against Oxford House residents, the City's zoning code favors them on its face. The zoning code allows only three unrelated, nonhandicapped people to reside together in a single family zone, but allows group homes to have up to eight handicapped residents. Oxford House's own expert witness testified Oxford Houses with eight residents can provide significant therapeutic benefits for their members. The district court nevertheless found the City's zoning ordinances are discriminatory because the eight-person limit would destroy the financial viability of many Oxford Houses, and recovering addicts need this kind of group home. Even if the eight-person rule causes some financial hardship for Oxford Houses, however, the rule does not violate the Fair Housing Act if the City had a rational basis for enacting the rule.

We conclude the eight-person rule is rational. Cities have a legitimate interest in decreasing congestion, traffic, and noise in residential areas, and ordinances restricting the number of unrelated people who may occupy a single family residence are reasonably related to these legitimate goals. The City does not need to assert a specific reason for choosing eight as the cut-off point, rather than ten or twelve. “[E]very line drawn by a legislature leaves some out that might well have been included. That exercise of discretion, however, is a legislative, not a judicial, function.” We conclude the City's eight-person restriction has a rational basis and thus is valid under the Fair Housing Act.

Notes

Application of Americans with Disabilities Act to Housing Discrimination: It was previously noted that Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act will only apply to discrimination in housing that has been federally subsidized. When the Americans with Disabilities Act was passed in 1990, it was recognized that housing already had comprehensive coverage as a result of the 1988 amendments to the Fair Housing Act. Only public accommodations, such as inns, hotels, motels, and places of lodging, were subject to Title III of the ADA and its prohibitions relating to nondiscrimination on the basis of disability. 42 U.S.C. §12181(7)(a). Residential hotels, which serve both transient and more permanent populations, however, by virtue of their hybrid status, might be covered by both the FHA and the ADA in certain aspects of the facility. Independent Hous. Servs. v. Fillmore Ctr. Ass'n, 840 F. Supp. 1328 (N.D. Cal. 1993).

Many individuals with severe impairments could remain in their own homes with family members or living independently if they had attendant care. Whether attendant care of a particular type is mandated under a state array of social services has been the subject of debate in litigation. In two of the most interesting and creative challenges to denial of attendant care, the Third Circuit Court of Appeals addressed this issue in two different but related contexts.

In Easley v. Snider, 36 F.3d 297 (3d Cir. 1994), two women with severe disabilities sought attendant care services from the Pennsylvania Department of Public Welfare. Tracey Easley was living at home, and Florence Howard was living in a nursing home. The state attendant care program provided services such as getting in and out of bed, assistance with routine bodily functions (bathing, dressing, feeding), ancillary services (shopping, cleaning, laundry), and companion services (transportation, reading mail). The program mandated eligibility based on the individual being mentally alert, the purpose being that the recipient would be able to make decisions about and direct the services. Because Ms. Easley and Ms. Howard were not mentally alert, they had been determined to be ineligible. This criteria was challenged as violating the ADA because a reasonable modification of allowing a surrogate to direct the services could be provided.

The court upheld the eligibility requirement, examining the actual services provided through the program, whose objective is to achieve greater personal control and independence for individuals with physical disabilities. The proposed alteration of allowing a surrogate to make decisions would substantially alter the vision of the program. The court recognized that a state program that provides services to a subgroup of individuals with disabilities is permissible.

In a case in the same Circuit Court of Appeals, Helen L. v. Didario, 46 F.3d 325 (3d Cir. 1995), decided only a year later, the court also addressed the state program of providing attendant care and nursing home services to individuals with disabilities in Pennsylvania. In this case, the plaintiffs were nursing home residents who were both mentally alert, and who both needed assistance in daily living. The evidence indicated that they could function in their own homes with attendant care services. The state budget, however, did not have sufficient funds in the attendant care program, but did have funding in the nursing home budget. Although the cost in the nursing home was substantially greater than the cost would be for attendant care, both were denied attendant care services because of the allocation of these budget lines.

The court applied the least restrictive environment principles under the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act in finding that the denial of services in this case violated the ADA. The court held that since Pennsylvania had chosen to provide services under the ADA, it must do so in manner appropriate to the requirements of the statute.

Question

Do any of the FHA, ADA, or Section 504 requirements prohibit a provider of assisted living services from providing a “tiered” level of services that require that residents in such buildings qualify for each level? See, e.g., Herriot v. Channing House, 37 Nat'l Disability L. Rep.¶212 (N.D. Cal. 2008) (continuing care retirement community did not discriminate against individual who needed 24-hour care for mobility challenges and dementia; individual wanted to remain in independent living portion after developing needs that required skilled nursing and assisted living).

G. Enforcement

Enforcement of the Fair Housing Act is possible either through complaint to the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) or through direct complaint in court. Exhaustion of administrative remedies is not required before bringing action in court. The administrative complaint mechanism contemplates referral to state or local agencies if they exist and have substantially similar rights and remedies. The Attorney General of the United States may also bring action in cases where there appears to be a pattern or practice of resistance to compliance with the FHA. The Attorney General may also intervene in a private action. 42 U.S.C. §3610–3614. See also Shapiro v. Cadman Towers, Inc., reproduced in Section [C][1], supra.

The remedies available to successful complainants include civil penalties up to $50,000 and other appropriate relief. 42 U.S.C. §3612. Actual and punitive damages and appropriate equitable relief also are allowed. Attorneys' fees and costs may be awarded in the court's discretion. 42 U.S.C. §3612–3613. An unsettled issue with respect to Title II claims seeking damages in cases involving deinstitutionalization and community living is whether state agencies are immune from damage actions in such cases.

The primary obstacle to group home type living involves use of zoning restrictions to deny special use permits or otherwise prevent group homes from being located in residential areas. The leading zoning case is City of Cleburne v. Cleburne Living Center, 473 U.S. 432 (1985). In that case, the Supreme Court held that denial of a special use permit for the establishment of a group home for individuals with intellectual disabilities was an unconstitutional application of a municipal zoning ordinance. While finding that individuals with intellectual disabilities are not members of a suspect class so as to entitle them to the application of the strict scrutiny test, the Court found that the ordinance as it was applied was not rationally related to a legitimate state interest.

Plaintiffs have used a number of other theories involving zoning and land use restrictions to prevent the establishment of group homes. These have included theories limiting the number of residents and requirements relating to the definition of family. See, e.g., Pacific Shores Properties, LLC v. City of Newport Beach, 730 F.3d 1142 (9th Cir. 2013) (reversing and remanding FHA and ADA case involving group homes for those with drug and alcohol dependency; challenging city's ordinance that defined “single housekeeping units” in a way that excluded group home; court indicated that evidence existed that new law had been enacted for sole purpose of discriminating against such group homes and that issue should be addressed at trial); Cherry Hill Tp. v. Oxford House, Inc., 263 N.J. Super. 25, 621 A.2d 952 (App. Div. 1993) (definition of family found in zoning ordinance unconstitutional because it distinguished between related and unrelated individuals and applied an amorphous standard of domestic bond).

H. Summary

Disability discrimination in housing incorporates many of the concepts and principles addressed in previous chapters referencing the Americans with Disabilities Act. To be protected from discrimination, one must meet the definition of handicap or disability and be otherwise qualified. Discrimination includes a failure to provide a reasonable accommodation. The principle of least restrictive environment is applied. The issues of attitudinal discrimination, disparate impact because of policies and practices, and physical design are all incorporated into protections against housing discrimination. The Fair Housing Act Amendments of 1968, however, provide additional statutory protection in the context of both the sale and rental of housing. While Constitutional protections are also available whenever state action is an issue (such as in cases of zoning), it is rarely used because of the comprehensive statutory protections. There is protection against intentional discrimination as well as discrimination that is unintended, but which has a disparate impact on persons with disabilities. While this chapter's cases primarily involve federal statutes, state and local laws and ordinances can also come into play.

The combination of statutory and constitutional protections has given rise to a growing body of judicial interpretation that addresses a range of issues. Individuals with mental health concerns and contagious and infectious diseases (such as HIV) are the most likely to face intentional discrimination through refusal to sell or rent or more indirectly through refusals to grant zoning or private deed variances. Those with mobility impairments face architectural design barriers. Unfortunately, in the context of housing, generally only new construction must be designed to meet accessibility design standards. Most housing is not affected by Titles II and III of the Americans with Disabilities Act, which contemplate some retrofitting of facilities built before the effective date of the statutes. While tenants may be able to remove barriers, they must do so at their own expense and return the premises to their previous condition. Individuals with sensory impairments and some mental impairments find protection under both the FHA and the ADA for accommodations related to animals required for service or emotional support.

Perhaps the most challenging housing issue is a result of the current policy of independent living in the community. While both the FHA and the ADA provide a statutory basis for individuals with disabilities requiring substantial medical or supervisory services (those with serious illnesses or mental health concerns), the major obstacle appears not to be discrimination, but lack of funding to provide the needed services in the community. That is a barrier requiring political advocacy in addition to individual and systemic case advocacy in the courts.

1. The Fair Housing Act is the only major disability discrimination law that continues to use the term “handicap” instead of disability in its language, although the terms have virtually identical definitions. Throughout this chapter, except for judicial decision excerpts or direct reference to the statutory language, the authors generally use the term disability instead of handicap.

4. L.C. and E.W. are currently receiving treatment in community-based programs. Nevertheless, the case is not moot. As the District Court and Court of Appeals explained, in view of the multiple institutional placements L.C. and E.W. have experienced, the controversy they brought to court is “capable of repetition, yet evading review.”

5. We do not in this opinion hold that the ADA imposes on the States a “standard of care” for whatever medical services they render, or that the ADA requires States to “provide a certain level of benefits to individuals with disabilities.” (Thomas, J., dissenting). We do hold, however, that States must adhere to the ADA's nondiscrimination requirement with regard to the services they in fact provide.

1. Like the District Court and the Ninth Circuit, we do not decide whether Edmonds' zoning code provision defining “family,” as the City would apply it against Oxford House, violates the FHA's prohibitions against discrimination set out in 42 U.S.C. §3604(f)(1)(A) and (f)(3)(B).

2. The plain import of the statutory language is reinforced by the House Committee Report, which observes: “A number of jurisdictions limit the number of occupants per unit based on a minimum number of square feet in the unit or the sleeping areas of the unit. Reasonable limitations by governments would be allowed to continue, as long as they were applied to all occupants, and did not operate to discriminate on the basis of race, color, religion, sex, national origin, handicap or familial status.” H.R. Rep. No. 100-711, p. 31 (1988).

Chapter 9

Health Care and Insurance

A. Introduction and Overview

Access to health care services is important to all Americans. For individuals with disabilities, it can be even more critical. Yet these individuals often face greater challenges than other Americans in receiving health care services. One barrier is discrimination by health care providers. Individuals with HIV, for example, often face discrimination and refusal to treat, either directly or indirectly. Reasonable accommodations (such as interpreters for individuals who are deaf) and accessible facilities (such as ramps to enter buildings and equipment usable by individuals with mobility impairments) may be necessary to ensure access.

The cost of health care is the most significant barrier, however. Unless an individual has some type of health insurance coverage, health care costs can be prohibitive. Health insurance is most often available through an employment setting. Those without jobs may not be able to afford individual health insurance policies, and even if they can afford them, they may not be able to obtain health insurance or the insurance may not adequately cover the treatments needed by the individual. “Obamacare” or the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (“ACA”) has improved this situation considerably by attaining insurance for twenty million people, but there are still issues concerning coverage and availability.

This chapter highlights the key federal statutes that are designed to ensure nondiscrimination in health coverage and to some degree access to health insurance. These statutes include the Rehabilitation Act, the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act, the Genetic Information Non-Discrimination Act, the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (“ACA” or “Obamacare”) and various state laws prohibiting discrimination. It should be apparent that these protections are somewhat limited in ensuring adequate health care for individuals with disabilities.

In addition, the chapter highlights some of the unique employment aspects of health care providers who themselves have disabilities, and how nondiscrimination policies address those situations.

[1] Chapter Goals

The goals for this chapter are to:

Review the key principles applicable to health care access and persons with disabilities
Understand the major statutory provisions applicable to the health care setting and persons with disabilities
Understand how the protection of people with disabilities from discrimination and medical decisionmaking interrelate
Know the conflicts between medical decisionmaking concerning care, rationing, end of life decisions, right to die legislation, and the rights of persons with disabilities
Understand the issues raised for persons with disabilities by the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (“ACA”)
Understand how, in the health care setting, the ADA determines who is protected by the statute
Comprehend the law with regard to architectural barriers and access to health care, and requirements of the ADA for reasonable accommodation and auxiliary aids and services
Understand the judicial split over whether insurance policies are covered by Title III of the ADA
Know how federal statutes interrelate to solve problems related to parity between insurance coverage of mental and physical health impairments, and the gaps still existing in coverage
Know the protections afforded by the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (GINA) in access to insurance coverage

[2] Key Concepts and Definitions

Alterations

Generally refers to a physical change that affects the usability of a facility. Where such changes are made after the effective date of a particular statute (ADA, Rehabilitation Act), the facility must meet specific design standards with respect to those areas that are altered. Repainting and similar kinds of cosmetic changes do not generally trigger requirements under the ADA or Rehabilitation Act.

Americans with Disabilities Act

Enacted in 1990, the ADA requires in Titles II and III that there be no discrimination on the basis of disability in the provision of health care services in hospitals and in offices and clinics of health care providers.

Architectural barriers

This primarily refers to design features that indirectly affect the ability of individuals with mobility and sensory impairments to gain access to the physical facilities and structures of providers in the health care setting.

Auxiliary aids and services

Titles II and III of the ADA require that health care providers give auxiliary aids and services, such as interpreters, to persons with disabilities who need them.

Covered facilities and programs

All aspects of programs receiving federal financial assistance are subject to Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act, not just those receiving the assistance. For example, the university hospital in a university receiving a federal grant in its arts and sciences department will be covered. Both public entities and private entities may receive federal financial assistance.

Design standards

Detailed sets of regulations provide specifications for a range of issues affecting physical design for both mobility and sensory impairments. These are standards that relate to new construction or that should be followed when there are certain types of alterations or renovations. The standards cover aspects such as slopes, elevators, parking, seating in assembly areas, restrooms, and paths of travel. They also cover signage. Each program or service is unique, and it is impossible to provide with specificity every detail of what would make a program or service as a whole accessible.

Existing facilities

Federal statutes have differing requirements regarding retrofitting physical facilities that were built before the applicable date of the relevant statute. Generally, under Title III of the ADA, public accommodations such as health care offices must remove barriers to the extent it is readily achievable to do so. For private providers of public accommodations receiving federal financial assistance, Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act requires that barriers in existing facilities be removed so that the program is accessible when viewed in its entirety.

Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act (“GINA”)

Federal statute that forbids discrimination in insurance based on the insured's and his family's genetic information and family members' manifestation of disease.

Health insurance policies and the ADA

There is a question as to whether the substance of the policies of health insurers is governed by Title III of the ADA as a public accommodation. If it is, health insurance policies would not be permitted to write policies that discriminate against particular illnesses or against persons with disabilities.

Licensing

Governmental agencies (primarily at the state level) engage in numerous licensing programs that could be covered under Title II of the ADA. These include licensing of businesses (such as building permits) and professional licensing (including health care professions).

Medical decisionmaking

There is a question as to whether the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act apply to medical decisions concerning treatment, end-of life decisions, etc.

Mental health parity

Refers to the concept that insurance coverage of mental and physical illnesses should be the same. Historically, there existed a large gap between the coverage provided for mental and physical illnesses. Congress has passed various statutes that attempt to close this gap, but not one of them does so one hundred percent.

New construction

Depending on the applicable date of the statute at issue (Title III or Section 504), a specific set of detailed design standards apply to new construction by entities providing accommodations to the public, such as offices of health professionals.

Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act

“Obamacare” or the “ACA” was passed to give health insurance coverage to millions more Americans who previously had no health insurance because of health status, pre-existing conditions, or expense. While there are problems related to the ACA—specifically many doctors' and hospitals' refusals to accept payment by ACA insurance companies and some insurance companies' refusals to participate—the ACA has improved health care access for individuals with disabilities.

Public accommodations

Within Title III of the ADA, this refers to private entities that provide accommodations open to the public such as the offices of health care professionals. Title II (for state and local governmentally provided programs) and Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act (for all entities receiving federal financial assistance) often, but not always, provide for similar requirements as Title III for access to physical facilities and nondiscrimination. The remedies under Title III, however, differ from those under Title II and Section 504.

Reasonable accommodations

Unlike most civil rights statutes, the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act require more than nondiscrimination. They also require reasonable accommodation. Some of the requirements are spelled out in regulatory and statutory language (although generally not as all inclusive listings). Reasonable accommodations include both auxiliary aids and services (such as interpreters) and modification of policies, practices, and procedures (such as allowing assistance animals in places where they are ordinarily prohibited).

This requirement is not intended to require unduly burdensome (administratively or financially) accommodations. Nor is it intended to require that fundamental alterations to a program be made. Case law highlights that the burden is generally on the program to demonstrate that a requested accommodation is not reasonable. It also demonstrates that federal statutes contemplate individualized determinations and an interactive process in determining what accommodations would be reasonable.

Individuals seeking accommodations are not entitled to their preferred or a best accommodation. The accommodation should be reasonable and effective. What is unclear at present is whether the accommodation must be “necessary” for it to be required.

Right to Die Legislation

A number of states have passed legislation that gives patients the right to take medication to end their lives under specific, restricted circumstances.

Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act

Section 504 prohibits discrimination against persons with disabilities in programs receiving federal financial assistance. Many ADA Title III programs that provide accommodations for the public receive federal financial assistance, and are therefore also covered by Section 504. Many programs subject primarily to Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act and Title II (such as public hospitals) may have within them entities subject to Title III, such as bookstores,.pngt shops, or Title II entities may lease or use or facilitate private programs. The determination of which requirements apply—Titles II, III, and/or Section 504—and how they relate can be complex and challenging.

Self evaluation

Title II of the ADA requires that state and local governmental programs conduct a self evaluation of the barriers in their programs and prepare a transition plan for addressing barriers.

B. Nondiscrimination in Health Care Services

Until the 1990 passage of the Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), 42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq., the only major protection from nondiscrimination by health care providers was under Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act, 29 U.S.C. §794. This section applies only to recipients of federal financial assistance, however, leaving most individuals with disabilities with little remedy against discrimination. Most courts hold that receipt of Medicare or Medicaid constitutes federal financial assistance. Therefore, physicians and hospitals accepting these payments are covered by Section 504.

The ADA of 1990 broadened the protection for persons with disabilities against discrimination in the provision of health care services. Title II prohibits state and local governments providing health care services from discriminating based on disability. Title III prohibits discrimination by twelve categories of public accommodation. Included in the list as public accommodations are offices of health care providers. There is a conflict in the courts over whether health insurance contracts themselves are public accommodations subject to the anti-discrimination mandates of the ADA. For more discussion on the issue of whether health insurance contracts are public accommodations, see Section [D], below. For more information and cases on coverage, see LAURA ROTHSTEIN & JULIA IRZYK, DISABILITIES AND THE LAW Sec. 10:1 (2012 and cumulative supplement).

Two major Supreme Court cases have addressed significant issues related to health care and individuals with disabilities under the Rehabilitation Act.^1 The first is Alexander v. Choate, 469 U.S. 287 (1984), excerpted in Chapter 1, in which the Court addressed the question of whether the state of Tennessee's policy of reducing the number of annual days of inpatient hospital care covered by its state Medicaid program violates Section 504. This policy has a disparate impact on individuals with disabilities, but because the proposed fourteen-day limitation does not deny disabled individuals meaningful access to Medicaid services or exclude them from those services, the policy was held not to violate Section 504.

The second decision, Bowen v. American Hosp. Ass'n, below, followed several years of political activity beginning in 1982. The issues are quite complex, because they involve religious, moral, medical, ethical, and legal questions and policies. While this kind of issue is not frequently addressed by the courts today, the decision provides an interesting overview of how regulations are promulgated, the deference given to medical providers, and the challenges in addressing these issues in a particularly emotional situation. Note that the Court uses the term “handicapped” that was considered appropriate at the time, instead of the current favored term, “persons with disabilities.”

Bowen v. American Hospital Ass'n

476 U.S. 610 (1986)

STEVENS, J., announced the judgment of the Court.

I.

The American Medical Association, the American Hospital Association, and several other respondents challenge the validity of Final Rules promulgated on January 12, 1984, by the Secretary of the Department of Health and Human Services. These Rules establish “Procedures relating to health care for handicapped infants,” and in particular require the posting of informational notices, authorize expedited access to records and expedited compliance actions, and command state child protective services agencies to “prevent instances of unlawful medical neglect of handicapped infants.”

Although the Final Rules comprise six parts, only the four mandatory components are challenged here.^2 Subsection (b) is entitled “Posting of informational notice” and requires every “recipient health care provider that provides health care services to infants in programs or activities receiving Federal financial assistance”—a group to which we refer generically as “hospitals”—to post an informational notice in one of two approved forms. Both forms include a statement that §504 prohibits discrimination on the basis of handicap, and indicate that because of this prohibition “nourishment and medically beneficial treatment (as determined with respect for reasonable medical judgments) should not be withheld from handicapped infants solely on the basis of their present or anticipated mental or physical impairments.” The notice's statement of the legal requirement does not distinguish between medical care for which parental consent has been obtained and that for which it has not. The notice must identify the telephone number of the appropriate child protective services agency and, in addition, a toll-free number for the Department that is available 24 hours a day. Finally, the notice must state that the “identity of callers will be kept confidential” and that federal law prohibits retaliation “against any person who provides information about possible violations.”

Subsection (c), which contains the second mandatory requirement, sets forth “Responsibilities of recipient state child protective services agencies.” Subsection (c) does not mention §504 (or any other federal statute) and does not even use the word “discriminate.” It requires every designated agency to establish and maintain procedures to ensure that “the agency utilizes its full authority pursuant to state law to prevent instances of unlawful medical neglect of handicapped infants.” Mandated procedures must include (1) “[a] requirement that health care providers report on a timely basis ... known or suspected instances of unlawful medical neglect of handicapped infants,” (2) a method by which the state agency can receive timely reports of such cases, (3) “immediate” review of those reports, including “on-site investigation,” where appropriate, (4) protection of “medically neglected handicapped infants” including, where appropriate, legal action to secure “timely court order[s] to compel the provision of necessary nourishment and medical treatment,” and (5) “[t]imely notification” to HHS of every report of “suspected unlawful medical neglect” of handicapped infants. The preamble to the Final Rules makes clear that this subsection applies “where a refusal to provide medically beneficial treatment is a result, not of decisions by a health care provider, but of decisions by parents.”

The two remaining mandatory regulations authorize “[e]xpedited access to records” and “[e]xpedited action to effect compliance.” Subsection (d) provides broadly for immediate access to patient records on a 24-hour basis, with or without parental consent, “when, in the judgment of the responsible Department official, immediate access is necessary to protect the life or health of a handicapped individual.” Subsection (e) likewise dispenses with otherwise applicable requirements of notice to the hospital “when, in the judgment of the responsible Department official, immediate action to effect compliance is necessary to protect the life or health of a handicapped individual.” The expedited compliance provision is intended to allow “the government [to] see[k] a temporary restraining order to sustain the life of a handicapped infant in imminent danger of death.” Like the provision affording expedited access to records, it applies without regard to whether parental consent to treatment has been withheld or whether the matter has already been referred to a state child protective services agency.

II.

The Final Rules represent the Secretary's ultimate response to an April 9, 1982, incident in which the parents of a Bloomington, Indiana, infant with Down's syndrome and other handicaps refused consent to surgery to remove an esophageal obstruction that prevented oral feeding. On April 10, the hospital initiated judicial proceedings to override the parents' decision, but an Indiana trial court, after holding a hearing the same evening, denied the requested relief. On April 12 the court asked the local Child Protection Committee to review its decision. After conducting its own hearing, the Committee found no reason to disagree with the court's ruling. The infant died six days after its birth.

Citing “heightened public concern” in the aftermath of the Bloomington Baby Doe incident, on May 18, 1982, the director of the Department's Office of Civil Rights, in response to a directive from the President, “remind[ed]” health care providers receiving federal financial assistance that newborn infants with handicaps such as Down's syndrome were protected by §504.

This notice was followed, on March 7, 1983, by an “Interim Final Rule” contemplating a “vigorous federal role.” The Interim Rule required health care providers receiving federal financial assistance to post “in a conspicuous place in each delivery ward, each maternity ward, each pediatric ward, and each nursery, including each intensive care nursery” a notice advising of the applicability of §504 and the availability of a telephone “hotline” to report suspected violations of the law to HHS. Like the Final Rules, the Interim Rule also provided for expedited compliance actions and expedited access to records and facilities when, “in the judgment of the responsible Department official,” immediate action or access was “necessary to protect the life or health of a handicapped individual.” The Interim Rule took effect on March 22.

On April 6, 1983, respondents American Hospital Association et al. filed a complaint in the Federal District Court for the Southern District of New York seeking a declaration that the Interim Final Rule was invalid and an injunction against its enforcement. Little more than a week later, on April 14, in a similar challenge brought by the American Academy of Pediatrics and other medical institutions, the Federal District Court for the District of Columbia declared the Interim Final Rule “arbitrary and capricious and promulgated in violation of the Administrative Procedure Act.” The District Judge in that case “conclude[d] that haste and inexperience ha[d] resulted in agency action based on inadequate consideration” of several relevant concerns and, in the alternative, found that the Secretary had improperly failed to solicit public comment before issuing the Rule.

On July 5, 1983, the Department issued new “Proposed Rules” on which it invited comment. Like the Interim Final Rule, the Proposed Rules required hospitals to post informational notices in conspicuous places and authorized expedited access to records to be followed, if necessary, by expedited compliance action. In a departure from the Interim Final Rule, however, the Proposed Rules required federally assisted state child protective services agencies to utilize their “full authority pursuant to State law to prevent instances of medical neglect of handicapped infants.” Mandated procedures mirrored those contained in the Final Rules described above. The preamble and appendix to the Proposed Rules did not acknowledge that hospitals and physicians lack authority to perform treatment to which parents have not given their consent.

After the period for notice and comment had passed, HHS, on December 30, 1983, promulgated the Final Rules and announced that they would take effect on February 13, 1984. On March 12 of that year respondents American Hospital Association et al. amended their complaint and respondents American Medical Association et al. filed suit to declare the new regulations invalid and to enjoin their enforcement. The actions were consolidated....

IV.

The Solicitor General is correct that “handicapped individual” as used in §504 includes an infant who is born with a congenital defect. If such an infant is “otherwise qualified” for benefits under a program or activity receiving federal financial assistance, §504 protects him from discrimination “solely by reason of his handicap.” It follows ... that handicapped infants are entitled to “meaningful access” to medical services provided by hospitals, and that a hospital rule or state policy denying or limiting such access would be subject to challenge under §504.

However, no such rule or policy is challenged, or indeed has been identified, in this case. Nor does this case involve a claim that any specific individual treatment decision violates §504. This suit is not an enforcement action, and as a consequence it is not necessary to determine whether §504 ever applies to individual medical treatment decisions involving handicapped infants. Respondents brought this litigation to challenge the four mandatory components of the Final Rules on their face, and the Court of Appeals' judgment which we review merely affirmed the judgment of the District Court which “declared invalid and enjoined enforcement of [the final] regulations, purportedly promulgated pursuant to section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973.”

V.

It is an axiom of administrative law that an agency's explanation of the basis for its decision must include “a ‘rational connection between the facts found and the choice made.’” Agency deference has not come so far that we will uphold regulations whenever it is possible to “conceive a basis” for administrative action.

Before examining the Secretary's reasons for issuing the Final Rules, it is essential to understand the pre-existing state-law framework governing the provision of medical care to handicapped infants. In broad outline, state law vests decisional responsibility in the parents, in the first instance, subject to review in exceptional cases by the State acting as parens patriae. Prior to the regulatory activity culminating in the Final Rules, the Federal Government was not a participant in the process of making treatment decisions for newborn infants. We presume that this general framework was familiar to Congress when it enacted §504. It therefore provides an appropriate background for evaluating the Secretary's action in this case.

The Secretary has identified two possible categories of violations of §504 as justifications for federal oversight of handicapped infant care. First, he contends that a hospital's refusal to furnish a handicapped infant with medically beneficial treatment “solely by reason of his handicap” constitutes unlawful discrimination. Second, he maintains that a hospital's failure to report cases of suspected medical neglect to a state child protective services agency may also violate the statute. We separately consider these two possible bases for the Final Rules.

VI.

In the immediate aftermath of the Bloomington Baby Doe incident, the Secretary apparently proceeded on the assumption that a hospital's statutory duty to provide treatment to handicapped infants was unaffected by the absence of parental consent. He has since abandoned that view. Thus, the preamble to the Final Rules correctly states that when “a non-treatment decision, no matter how discriminatory, is made by parents, rather than by the hospital, section 504 does not mandate that the hospital unilaterally overrule the parental decision and provide treatment notwithstanding the lack of consent.” A hospital's withholding of treatment when no parental consent has been given cannot violate §504, for without the consent of the parents or a surrogate decisionmaker the infant is neither “otherwise qualified” for treatment nor has he been denied care “solely by reason of his handicap.”

Indeed, it would almost certainly be a tort as a matter of state law to operate on an infant without parental consent.

Now that the Secretary has acknowledged that a hospital has no statutory treatment obligation in the absence of parental consent, it has become clear that the Final Rules are not needed to prevent hospitals from denying treatment to handicapped infants. The Solicitor General concedes that the administrative record contains no evidence that hospitals have ever refused treatment authorized either by the infant's parents or by a court order. Even the Secretary never seriously maintained that posted notices, “hotlines,” and emergency on-site investigations were necessary to process complaints against hospitals that might refuse treatment requested by parents. The parental interest in calling such a refusal to the attention of the appropriate authorities adequately vindicates the interest in enforcement of §504 in such cases.

The Secretary's belated recognition of the effect of parental nonconsent is important, because the supposed need for federal monitoring of hospitals' treatment decisions rests entirely on instances in which parents have refused their consent. Thus, in the Bloomington, Indiana, case that precipitated the Secretary's enforcement efforts in this area, as well as in the University Hospital case that provided the basis for the summary affirmance in the case now before us, the hospital's failure to perform the treatment at issue rested on the lack of parental consent. The Secretary's own summaries of these cases establish beyond doubt that the respective hospitals did not withhold medical care on the basis of handicap and therefore did not violate §504; as a result, they provide no support for his claim that federal regulation is needed in order to forestall comparable cases in the future.

The Secretary's initial failure to recognize that withholding of consent by parents does not equate with discriminatory denial of treatment by hospitals likewise undermines the Secretary's findings in the preamble to his proposed rulemaking. In that statement, the Secretary cited four sources in support of the claim that “Section 504 [is] not being uniformly followed.” None of the cited examples, however, suggests that recipients of federal financial assistance, as opposed to parents, had withheld medical care on the basis of handicap.

In sum, there is nothing in the administrative record to justify the Secretary's belief that “discriminatory withholding of medical care” in violation of 504 provides any support for federal regulation.

VII.

As a backstop to his manifestly incorrect perception that withholding of treatment in accordance with parental instructions necessitates federal regulation, the Secretary contends that a hospital's failure to report parents' refusals to consent to treatment violates §504, and that past breaches of this kind justify federal oversight.

By itself, §504 imposes no duty to report instances of medical neglect—that undertaking derives from state-law reporting obligations or a hospital's own voluntary practice. Although a hospital's selective refusal to report medical neglect of handicapped infants might violate §504, the Secretary has failed to point to any specific evidence that this has occurred. The 49 actual investigations summarized in the preamble to the Final Rules do not reveal any case in which a hospital either failed, or was accused of failing, to make an appropriate report to a state agency. Nor can we accept the Solicitor General's invitation to infer discriminatory nonreporting from the studies cited in the Secretary's proposed rulemaking. Even assuming that cases in which parents have withheld consent to treatment for handicapped infants have gone unreported, that fact alone would not prove that the hospitals involved had discriminated on the basis of handicap rather than simply failed entirely to discharge their state-law reporting obligations, if any, a matter which lies wholly outside the nondiscrimination mandate of §504.

The particular reporting mechanism chosen by the Secretary—indeed the entire regulatory framework imposed on state child protective services agencies—departs from the nondiscrimination mandate of §504 in a more fundamental way. The mandatory provisions of the Final Rules omit any direct requirement that hospitals make reports when parents refuse consent to recommended procedures. Instead, the Final Rules command state agencies to require such reports, regardless of the state agencies' own reporting requirements (or lack thereof). Far from merely preventing state agencies from remaining calculatedly indifferent to handicapped infants while they tend to the needs of the similarly situated nonhandicapped, the Final Rules command state agencies to utilize their “full authority” to “prevent instances of unlawful medical neglect of handicapped infants.” The Rules effectively make medical neglect of handicapped newborns a state investigative priority, possibly forcing state agencies to shift scarce resources away from other enforcement activities—perhaps even from programs designed to protect handicapped children outside hospitals. The Rules also order state agencies to “immediate[ly]” review reports from hospitals, to conduct “on-site investigation[s],” and to take legal action “to compel the provision of necessary nourishment and medical treatment”—all without any regard to the procedures followed by state agencies in handling complaints filed on behalf of nonhandicapped infants. These operating procedures were imposed over the objection of several state child protective services agencies that the requirement that they turn over reports to HHS “conflicts with the confidentiality requirements of state child abuse and neglect statutes”—thereby requiring under the guise of nondiscrimination a service which state law denies to the nonhandicapped.

The complaint-handling process the Secretary would impose on unwilling state agencies is totally foreign to the authority to prevent discrimination conferred on him by §504. “Section 504 seeks to assure evenhanded treatment,” “neither the language, purpose, nor history of §504 reveals an intent to impose an affirmative-action obligation” on recipients of federal financial assistance. The Solicitor General also recognizes that §504 is concerned with discrimination and with discrimination alone. In his attempt to distinguish the Secretary's 1976 determination that it “is beyond the authority of section 504” to promulgate regulations “concerning adequate and appropriate psychiatric care or safe and humane living conditions for persons institutionalized because of handicap or concerning payment of fair compensation to patients who perform work,” the Solicitor General explains:

“This conclusion of course was consistent with the fact that, as relevant here, Section 504 is essentially concerned only with discrimination in the relative treatment of handicapped and nonhandicapped persons and does not confer any absolute right to receive particular services or benefits under federally assisted programs.”

The Final Rules, however, impose just the sort of absolute obligation on state agencies that the Secretary had previously disavowed. The services state agencies are required to make available to handicapped infants are in no way tied to the level of services provided to similarly situated nonhandicapped infants. Instead, they constitute an “absolute right to receive particular services or benefits” under a federally assisted program. Even if a state agency were scrupulously impartial as between the protection it offered handicapped and nonhandicapped infants, it could still be denied federal funding for failing to carry out the Secretary's mission with sufficient zeal.

It is no answer to state, as does the Secretary, that these regulations are a necessary “‘metho[d] ... to give reasonable assurance’ of compliance.” For while the Secretary can require state agencies to document their own compliance with §504, nothing in that provision authorizes him to commandeer state agencies to enforce compliance by other recipients of federal funds (in this instance, hospitals). State child protective services agencies are not field offices of the HHS bureaucracy, and they may not be conscripted against their will as the foot soldiers in a federal crusade.

VIII.

Even according the greatest respect to the Secretary's action, however, deference cannot fill the lack of an evidentiary foundation on which the Final Rules must rest. The Secretary's basis for federal intervention is perceived discrimination against handicapped infants in violation of §504, and yet the Secretary has pointed to no evidence that such discrimination occurs.

The need for a proper evidentiary basis for agency action is especially acute in this case because Congress has failed to indicate, either in the statute or in the legislative history, that it envisioned federal superintendence of treatment decisions traditionally entrusted to state governance. “[W]e must assume that the implications and limitations of our federal system constitute a major premise of all congressional legislation, though not repeatedly recited therein.” Congress therefore “will not be deemed to have significantly changed the federal-state balance”—or to have authorized its delegates to do so—“unless otherwise the purpose of the Act would be defeated.” “[I]t must appear that there are findings, supported by evidence, of the essential facts ... which would justify [the Secretary's] conclusion.” The administrative record does not contain the reasoning and evidence that is necessary to sustain federal intervention into a historically state-administered decisional process that appears—for lack of any evidence to the contrary—to be functioning in full compliance with §504.

[T]he Department regards its mission as one principally concerned with the quality of medical care for handicapped infants rather than with the implementation of §504. We could not quarrel with a decision by the Department to concentrate its finite compliance resources on instances of life-threatening discrimination rather than instances in which merely elective care has been withheld. But nothing in the statute authorizes the Secretary to dispense with the law's focus on discrimination and instead to employ federal resources to save the lives of handicapped newborns, without regard to whether they are victims of discrimination by recipients of federal funds or not. Section 504 does not authorize the Secretary to give unsolicited advice either to parents, to hospitals, or to state officials who are faced with difficult treatment decisions concerning handicapped children. We may assume that the “qualified professionals” employed by the Secretary may make valuable contributions in particular cases, but neither that assumption nor the sincere conviction that an immediate “on-site investigation” is “necessary to protect the life or health of a handicapped individual” can enlarge the statutory powers of the Secretary.

The administrative record demonstrates that the Secretary has asserted the authority to conduct on-site investigations, to inspect hospital records, and to participate in the decisional process in emergency cases in which there was no colorable basis for believing that a violation of §504 had occurred or was about to occur. The District Court and the Court of Appeals correctly held that these investigative actions were not authorized by the statute and that the regulations which purport to authorize a continuation of them are invalid.

The judgment of the Court of Appeals is affirmed.

Questions

1. Does this decision strike down the use of infant care review committees? See footnote 2 in the Bowen decision.

2. The Section 504 regulations included a provision that the decision about whether to treat or not should not include consideration of the negative effect of the child's condition on others, including parents, siblings, and society. Is it possible not to consider those effects? Should the impact on others be a valid consideration?

Notes

1. Institutional Ethics Committees: The types of committees suggested in the regulations addressed in the Bowen case have been implemented in a number of hospitals. There are several practical issues relating to the implementation of such committees. These issues include how members of the committee are appointed, what their term of appointment is and how they are removed, what their decisionmaking authority is, what liability is involved, and other practical issues relating to when they meet, whether they vote or reach consensus, etc. For a discussion of these issues, see Alexander Morgan Capron, Legal Perspectives on Institutional Ethics Committees, 11 J. COLLEGE & UNIV. L. 417 (1985); Thaddeus Mason Pope, Multi-Institutional Healthcare Ethics Committees: The Procedurally Fair Internal Dispute Resolution Mechanism, 31 CAMPBELL L. REV. 257 (2009) (discussing Institutional Ethics Committees' role, function, prevalence, and shortcomings); Thaddeus Mason Pope, The Growing Power of Healthcare Ethics Committees Heightens Due Process Concerns, 15 CARDOZO J. CONFLICT RESOL. 425 (2014) (discussing the growing influence of the committees); Anya E. R. Prince & Arlene M. Davis, Navigating Professional Norms in an Inter-Professional Environment: The “Practice” of Healthcare Ethics Committees, 15 CONN. PUB. INT. L.J. 115 (2016) (discussing the history, structure, and membership of Healthcare Ethics Committees).

2. Values as Factors in Decisionmaking: Decisionmaking involving issues of seriously ill newborns obviously includes values that will be incorporated into standards to be applied. One's moral and/or religious perspective on life will affect whether any of the following standards are applied: biological life should be preserved at all costs; what the infant would want; can the infant relate to life adequately to have some meaning; the cost of the infant's life to others. For a discussion of these issues, see Rebecca Dresser, Life, Death, and Incompetent Patients: Conceptual Infirmities and Hidden Values in the Law, 28 ARIZ. L. REV. 373 (1986).

3. Medicaid Prioritization and Health Care Rationing: As a response to rising health care costs, many states base Medicaid funding prioritization on certain conditions. Medicaid is federally funded, but state administered. For that reason both Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act and Title II of the Americans with Disabilities Act could be implicated in challenges that such plans discriminate on the basis of disability in violation of federal discrimination laws. What is the likelihood that plaintiffs would succeed in such an action? For a discussion of this issue, see Robert J. Moosy, Jr., Health Care Prioritization and the ADA: The Oregon Plan 1991–1993, 31 HOUS. L. REV. 265 (1994); David Orentlicher, Rationing and the Americans with Disabilities Act, 217 JAMA 308 (1994).

4. The ADA and the Rehabilitation Act were amended by the ADA Amendments Act of 2008 (ADAAA), which took effect on January 1, 2009. As earlier chapters demonstrate, Congress passed the amendments to overturn a number of United States Supreme Court opinions interpreting the ADA and their application by the lower federal courts that had the effect of significantly narrowing the definition of individuals with disabilities. Some of these opinions concluded that persons with serious impairments such as intellectual disabilities, deafness, diabetes and cancer were not individuals with disabilities and were therefore not protected by the Act from discrimination. The ADAAA has the effect of including a broader group of persons within the definition of persons with disabilities. For more information on the ADAAA, see Chapters 1 and 2.

—————

The Bowen decision provides a perspective on the application of Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act to treatment of seriously ill newborns. The decision does not really address the discrimination issue, but rather focuses on the validity of the regulations on this issue promulgated pursuant to Section 504.

The following decision focuses more on the discrimination issue in the context of the ADA and Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act with respect to withdrawal of treatment from a seriously ill newborn.

In re Baby K

832 F. Supp. 1022 (E.D. Va. 1993)

HILTON, DISTRICT JUDGE:

Findings of Fact

1. Plaintiff Hospital is a general acute care hospital located in Virginia that is licensed to provide diagnosis, treatment, and medical and nursing services to the public as provided by Virginia law. Among other facilities, the Hospital has a Pediatric Intensive Care Department and an Emergency Department.

2. The Hospital is a recipient of federal and state funds including those from Medicare and Medicaid and is a “participating hospital” pursuant to 42 U.S.C. §1395cc.

3. The Hospital and its staff (including emergency doctors, pediatricians, neonatologists and pediatric intensivists) treat sick children on a daily basis.

4. Defendant Ms. H, a citizen of the Commonwealth of Virginia, is the biological mother of Baby K, an infant girl born by Caesarean section at the Hospital on October 13, 1992. Baby K was born with anencephaly.

5. Anencephaly is a congenital defect in which the brain stem is present but the cerebral cortex is rudimentary or absent. There is no treatment that will cure, correct, or ameliorate anencephaly. Baby K is permanently unconscious and cannot hear or see. Lacking a cerebral function, Baby K does not feel pain. Baby K has brain stem functions primarily limited to reflexive actions such as feeding reflexes (rooting, sucking, swallowing), respiratory reflexes (breathing, coughing), and reflexive responses to sound or touch. Baby K has a normal heart rate, blood pressure, liver function, digestion, kidney function, and bladder function and has gained weight since her birth. Most anencephalic infants die within days of birth.

6. Baby K was diagnosed prenatally as being anencephalic. Despite the counselling of her obstetrician and neonatologist that she terminate her pregnancy, Ms. H refused to have her unborn child aborted.

7. A Virginia court of competent jurisdiction has found defendant Mr. K, a citizen of the Commonwealth of Virginia, to be Baby K's biological father.

8. Ms. H and Mr. K have never been married.

9. Since Baby K's birth, Mr. K has, at most, been only distantly involved in matters relating to the infant. Neither the Hospital nor Ms. H ever sought Mr. K's opinion or consent in providing medical treatment to Baby K.

10. Because Baby K had difficulty breathing immediately upon birth, Hospital physicians provided her with mechanical ventilator treatment to allow her to breathe.

11. Within days of Baby K's birth, Hospital medical personnel urged Ms. H to permit a “Do Not Resuscitate Order” for Baby K that would discontinue ventilator treatment. Her physicians told her that no treatment existed for Baby K's anencephalic condition, no therapeutic or palliative purpose was served by the treatment, and that ventilator care was medically unnecessary and inappropriate. Despite this pressure, Ms. H continued to request ventilator treatment for her child.

12. Because of Ms. H's continued insistence that Baby K receive ventilator treatment, her treating physicians requested the assistance of the Hospital's “Ethics Committee” in overriding the mother's wishes.

13. A three person Ethics Committee subcommittee, composed of a family practitioner, a psychiatrist, and a minister, met with physicians providing care to Baby K. On October 22, 1992, the group concluded that Baby K's ventilator treatment should end because “such care is futile” and decided to “wait a reasonable time for the family to help the caregiver terminate aggressive therapy.” If the family refused to follow this advice, the committee recommended that the Hospital should “attempt to resolve this through our legal system.”

14. Ms. H subsequently rejected the committee's recommendation. Before pursuing legal action to override Ms. H's position, the Hospital decided to transfer the infant to another health care facility.

15. Baby K was transferred to a nursing home (“Nursing Home”) in Virginia on November 30, 1992 during a period when she was not experiencing respiratory distress and thus did not need ventilator treatment. A condition of the transfer was that the Hospital agreed to take the infant back if Baby K again developed respiratory distress to receive ventilator treatment which was unavailable at the Nursing Home. Ms. H agreed to this transfer.

16. Baby K returned to the Hospital on January 15, 1993 after experiencing respiratory distress to receive ventilator treatment. Hospital officials again attempted to persuade Ms. H to discontinue ventilator treatment for her child. Ms. H again refused. After Baby K could breathe on her own, she was transferred back to the Nursing Home on February 12, 1993.

17. Baby K again experienced breathing difficulties on March 3, 1993 and returned to the Hospital to receive ventilator treatment.

18. On March 15, 1993, Baby K received a tracheotomy, a procedure in which a breathing tube is surgically implanted in her windpipe, to facilitate ventilator treatment. Ms. H agreed to this operation.

19. After no longer requiring ventilator treatment, Baby K was transferred back to the Nursing Home on April 13, 1993 where she continues to live.

20. Baby K will almost certainly continue to have episodes of respiratory distress in the future. In the absence of ventilator treatment during these episodes, she would suffer serious impairment of her bodily functions and soon die.

21. Ms. H visits Baby K daily. The mother opposes the discontinuation of ventilator treatment when Baby K experiences respiratory distress because she believes that all human life has value, including her anencephalic daughter's life. Ms. H has a firm Christian faith that all life should be protected. She believes that God will work a miracle if that is his will. Otherwise, Ms. H believes, God, and not other humans, should decide the moment of her daughter's death. As Baby K's mother and as the only parent who has participated in the infant's care, Ms. H believes that she has the right to decide what is in her child's best interests.

22. On the Hospital's motion, a guardian ad litem to represent Baby K was appointed pursuant to Virginia Code §8.01-9.

23. Both the guardian ad litem and Mr. K share the Hospital's position that ventilator treatment should be withheld from Baby K when she experiences respiratory distress.

24. The Hospital has stipulated that it is not proposing to deny ventilator treatment to Baby K because of any lack of adequate resources or any inability of Ms. H to pay for the treatment.

Conclusions of Law

Pursuant to the Declaratory Judgment Act, 28 U.S.C. §2201, the Hospital has sought declaratory and injunctive relief under four federal statutes and one Virginia statute: the Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act, 42 U.S.C. §1395dd; the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, 29 U.S.C. §794; the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990, 42 U.S.C. §12101 et seq.; the Child Abuse Amendments of 1984, 42 U.S.C. §5102 et seq.; and the Virginia Medical Malpractice Act, Va.Code §8.01-581.1 et seq.

I. Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act

[Discussion of this issue omitted.]

II. Rehabilitation Act

Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act prohibits discrimination against an “otherwise qualified” handicapped individual, solely by reason of his or her handicap, under any program or activity receiving federal financial assistance. Hospitals such as plaintiff that accept Medicare and Medicaid funding are subject to the Act. Baby K is a “handicapped” and “disabled” person within the meaning of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973. A “handicapped individual” under the Rehabilitation Act “includes an infant who is born with a congenital defect.”

Section 504's plain text spells out the necessary scope of inquiry: Is Baby K otherwise qualified to receive ventilator treatment and is ventilator treatment being threatened with being denied because of an unjustified consideration of her anencephalic handicap? The Hospital has admitted that the sole reason it wishes to withhold ventilator treatment for Baby K over her mother's objections, is because of Baby K's anencephaly—her handicap and disability.

When the Rehabilitation Act was passed in 1973, Congress intended that discrimination on the basis of a handicap be treated in the same manner that Title VI of the Civil Rights Act treats racial discrimination. This analogy to race dispels any ambiguity about the extent to which Baby K has statutory rights not to be discriminated against on the basis of her handicap. It also shatters the Hospital's contention that ventilator treatment should be withheld because Baby K's recurring breathing troubles are intrinsically related to her handicap. No such distinction would be permissible within the context of racial discrimination. In addition, the Hospital was able to perform a tracheotomy on Baby K. This surgery was far more complicated than linking her to a ventilator to allow her to breathe. Just as an AIDS patient seeking ear surgery is “otherwise qualified” to receive treatment despite poor long term prospects of living, Baby K is “otherwise qualified” to receive ventilator treatment despite similarly dismal health prospects. Thus, the Hospital's desire to withhold ventilator treatment from Baby K over her mother's objections would violate the Rehabilitation Act.

III. Americans with Disabilities Act

Section 302 of the Americans with Disabilities Act (“ADA”) prohibits discrimination against disabled individuals by “public accommodations.” The Hospital is a public accommodation under the ADA.

Section 302(a) of the ADA states a general rule of nondiscrimination against the disabled:

“General rule. No individual shall be discriminated against on the basis of disability in the full and equal enjoyment of the goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, or accommodation of any place of public accommodations by any person who owns, leases (or leases to), or operates a place of public accommodation.” 42 U.S.C. §12182(a).

In contrast to the Rehabilitation Act, the ADA does not require that a handicapped individual be “otherwise qualified” to receive the benefits of participation. Further, section 302(b)(1)(A) of the ADA states that “[i]t shall be discriminatory to subject an individual or class of individuals on the basis of a disability ... to a denial of the opportunity of the individual or class to participate in or benefit from the goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, or accommodations of an entity.” 42 U.S.C. §12182(b)(1)(A)(i).

The Hospital asks this court for authorization to deny the benefits of ventilator services to Baby K by reason of her anencephaly. The Hospital's claim is that it is “futile” to keep alive an anencephalic baby, even though the mother has requested such treatment. But the plain language of the ADA does not permit the denial of ventilator services that would keep alive an anencephalic baby when those life-saving services would otherwise be provided to a baby without disabilities at the parent's request. The Hospital's reasoning would lead to the denial of medical services to anencephalic babies as a class of disabled individuals. Such discrimination against a vulnerable population class is exactly what the American with Disabilities Act was enacted to prohibit. The Hospital would therefore violate the ADA if it were to withhold ventilator treatment from Baby K.

IV. Child Abuse Act

[Discussion of application of Child Abuse Act, Virginia Medical Malpractice Act, and Constitutional and Common Law Issue omitted.]

For the foregoing reasons, the Hospital's request for a declaratory judgment that the withholding of ventilator treatment from Baby K would not violate the Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act, the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Child Abuse Amendments of 1984, and the Virginia Medical Malpractice Act should be DENIED. Under the Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act, the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and the Americans with Disabilities Act, the Hospital is legally obligated to provide ventilator treatment to Baby K. The court makes no ruling as to any rights or obligations under the Child Abuse Amendments of 1984 and under the Virginia Medical Malpractice Act.

Questions

The lower court in Baby K states that, unlike the Rehabilitation Act, the ADA does not require that an individual be otherwise qualified in order to state a claim. Does that statement make any sense? Isn't the requirement that an individual be otherwise qualified implicit in all disability discrimination statutes? Would a deaf patient with serious back problems who went to an ophthalmologist for treatment of the back problems, who subsequently refused to treat him, be able to claim discrimination on the basis of his disability (deafness)? Or would the ophthalmologist be able to claim that the patient is not otherwise qualified because the patient is not seeking the treatment for which the physician has expertise?

Notes

1. On appeal, the Fourth Circuit did not address the ADA claim. In re Baby K, 16 F.3d 590 (4th Cir. 1994). The court instead found that the hospital had violated the Emergency Medical Treatment and Active Labor Act, 42 U.S.C. §1395dd (b), (e)(3)(A), which mandates the provision of life-sustaining treatment in emergency situations. The appellate court did not comment on the ADA or Section 504.

2. The ADA and Standards of Emergency Care. Some commentators have questioned the role of courts in resolving “essentially medical matters.” For a discussion of this, see George J. Annas, Asking the Courts to Set the Standard of Emergency Care—The Case of Baby K, 330 NEW ENG. J. MED. 1542 (1994). See also Schrode, Life in Limbo: Revising Policies for Permanently Unconscious Patients, 31 HOUS. L. REV. 1609 (1995).

3. Right to Die and Assisted Suicide. The Bowen and Baby K cases focus on termination of treatment for seriously ill newborns and infants. The issues are somewhat different with respect to adults and others who are not infants regarding termination of treatment. In 1990, the Supreme Court in Cruzan v. Director, Missouri Dep't of Health, 497 U.S. 261 (1990), recognized a right to die in certain instances. That case involved a woman who was comatose and whose condition was irreversible. Since that time, there has been a great deal of media attention to the issue of the right to die by alert and competent individuals who are suffering from painful, terminal diseases. Substantial attention also has been given to the right to assisted suicide.

States have begun to consider a variety of responses to these difficult and complex legal, medical, ethical, and religious issues. Both Oregon and Washington passed laws that permit a terminally ill patient to request and receive medication to end his or her life. Both of these “Death with Dignity Acts” require that the patient be a state resident, be diagnosed by at least two physicians as terminal and within six months of death, be informed of medical options, be competent, and enter into the decision voluntarily. Both also require oral and written requests and two witnesses in addition to the physicians. Both specify that no person shall qualify solely because of age or disability. The Washington statute specifically states that the medication is to be self-administered, but although the intent behind the Oregon statute is for self-administration of medication, it is not explicit in the statute. See ORS §127.800 (2007); Rev. Code Wash. §70.245.010 (2009). Vermont, and California have passed similar measures. See VT. STAT. ANN. Tit. 18 §§5281–5293 (2013); CAL. HEALTH & SAFETY CODE §§443–443.22 (2015).

The Oregon statute took effect in 1997, while the Washington statute took effect in 2009. A study of ten years of experience with the Oregon statute revealed that only 341 persons ended their lives using the Act's protections of the 296,000 who died in Oregon during the same time period. See Dan Colburn, Death with Dignity Act Applies to Very Few, THE OREGONIAN (Aug. 5, 2009). There are also a few cases that address the issue. See Baxter v. State, 224 P.3d 1211 (Mont. 2009) (vacating a lower court ruling that there is a right to affirmatively end one's life under the Montana constitution, but holding doctors immune from prosecution when the patient consents to a lethal dose of medicine and self-administers the medication that causes death). The question of a right to die under the New Mexico constitution is under consideration by the New Mexico Supreme Court. Morris v. Brandenburg, 356 P.3d 564 (N.M. Ct. App. 2015) (overturning lower court's holding that a right exists), writ of certiorari granted, 8/31/15.

There is a question about whether these laws violate Title II of the ADA. A patient who meets the other requirements, but whose condition physically prevents self-administration may argue that the law discriminates against him because of his disability. How would the courts be likely to treat such a challenge? What if an individual who is severely disabled and in extreme pain, but not terminally ill, wishes to have such a prescription? Would the Oregon and Washington statutes be discriminatory on that basis?

The Oregon Death with Dignity Act has received a substantial amount of media attention. Many of its critics are individuals who are severely disabled. These groups sometimes argue that such statutes will be the precursor of statutes permitting euthanasia of individuals with severe disabilities. See Judge Weighs Suicide Law, WASHINGTON POST, Dec. 20, 1994, at A8.

The Supreme Court addressed the Oregon Death with Dignity Act, and held that the U.S. Attorney General may not bar dispensing controlled substances used for assisted suicide where there is a medical regime allowing that conduct. See Gonzales v. Oregon, 126 S. Ct. 904, 163 L. Ed. 2d 748 (2006).

For discussions of this issue, see Marc C. Siegel, Lethal Pity: The Oregon Death with Dignity Act, Its Implications for the Disabled, and the Struggle for Equality in an Able-Bodied World, 16 LAW & INEQ. J. 259 (1998); Stephen L. Mikochik, Assisted Suicide and Disabled People, 46 DEPAUL L. REV. 987 (1997).

4. End of Life Issues. A controversial issue with disability rights implications involves who can make decisions about end of life. The Terry Schiavo case in 2005 received substantial media attention and interest by the public. The case involved a dispute between the husband of Terry Schiavo, who wanted to withhold nutrition and hydration because of his acceptance of medical evidence that she no longer had viable brain activity, and Schiavo's parents, who wanted to continue with her feeding tube. There were a number of judicial decisions addressing various legal theories in this case. One of those decisions was based on disability discrimination law. In Schiavo v. Schiavo, 403 F.3d 1289 (11th Cir. 2005), the court held that even if the hospice that cared for Terry Schiavo was a public accommodation, its compliance with the state judge's order to withhold nutrition and hydration was not discrimination on the basis of disability. The court held that neither the ADA nor the Rehabilitation Act was intended to apply to decisions involving the termination of life support or medical treatment. A number of cases have since Schiavo held that the ADA and Rehabilitation Act are not applicable to end of life medical decisions. See Burger v. Bloomberg, 418 F.3d 882, 883 (8th Cir. 2005); Fitzgerald v. Corr. Corp. of Am., 403 F.3d 1134, 1144 (10th Cir. 2005). Compare Tidwell v. Stringer, 2014 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 75773, 2014 WL 2508955, at 3 (S.D. Ala. June 3, 2014) (stating that the cases do not stand for the proposition that the ADA and Rehabilitation Acts do not apply to medical decisions, but rather that, in those cases, the plaintiffs failed to meet the essential elements of their claims).

5. National Health Care Reform. There was no question that the country needed health care reform by the time President Obama took office. Nearly 47 million persons lacked insurance, and, therefore, found it difficult to secure health care. President Obama made health care reform one of the primary objectives of his presidency. The Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (“ACA”) was effective on March 23, 2010, and subsequently survived two challenges before the U.S. Supreme Court. People fear the high cost of the health care reform and potential governmental control over health care decisions. One of the greatest fears was that the government would intrude upon end of life decisions, requiring people who are old, sick and disabled to end their lives. While there is little support for this fear in the ACA, rationing of health care is an important issue to discuss. In effect, rationing of health care already occurs. Those who do not have health insurance generally do not get the care they need. A system that covers everyone will necessarily ration care, some say, or otherwise become prohibitively expensive. See Peter Singer, Why We Must Ration Health Care, NY TIMES (July 19, 2009). Others argue that cost cutting measures that change how health care is delivered in less expensive and more effective ways are viable alternatives to rationing. See Atul Gawande, et al., 10 Steps to Better Health Care, NY TIMES (Aug. 13, 2009).

Attorneys General of several states joined to challenge the ACA's constitutionality because of the provision that requires Americans to buy health insurance (the “individual mandate”). In National Federation of Independent Business v. Sebelius, 132 S. Ct. 2566 (2012), the Supreme Court held that the individual mandate was unconstitutional under the Commerce Clause and Necessary and Proper Clause powers, but upheld the individual mandate as constitutional under Congress's taxing power. The Court also held that the provision of the ACA that significantly expanded Medicaid was an invalid exercise of Congress's spending power, because it coerced the states to either accept the expansion or lose existing Medicaid funding. Subsequently, the Supreme Court rejected another challenge to the ACA. See King v. Burwell, 135 S. Ct. 2480 (2015) (holding that the tax credits for buying insurance under the ACA apply to both the exchanges established by the states and those established by the federal government when states refused to operate such exchanges).

Persons with disabilities have an important stake in the outcome of the health care reform because of their need for medical services. See Jessica L. Roberts, Health Law as Disability Rights Law, 97 MINN. L. REV. 1963 (2013), which addresses health care access for individuals with disabilities, and Mary Crossley, Disability Cultural Competence in the Medical Profession, 9 J. HEALTH L. & POL'Y 89 (2015). Disability advocates argued that health care reform is necessary, but they urged federal legislators to amend Medicaid to remove its institutional biases. That is, many persons with disabilities can get benefits under Medicaid only if they are living in institutional settings. Advocates argue that community-based care would be superior and less expensive. Thus, advocates urged Congress to pass the Community Living Assistance Services and Supports Act (CLASS) as part of the ACA. It was passed, but was later repealed. A second bill, the Community Choice Act, would have given support to families with persons with disabilities without forcing them into poverty by permitting them to collect Medicaid, and would remove the institutional bias of Medicaid. It never passed. See Marshall B. Kapp, Home and Community-Based Long-Term Services and Supports: Health Reform's Most Enduring Legacy?, 8 ST. LOUIS U.J. HEALTH L. & POL'Y 9, 27–28 (2014) (noting that by October of 2011, the Obama Administration announced that it would cease efforts to implement CLASS, Congress repealed the Act, and the President signed the repealing legislation).

Hypothetical Problem 9.1

Consider the following hypothetical problem after reading the Supreme Court opinion in Bragdon v. Abbott and the lower court's opinion on remand. In determining whether Shanon is a person with a disability, use the definition of disability recently enacted in the ADAAA.

Shanon Burke is a college student who attends State University. She has a history of asthma, and uses medication and an inhaler for her asthma. She returned to college in August 2016 and within a few weeks, there was a rapid spread among the students of the influenza virus. The University Health Services establishes a protocol for isolating students with the virus, which encourages sick students to stay in their room and to have their parents take them home as soon as possible. By mid-October, Shanon begins to feel ill with influenza symptoms of achiness, high fever, listlessness and vomiting. Because of her asthma, she experiences difficulty breathing. Shanon goes to the student health services, but when she arrives, the health services makes her enter through the backdoor into a “waiting room” for students with flu symptoms. Shanon goes into the waiting room, but the nurse tells her that the health services is overwhelmed and that she should call her parents (who live 6 hours away by car) to pick her up and take her home. The nurse also tells her she may go back to her dorm room for the next 8 hours, but that she should notify her roommate to evacuate the room. The nurse calls Shanon's roommate, Maria, and tells her to leave the room until the next day. The school will clean the room after Shanon leaves and then Maria will be permitted to return to the room.

Shanon is very sick and getting sicker by the moment. She calls her parents to find that they are both out of town, and will not be able to pick her up until the next day. Shanon cannot fly home because the FAA has promulgated a temporary rule stating that persons with flu symptoms may not fly. The Health Services refuses to allow Shanon to stay there because they consider Shanon a threat to the health of workers and other students at the Health Services. Shanon explains to the Health Services that her asthma is much worse and that she cannot breathe. Health Services refuses to give Shanon a bed and sends her back to her empty dorm room. Shanon has a bad night, and her parents arrive early the next day. Shanon can barely breathe and her parents rush her to the closest hospital emergency room where they begin to treat Shanon. While Shanon survives, her lungs are seriously damaged and her asthma is much worse as a result of the University Health Services' refusal to treat her.

Does Shanon have an action against the University under Title II or Title III of the ADA or under Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act? If so, what is the University's best defense? Analyze the arguments the University will make and the response that Shanon's attorney will make when Shanon brings a lawsuit against the University. What type of evidence should the University counsel attempt to find to support its case? What evidence should Shanon's attorney look for to support her case?

—————

The previous cases addressed discrimination by terminating treatment. Discrimination can occur, of course, in the context of denial of treatment or providing treatment in a segregated setting or only where additional costs are paid. Historically, litigation involving health care discrimination arises most frequently in the context of individuals seeking treatment who have HIV or AIDS. The following case addresses that issue. While previous Supreme Court cases had addressed health care in the context of the Rehabilitation Act, this was the first health care access case decided under the Americans with Disabilities Act.

Bragdon v. Abbott

524 U.S. 624 (1998)

JUSTICE KENNEDY delivered the opinion of the Court.

We address in this case the application of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (ADA) to persons infected with the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). We granted certiorari to review, first, whether HIV infection is a disability under the ADA when the infection has not yet progressed to the so-called symptomatic phase; and, second, whether the Court of Appeals, in affirming a grant of summary judgment, cited sufficient material in the record to determine, as a matter of law, that respondent's infection with HIV posed no direct threat to the health and safety of her treating dentist.

[Author's Note: This portion of the opinion addresses only whether HIV is a direct threat. The portion regarding whether Sidney Abbott is disabled under the ADA is described in Chapter 2.]

I

Respondent Sidney Abbott has been infected with HIV since 1986. When the incidents we recite occurred, her infection had not manifested its most serious symptoms. On September 16, 1994, she went to the office of petitioner Randon Bragdon in Bangor, Maine, for a dental appointment. She disclosed her HIV infection on the patient registration form. Petitioner completed a dental examination, discovered a cavity, and informed respondent of his policy against filling cavities of HIV-infected patients. He offered to perform the work at a hospital with no added fee for his services, though respondent would be responsible for the cost of using the hospital's facilities. Respondent declined.

The petition for certiorari presented three other questions for review. The questions stated:

3. When deciding under title III of the ADA whether a private health care provider must perform invasive procedures on an infectious patient in his office, should courts defer to the health care provider's professional judgment, as long as it is reasonable in light of then-current medical knowledge?

4. What is the proper standard of judicial review under title III of the ADA of a private health care provider's judgment that the performance of certain invasive procedures in his office would pose a direct threat to the health or safety of others?

5. Did petitioner, Randon Bragdon, D. M. D., raise a genuine issue of fact for trial as to whether he was warranted in his judgment that the performance of certain invasive procedures on a patient in his office would have posed a direct threat to the health or safety of others?

Of these, we granted certiorari only on question three. The question is phrased in an awkward way, for it conflates two separate inquiries. In asking whether it is appropriate to defer to petitioner's judgment, it assumes that petitioner's assessment of the objective facts was reasonable. The central premise of the question and the assumption on which it is based merit separate consideration.

Again, we begin with the statute. Notwithstanding the protection given respondent by the ADA's definition of disability, petitioner could have refused to treat her if her infectious condition “pose[d] a direct threat to the health or safety of others.” 42 U.S.C. §12182(b)(3). The ADA defines a direct threat to be “a significant risk to the health or safety of others that cannot be eliminated by a modification of policies, practices, or procedures or by the provision of auxiliary aids or services.” Ibid. Parallel provisions appear in the employment provisions of Title I. §§12111(3), 12113(b).

The ADA's direct threat provision stems from the recognition in School Bd. of Nassau Cty. v. Arline, 480 U.S. 273, 287 (1987), of the importance of prohibiting discrimination against individuals with disabilities while protecting others from significant health and safety risks, resulting, for instance, from a contagious disease. In Arline, the Court reconciled these objectives by construing the Rehabilitation Act not to require the hiring of a person who posed “a significant risk of communicating an infectious disease to others.” Congress amended the Rehabilitation Act and the Fair Housing Act to incorporate the language. It later relied on the same language in enacting the ADA. Because few, if any, activities in life are risk free, Arline and the ADA do not ask whether a risk exists, but whether it is significant.

The existence, or nonexistence, of a significant risk must be determined from the standpoint of the person who refuses the treatment or accommodation, and the risk assessment must be based on medical or other objective evidence. As a health care professional, petitioner had the duty to assess the risk of infection based on the objective, scientific information available to him and others in his profession. His belief that a significant risk existed, even if maintained in good faith, would not relieve him from liability. To use the words of the question presented, petitioner receives no special deference simply because he is a health care professional. It is true that Arline reserved “the question whether courts should also defer to the reasonable medical judgments of private physicians on which an employer has relied.” At most, this statement reserved the possibility that employers could consult with individual physicians as objective third-party experts. It did not suggest that an individual physician's state of mind could excuse discrimination without regard to the objective reasonableness of his actions.

Our conclusion that courts should assess the objective reasonableness of the views of health care professionals without deferring to their individual judgments does not answer the implicit assumption in the question presented, whether petitioner's actions were reasonable in light of the available medical evidence. In assessing the reasonableness of petitioner's actions, the views of public health authorities, such as the U.S. Public Health Service, CDC, and the National Institutes of Health, are of special weight and authority. The views of these organizations are not conclusive, however. A health care professional who disagrees with the prevailing medical consensus may refute it by citing a credible scientific basis for deviating from the accepted norm.

We have reviewed so much of the record as necessary to illustrate the application of the rule to the facts of this case. For the most part, the Court of Appeals followed the proper standard in evaluating the petitioner's position and conducted a thorough review of the evidence. Its rejection of the District Court's reliance on the Marianos affidavits was a correct application of the principle that petitioner's actions must be evaluated in light of the available, objective evidence. The record did not show that CDC had published the conclusion set out in the affidavits at the time petitioner refused to treat respondent.

A further illustration of a correct application of the objective standard is the Court of Appeals' refusal to give weight to the petitioner's offer to treat respondent in a hospital. Petitioner testified that he believed hospitals had safety measures, such as air filtration, ultraviolet lights, and respirators, which would reduce the risk of HIV transmission. Petitioner made no showing, however, that any area hospital had these safeguards or even that he had hospital privileges. His expert also admitted the lack of any scientific basis for the conclusion that these measures would lower the risk of transmission. Petitioner failed to present any objective, medical evidence showing that treating respondent in a hospital would be safer or more efficient in preventing HIV transmission than treatment in a well-equipped dental office.

We are concerned, however, that the Court of Appeals might have placed mistaken reliance upon two other sources. In ruling no triable issue of fact existed on this point, the Court of Appeals relied on the 1993 CDC Dentistry Guidelines and the 1991 American Dental Association Policy on HIV. This evidence is not definitive. As noted earlier, the CDC Guidelines recommended certain universal precautions which, in CDC's view, “should reduce the risk of disease transmission in the dental environment.” U.S. Dept. of Health and Human Services, Public Health Service, CDC, Recommended Infection Control Practices for Dentistry. The Court of Appeals determined that, “[w]hile the guidelines do not state explicitly that no further risk-reduction measures are desirable or that routine dental care for HIV-positive individuals is safe, those two conclusions seem to be implicit in the guidelines' detailed delineation of procedures for office treatment of HIV-positive patients.” In our view, the Guidelines do not necessarily contain implicit assumptions conclusive of the point to be decided. The Guidelines set out CDC's recommendation that the universal precautions are the best way to combat the risk of HIV transmission. They do not assess the level of risk.

Nor can we be certain, on this record, whether the 1991 American Dental Association Policy on HIV carries the weight the Court of Appeals attributed to it. The Policy does provide some evidence of the medical community's objective assessment of the risks posed by treating people infected with HIV in dental offices. It indicates:

Current scientific and epidemiologic evidence indicates that there is little risk of transmission of infectious diseases through dental treatment if recommended infection control procedures are routinely followed. Patients with HIV infection may be safely treated in private dental offices when appropriate infection control procedures are employed. Such infection control procedures provide protection both for patients and dental personnel.

We note, however, that the Association is a professional organization, which, although a respected source of information on the dental profession, is not a public health authority. It is not clear the extent to which the Policy was based on the Association's assessment of dentists' ethical and professional duties in addition to its scientific assessment of the risk to which the ADA refers. Efforts to clarify dentists' ethical obligations and to encourage dentists to treat patients with HIV infection with compassion may be commendable, but the question under the statute is one of statistical likelihood, not professional responsibility. Without more information on the manner in which the American Dental Association formulated this Policy, we are unable to determine the Policy's value in evaluating whether petitioner's assessment of the risks was reasonable as a matter of law.

The court considered materials submitted by both parties on the cross motions for summary judgment. The petitioner was required to establish that there existed a genuine issue of material fact. Evidence which was merely colorable or not significantly probative would not have been sufficient.

We acknowledge the presence of other evidence in the record before the Court of Appeals which, subject to further arguments and examination, might support affirmance of the trial court's ruling. For instance, the record contains substantial testimony from numerous health experts indicating that it is safe to treat patients infected with HIV in dental offices. We are unable to determine the import of this evidence, however. The record does not disclose whether the expert testimony submitted by respondent turned on evidence available in September 1994.

There are reasons to doubt whether petitioner advanced evidence sufficient to raise a triable issue of fact on the significance of the risk. Petitioner relied on two principal points: [f]irst, he asserted that the use of high-speed drills and surface cooling with water created a risk of airborne HIV transmission. The study on which petitioner relied was inconclusive, however, determining only that “[f]urther work is required to determine whether such a risk exists.” Petitioner's expert witness conceded, moreover, that no evidence suggested the spray could transmit HIV. His opinion on airborne risk was based on the absence of contrary evidence, not on positive data. Scientific evidence and expert testimony must have a traceable, analytical basis in objective fact before it may be considered on summary judgment.

Second, petitioner argues that, as of September 1994, CDC had identified seven dental workers with possible occupational transmission of HIV. These dental workers were exposed to HIV in the course of their employment, but CDC could not determine whether HIV infection had resulted. It is now known that CDC could not ascertain whether the seven dental workers contracted the disease because they did not present themselves for HIV testing at an appropriate time after their initial exposure. It is not clear on this record, however, whether this information was available to petitioner in September 1994. If not, the seven cases might have provided some, albeit not necessarily sufficient, support for petitioner's position. Standing alone, we doubt it would meet the objective, scientific basis for finding a significant risk to the petitioner.

We conclude the proper course is to give the Court of Appeals the opportunity to determine whether our analysis of some of the studies cited by the parties would change its conclusion that petitioner presented neither objective evidence nor a triable issue of fact on the question of risk. In remanding the case, we do not foreclose the possibility that the Court of Appeals may reach the same conclusion it did earlier. A remand will permit a full exploration of the issue through the adversary process.

The determination of the Court of Appeals that respondent's HIV infection was a disability under the ADA is affirmed. The judgment is vacated, and the case is remanded for further proceedings consistent with this opinion.

Notes and Questions

1. On remand, the Court of Appeals in Bragdon once again held that there was inadequate evidence of a direct threat, and affirmed the grant of summary judgment to the plaintiff. The court stated:

In compliance with the Court's directive, we have reexamined the evidence to determine whether summary judgment was warranted. In order to reverse our course, we would have to find, contrary to our original intuition, either that (i) Ms. Abbott did not merit judgment as a matter of law even in the absence of disputed facts, or (ii) that Dr. Bragdon had submitted sufficient evidence to create a genuine issue of material fact as to his direct threat defense. In our reexamination, we apply conventional summary judgment jurisprudence, drawing all reasonable factual inferences in favor of Dr. Bragdon. Despite the leniency of this approach, we do not indulge “conclusory allegations, improbable inferences, and unsupported speculation.”

A. Ms. Abbott's Evidence.

The Supreme Court raised questions regarding whether the Guidelines, which state that use of the universal precautions therein described “should reduce the risk of disease transmission in the dental environment,” necessarily imply that the reduction of risk would be to a level below that required to show direct threat. We have reconsidered this point.

The CDC did not write the 1993 Guidelines in a vacuum, but, rather, updated earlier versions issued in 1986 and 1987, respectively. The 1986 text calls the universal precautions “effective for preventing hepatitis B, acquired immunodeficiency syndrome, and other infectious diseases caused by bloodborne viruses.” The 1987 edition explains that use of the universal precautions eliminates the need for additional precautions that the CDC formerly had advocated for handling blood and other bodily fluids known or suspected to be infected with bloodborne pathogens. Neither the parties nor any of the amici have suggested that the 1993 rewrite was intended to retreat from these earlier risk assessments, and we find no support for such a position in the Guidelines' text. Thus, we have again determined that the Guidelines are competent evidence that public health authorities considered treatment of the kind that Ms. Abbott required to be safe, if undertaken using universal precautions.

Second, the Court questioned the appropriate weight to accord the Policy, expressing concern that the Policy might be based in whole or in part on the Association's view of dentists' ethical obligations, rather than on a pure scientific assessment. The supplemental briefing that we requested yielded a cornucopia of information regarding the process by which the Policy was assembled. We briefly recount the undisputed facts.

The Association formulates scientific and ethical policies by separate procedures, drawing on different member groups and different staff complements. The Association's Council on Scientific Affairs, comprised of 17 dentists (most of whom hold advanced dentistry degrees), together with a staff of over 20 professional experts and consultants, drafted the Policy at issue here. By contrast, ethical policies are drafted by the Council on Ethics, a wholly separate body. Although the Association's House of Delegates must approve policies drafted by either council, we think that the origins of the Policy satisfy any doubts regarding its scientific foundation.

For these reasons, we are confident that we appropriately relied on the Guidelines and the Policy. Moreover, as the Supreme Court acknowledged, these two pieces of evidence represent only a fraction of the proof advanced to support Ms. Abbott's motion. For example, she proffered the opinions of several prominent experts to the effect that, in 1994, the cavity-filling procedure could have been performed safely in a private dental office, as well as proof that no public health authority theretofore had issued warnings to health care providers disfavoring this type of treatment for asymptomatic HIV-positive patients. These materials, in and of themselves, likely suffice to prove Ms. Abbott's point. Thus, we again conclude, after due reevaluation, that Ms. Abbott served a properly documented motion for summary judgment.

B. Dr. Bragdon's Evidence.

We next reconsider whether Dr. Bragdon offered sufficient proof of direct threat to create a genuine issue of material fact and thus avoid the entry of summary judgment. In Abbott II, we canvassed eight items of evidence adduced by Dr. Bragdon in an effort to demonstrate a genuine issue of material fact. The Supreme Court suggested that one such piece of evidence—the seven cases that the CDC considered “possible” HIV patient-to-dental worker transmissions—should be reexamined.

The Court's concern revolved around how the word “possible” was understood in this context at the relevant time. To frame the issue, the Court noted that the CDC marks an HIV case as a “possible” occupational transmission if a stricken worker, who had no other demonstrated opportunity for infection, simply failed to present himself for testing after being exposed to the virus at work. The Court speculated that if this definition of “possible” was not available in September 1994, the existence of seven “possible” cases “might have provided some, albeit not necessarily sufficient, support for [Dr. Bragdon's] position.” In other words, if a dentist knew of seven “possible” occupational transmissions to dental workers without understanding that “possible” meant no more than that the CDC could not determine whether workers were infected occupationally, he might reasonably regard the risk of treating an HIV-infected patient to be significant.

Upon reexamination of the record, we find that the CDC's definition of the word “possible,” as used here, had been made public during the relevant period. The record contains two scientific articles published before Ms. Abbott entered Dr. Bragdon's office which explained this definition. Since an objective standard pertains here, the existence of the list of seven “possible” cases does not create a genuine issue of material fact as to direct threat.

In his supplemental briefing and oral argument, Dr. Bragdon has drawn our attention again to the CDC's report of 42 documented cases of occupational transmission of HIV to health-care workers (none of whom were dental workers). He repeats his argument that, because dental workers are subject to dangers similar to those faced by other health-care workers, these cases can be extrapolated to create an issue of fact as to the degree of risk to dental workers in September 1994. We previously held that this evidence was insufficient without a documented showing that the risks to dentists and other health-care workers are comparable, and the appellant offers us no cogent reason to change our view. The Supreme Court did not question our position on this front, and Dr. Bragdon points to no record support that we previously might have overlooked.

Our assessment of Dr. Bragdon's, and his amici's, other reprised arguments similarly remains unchanged. Each piece of evidence to which they direct us is still “too speculative or too tangential (or, in some instances, both) to create a genuine issue of material fact.”

163 F.3d 87 (1st Cir. 1998).

2. Once the hospital is on notice that a physician to whom it extends practice privileges is discriminating against individuals with disabilities, is the hospital also in violation of the ADA if it continues to extend privileges to that physician? Even if the physician is not subject to Section 504, if discriminatory conduct by a physician with privileges is made known to the hospital, does it have an obligation to investigate and to take appropriate action? If it fails to do so, is it in violation of Section 504? See also Doe v. Jamaica Hosp., 202 A.D.2d 386, 608 N.Y.S.2d 518 (1994) (physician who refused to treat a patient with AIDS would not be subject to §504 because the physician did not receive federal financial assistance).

3. Would it matter whether both the ADA and Section 504 were being violated? Which avenue of redress should be used? Why?

4. Medical Care for Patients with HIV. In addition to Bragdon, there have been a number of other decisions where courts have found violations of the ADA or Section 504 by health care providers who refused to treat individuals with HIV. In Miller v. Spicer, 822 F. Supp. 158 (D. Del. 1993), the court held that there was a violation of Section 504 when an emergency room surgeon refused to treat an individual whom he thought to be HIV-positive. A complaint against Philadelphia emergency medical technicians and firefighters involved a refusal to assist people with AIDS. Part of the settlement included an agreement to undergo AIDS awareness training. U.S. Department of Justice Complaint No. 204-62-24 (settled March 18, 1994). A refusal to treat an HIV-positive patient cost a dental care center $100,000 in damages and penalties. The settlement with the Department of Justice also included an agreement to establish a policy prohibiting bias on the basis of AIDS and staff training. United States v. Castle Dental Soc'y, No. CA-H933140 (S.D. Tex., settled Sept. 22, 1994). See also LAURA ROTHSTEIN & JULIA IRZYK, DISABILITIES AND THE LAW §10.04 (2012 and cumulative supplement).

In Lesley v. Hee Man Chie, 250 F.3d 47 (1st Cir. 2001), the court held that a pregnant woman who was transferred to a different hospital after testing HIV positive was not discriminated against because she was unable to show that the transfer was not linked to legitimate medical necessity. In Green v. City of Welch, 467 F. Supp. 2d 656 (S.D. W. Va. 2006), the court allowed a suit to go forward where the estate of a man with HIV claimed CPR assistance was denied to the decedent because of his HIV status. For other cases, see LAURA ROTHSTEIN & JULIA IRZYK, DISABILITIES AND THE LAW §10:2 (2012 and cumulative supplement).

C. Architectural Barriers, Auxiliary Aids and Services, and Reasonable Accommodation

The previous section highlights situations in which an individual with a disability might be refused or denied health care services because of prejudices of the provider. While this may often be the case of individuals with HIV or with individuals with intellectual disabilities, the more common barrier to health care service access involves architectural barriers and the need for reasonable accommodations, including auxiliary aids and services or other accommodations.

It is probable that most major health care programs, such as hospitals and clinics, have accessible ramped entrances, because wheelchairs and gurneys are commonly used in these facilities. These facilities are also likely to be accessible with respect to restrooms and other similar facilities. The facilities that are less likely to be accessible are health care offices located in the residence of the provider or in commercial facilities other than hospitals and clinics.

Although most major hospitals are recipients of federal financial assistance, individual physicians and other health care providers, as a general rule, are not. For that reason, the Americans with Disabilities Act is substantially more comprehensive in its protection of individuals with disabilities than Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act. The physical facility access requirements are much stronger under the ADA, as Chapter 4 on Public Accommodations illustrates. A private health care provider such as a doctor's office or clinic generally would fall within the definition of a “public accommodation” under Title III of the ADA, and thus would be required to remove barriers to the extent it is readily achievable to do so, in addition to being required to make new construction accessible. The importance of access to health care providers is recognized in the regulations relating to new construction and alterations of buildings that are to be used for public accommodations. There is an exemption that allows certain of these facilities to be built without an elevator, where the facility has fewer than three stories or has less than 3,000 square feet per story. 28 C.F.R. §36.401(d). This exemption does not apply, however, when the facility is intended to be used for professional offices of health care providers. The guidance explains this regulation:

A public accommodation, such as the professional office of a health care provider, is required to remove architectural barriers to its facility to the extent that such barrier removal is readily achievable (see §36.304), but it is not otherwise required by this part to undertake new construction or alterations. This part does not require that an existing two story building that houses the professional office of a health care provider be altered for the purpose of providing elevator access. If, however, alterations to the area housing the office of the health care provider are undertaken for other purposes, the installation of an elevator might be required, but only if the cost of the elevator is not disproportionate to the cost of the overall alteration. Neither the Act nor this part prohibits a health care provider from locating his or her professional office in an existing facility that does not have an elevator.

28 C.F.R. pt. 36, App. C, §36.404.

By contrast to the ADA, Section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act only applies to recipients of federal financial assistance, such as hospitals. Before the passage of the ADA, these facilities were required to be accessible when viewed in their entirety. Under the ADA, if the facility is operated by a state or local governmental entity, Title II accessibility requirements would apply. If the facility is privately operated, Title III would apply in many instances.

Because the ADA requirement that elevators be built for new construction or alterations of health care facilities may not reach existing health care facilities, and the Rehabilitation Act's application only to facilities receiving federal financial assistance, a wheelchair user who wants to visit a dentist office on the second floor of an old building without an elevator may have no remedy under the ADA or the Rehabilitation Act. Under both statutes, however, the service providers may be expected to relocate a visit as an accommodation (such as a lawyer meeting in an alternative location). This will be unlikely to work, however, in the instance of health care providers whose unique equipment cannot be easily moved.

The ADA regulations also provide guidance on places of public accommodation in private residences. They require that the portions of the residence used exclusively for the residence need not meet access requirements. Those portions that are used as public accommodations, however, must meet access requirements in areas including the front sidewalk, the entrance, and portions of the residence (including restrooms) used by the public. 28 C.F.R. Section 36.207.

A related challenge for individuals with mobility and similar impairments can be that the health care office is accessible with respect to getting in and around the facility, but the equipment is not accessible. Special chairs for eye exams and dental treatment, for example, may be difficult to use for someone with a mobility impairment. Examination tables may be technically “accessible,” but the providers may not be experienced at assisting individuals with spinal cord injuries in getting on and off a table for routine medical types of exams, such as annual gynecological exams.

With the advent of managed care, individuals with disabilities who have chronic health care needs face unique obstacles. In many managed care programs, the selection of physicians is limited, as is access to specialists without going through the primary care physician. An individual with mobility impairments may have particular difficulties if the offices of the listed providers are not accessible. Even if they are accessible, transportation difficulties may be a severe barrier. The bus system may not be completely accessible, and even if it is accessible, substantially more time might be required to use an accessible transportation system. In addition, although the entrance to the provider's office might be accessible, fixed equipment, such as a dental chair, might not be accessible for an individual with a mobility impairment. In Anderson v. Department of Pub. Welfare, 1 F. Supp. 2d 456 (E.D. Pa. 1998), the court held that health maintenance providers must ensure that the services viewed in their entirety are accessible, but this does not resolve many of the details about what that means.

There is minimal case law to provide guidance on physical access in health care provider facilities. Relevant litigation revolves around what constitutes a third floor and what constitutes an “alteration” for purposes of the ADA to trigger compliance. There are, however, some settlements of lawsuits. See Elizabeth Pendo, Disability, Equipment Barriers, and Women's Health: Using the ADA to Provide Meaningful Access, 2 ST. LOUIS U.J. HEALTH L. & POL'Y 15, 33–37 (2008) (discussing several lawsuits raising these issues that have settled and noting “there are relatively few cases brought challenging inaccessible facilities or equipment in the context of medical care” and “[t]he paucity of private actions is unfortunate, but not surprising.”); Elizabeth Pendo, Reducing Disparities Through Health Care Reform: Disability and Accessible Medical Equipment, 2010 UTAH L. REV. 1057 (providing additional details on lawsuits that have settled in this area, including ones for architectural barriers and inaccessible equipment). There is also some judicial guidance on the issue of reasonable accommodations in the health care provider context.

One area that has received substantial judicial attention involves the issue of providing interpreter service to individuals who are deaf at hospitals and in other health care settings. The issue can involve the feasibility of ensuring that appropriate communication services are available as well as the cost for providing such services.

Hypothetical Problem 9.2

Read the following hypothetical Problem, and, after reading Aikens and Mayberry, prepare to discuss the problem.

Charlie Cortez is a two year old child who was born with a hearing impairment. Charlie's parents, Anna and Mario Cortez, do not have hearing impairments. They suspect there is something wrong with Charlie's hearing because he does not react to loud noises and because his speech is delayed. They go to a group of doctors in Los Angeles who specialize in hearing difficulties to have Charlie diagnosed. The diagnosis is that Charlie has a hearing impairment, and that a device called the cochlear implant would improve his hearing. The doctor they see, Jon Walter, recommends that Anna and Mario take Charlie to Dr. Hugh Malloy, who he believes is one of the best ear surgeons in the City. Dr. Walter tells Anna and Mario that Dr. Malloy has a hearing impairment himself and that he has a son with a hearing impairment. When Anna and Mario take Charlie to see Dr. Malloy, through an interpreter, he tells them that Charlie would likely be able to hear fairly well and would develop good speech habits if had a cochlear implant. Dr. Malloy, however, tells them that he will not do the surgery on Charlie. He believes that persons with deafness from birth should learn to sign and read lips and to become part of the community of persons who are deaf. The device will keep Charlie from that experience, and it is Malloy's practice to refuse to give children cochlear implants because, although he had his own son get a cochlear implant, he believes it is more harmful than not having the cochlear implant because of the separation from the deaf community. Anna and Mario are very upset and want to force Dr. Malloy to perform the surgery because they know he is the best ear surgeon in town. When he refuses, they visit a lawyer to see if they have a cause of action of discrimination against Dr. Malloy based on the ADA. Consider the different arguments the plaintiffs' and defendant's lawyers would make in this case. Would it make a difference if Dr. Malloy were the only specialist in town who knew how to put in cochlear implants?

—————

The following two cases raise the issue in different contexts. First, in Aikins, the court addressed the obligation in a hospital setting, including liability issues related to both the hospital and the treating physician. The Mayberry decision looks at the issue with respect to the individual health care provider.

Aikins v. St. Helena Hospital

843 F. Supp. 1329 (N.D. Cal. 1994)

FERN M. SMITH, DISTRICT JUDGE:

Background

The events giving rise to this lawsuit occurred between October 30 and November 4, 1992. Mrs. Aikins is a deaf woman whose husband, Harvey Aikins, suffered a massive cardiac arrest at approximately 8:00 p.m. on October 30, 1992. Following Mr. Aikins's attack, Mrs. Aikins went to the home of some neighbors and had them call 911. According to Mrs. Aikins, the paramedics arrived at her home approximately four minutes after the call to 911, which defendants assert was approximately fifteen minutes after Mr. Aikins suffered the attack. The paramedics then transported Mr. Aikins to St. Helena Hospital.

Dr. Lies was working in St. Helena's emergency room when Mr. Aikins was brought in. Dr. Lies is an independent contractor on staff at the hospital. He exercises no authority over hospital policy. When the paramedics informed Dr. Lies that they had arrived within four minutes of Mr. Aikins's attack, Dr. Lies decided to perform an emergency angioplasty. He attempted to consult Mrs. Aikins and to obtain her consent, but Mrs. Aikins could not understand him and requested that interpreters be provided. A hospital operator with some knowledge of fingerspelling was summoned and attempted to fingerspell Dr. Lies's comments for Mrs. Aikins. The woman became frustrated, however, and gave up her efforts within a minute. Shortly thereafter, Mrs. Aikins's neighbors arrived and attempted to mediate between Dr. Lies and Mrs. Aikins. Dr. Lies asserts that the neighbors “were quite able to communicate with [Mrs. Aikins]” and relayed to her his opinion that, with immediate medical intervention, Dr. Lies might be able to save Mr. Aikins's life. Mrs. Aikins submits that the neighbors only passed her a terse note stating that Mr. Aikins may have had a massive cardiac arrest and that he was “brain dead.”

Subsequently, Mrs. Aikins went to the hospital's administrative office and made further attempts to secure interpreter services. At approximately 9:00 p.m., she was approached by a member of the hospital staff who sought to obtain her signature on forms consenting to the emergency procedure. Although the forms say that “[y]our signature on this form indicates ... (2) that the operation procedure set forth above has been adequately explained to you by your physician, (3) that you have had a chance to ask questions, [and] (4) that you have received all of the information you desire concerning the operation or procedure...,” Mrs. Aikins claims that she was told only that “Dr. Lies needed [her] signature to permit him to perform surgery to save [her] husband's life.” Dr. Lies claims that, although he believed that it was unnecessary under the circumstances to obtain Mrs. Aikins's consent to the surgery, “given [her] disability, [he] wanted her to be involved.”

Later that evening, Dr. Lies contacted Mrs. Aikins's daughter, Francine Stern, to request that she fly up to Calistoga from Los Angeles to help her mother. Ms. Stern, who was Mr. Aikins's stepdaughter, is a fluent signer. Ms. Stern told Dr. Lies that she would be unable to come up until November 2nd.

Mrs. Aikins went to her husband's room at approximately 12:30 on the night of the operation. She claims that the nurse on duty told her that Mr. Aikins would not survive without life support and that Mrs. Aikins then requested that life support be discontinued. She then went to the administrative office, accompanied by a deaf friend, to request interpreter services again. Both the office and another nurse whom Mrs. Aikins and her friend later encountered in Mr. Aikins's room allegedly told Mrs. Aikins that the hospital had no means of procuring interpreter services.

The following day, October 31, 1992, Mr. Aikins showed no neurologic improvement, prompting Dr. Lies to question Mrs. Aikins about the length of time between the heart attack and the arrival of the paramedics. Dr. Lies submits that it was during this questioning, seemingly conducted through Mrs. Aikins's in-laws, that he first learned that fifteen minutes, not four, had elapsed between Mr. Aikins's heart attack and the commencement of CPR. Based on this new information, Dr. Lies ordered an EEG. The EEG was performed on November 1, 1992, at 9:00 a.m. and revealed that Mr. Aikins had no brain activity.

On November 2nd, Mrs. Aikins's daughter arrived and participated in a meeting with Dr. Lies and Mrs. Aikins. Mrs. Aikins claims that this meeting was the first opportunity that she had to communicate directly with Dr. Lies and to receive complete answers to her questions. As a result of the meeting, Mrs. Aikins requested that her husband's life support be discontinued. Mr. Aikins died two days later.

Discussion

I. Plaintiffs' Standing to Seek Injunctive Relief

Defendants have challenged CAD's [California Association of the Deaf] standing to participate in this lawsuit.

The Supreme Court has developed a three-part test for standing, a constitutional prerequisite growing out of Article III's “case or controversy” requirement. See U.S. Const. art. III, §2, cl. 1. The first prong of the test is the “injury in fact” requirement: “[T]he plaintiff must have suffered an ‘injury in fact’—an invasion of a legally-protected interest which is (a) concrete and particularized; and (b) ‘actual or imminent, not “conjectural” or “hypothetical.’”” The second and third elements of the test are causation and redressability. As it is clear that defendants caused whatever violation of the relevant statutes may have occurred, and that a favorable decision of this Court would redress any injuries caused by violation of the statutes, only the first aspect of the inquiry is at issue here.

City of Los Angeles v. Lyons, 461 U.S. 95 (1983), established that a plaintiff seeking injunctive relief premised upon an alleged past wrong must demonstrate a “real and immediate threat” of repeated future harm to satisfy the injury in fact prong of the standing test.

Mrs. Aikins has not shown her standing to seek injunctive relief under Lyons. In her complaint, Mrs. Aikins alleges only that she is a deaf individual and within the protection of the ADA, the Rehabilitation Act, and various state statutes. Mrs. Aikins further states that she owns a mobile home seven miles from St. Helena Hospital and that she stays at the home for several days each year. These allegations do not establish the “real and immediate threat” of future harm that Lyons requires. Mrs. Aikins has shown neither that she is likely to use the hospital in the near future, nor that defendants are likely to discriminate against her when she does use the hospital. The Court cannot infer from Mrs. Aikins's limited experience with Dr. Lies and St. Helena Hospital that defendants routinely fail to comply with applicable anti-discrimination statutes.

Plaintiffs rely on Greater Los Angeles Council on Deafness, Inc., et al., Plaintiffs-Appellants, v. Malcolm Baldrige, 827 F.2d at 1353, to establish their standing for injunctive relief. In that case, plaintiffs were GLAD, a nonprofit organization dedicated to furthering the interests of deaf and hearing-impaired individuals, an attorney for GLAD who had filed an administrative complaint with the Department of Commerce, and two deaf individuals acting on their own behalf and as representatives of a class of similarly situated persons. Plaintiffs sought a writ of mandamus against the Department of Commerce, alleging that the department had failed to act on an administrative complaint that charged a public television station with violation of the Rehabilitation Act for failure to provide closed-captioned hearing. Plaintiffs alleged that the department's failure to act on the complaint was itself a violation of the Act. In holding that plaintiffs had standing to pursue their claim for injunctive relief, the Ninth Circuit noted that “[t]he actual or threatened injury required by Article III may exist solely by virtue of a statute that creates legal rights, the invasion of which creates standing.” The court found that the Rehabilitation Act was such a statute.

Council on Deafness is distinguishable from this case. Implicitly at issue in that case was whether defendant's alleged violation of the Rehabilitation Act was an “injury in fact” sufficient to confer standing on plaintiffs. If the claimed violation constituted an injury, there was no question as to the imminence of the harm occasioned by the injury. Plaintiffs had filed an administrative complaint, on which defendant had failed to act; thus, the claimed injury was ongoing. Here, by contrast, imminence has not been shown. Although an alleged violation of the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act is an injury sufficient to give rise to an Article III case or controversy, Mrs. Aikins has not shown that defendants' alleged discrimination is ongoing and that she is likely to be served by defendants in the near future. Mrs. Aikins's claims for injunctive relief are accordingly dismissed with leave to amend to show that Mrs. Aikins faces a real and immediate threat of future injury at the hands of defendants.

CAD's standing to seek injunctive relief suffers from the same defects. An association seeking to bring suit on behalf of its members must show: (1) that its members would have standing to sue in their own right; (2) that the interests that it seeks to protect are germane to the organization's purpose; and (3) that neither the claim asserted nor the relief requested require the participation of individual members. CAD has alleged only that it is a nonprofit organization with at least eight hundred members, organized for the purpose of serving the needs of deaf individuals “through advocacy, education and referral,” and that some members of CAD “have been or likely will be served by defendants....” Although these allegations are sufficient to satisfy the second and third requirements for associational standing, they fail to show that CAD's members would have standing to sue in their own right. CAD's claims are accordingly dismissed with leave to amend to show standing to seek injunctive relief only.

Plaintiffs' Claims under the Americans with Disabilities Act

Plaintiffs claim that defendants violated the Americans with Disabilities Act (“ADA”) by denying Mrs. Aikins access to information in connection with the treatment of her husband. The ADA provides, in pertinent part: “No individual shall be discriminated against on the basis of disability in the full and equal enjoyment of the goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, or accommodations of any place of public accommodation by any person who owns, leases (or leases to), or operates a place of public accommodation.” 42 U.S.C. §12182(a).

A. The ADA Does Not Apply to Dr. Lies

Dr. Lies contends that plaintiffs' claims against him under the ADA must fail because the Act does not apply to him in his capacity as an independent contractor with St. Helena. The regulations implementing the ADA alter the language of the statute slightly to read as follows: “No individual shall be discriminated against on the basis of disability ... by any private entity who owns, leases (or leases to), or operates a place of public accommodation.” 28 C.F.R. §36.201(a) (1993). The preamble to the regulation notes that the change was designed to make clear that the regulation “places the ADA's nondiscrimination obligations on ‘public accommodations’ rather than on ‘persons’ or ‘places of public accommodation.’” 36 C.F.R. App. B §36.104 (1993).

The statute and the regulation both indicate that individuals may be liable under the ADA if they “own, lease (or lease to), or operate” a place of public accommodation. 42 U.S.C. §12182(a); 28 C.F.R. §35.201(a) (1993). The use of language relating to ownership or operation implies a requirement of control over the place providing services. Dr. Lies, however, is an independent contractor with St. Helena. He is not on the hospital's board of directors, and he has no authority to enact or amend hospital policy. Because he lacks the power to control hospital policy on the use of interpreters, this Court holds that Dr. Lies is not a proper defendant under the ADA.

Plaintiffs contend that this construction of the ADA undercuts the Act's purpose. Noting that the Act defines “public accommodation” to include the “professional office of a health care provider,” 42 U.S.C. §12181(7)(F), plaintiffs maintain that the Act would clearly cover Dr. Lies had he provided services to Mr. and Mrs. Aikins at his own office. They argue that he should not be able to escape liability under the ADA merely because in this case he provided services outside his office. “To hold otherwise,” plaintiffs suggest, “would allow individuals to discriminate whenever they provide part of their services outside of their place of public accommodation while disallowing the very same type of discrimination for those services provided at the place of public accommodation.”

Plaintiffs' policy argument does not warrant a departure from the statute's implicit requirement of ownership or control. The Court's construction of the Act is not at odds with the ADA's fundamental purpose of eliminating discrimination against individuals with disabilities, see 42 U.S.C. §12101(b)(1), because it retains accountability for those in a position to ensure nondiscrimination.

B. St. Helena Has Not Shown That It Complied with the Act as a Matter of Law

St. Helena does not dispute that the ADA applies to it, see 42 U.S.C. §12181(7)(F), but claims that it complied with the Act as a matter of law. Alternatively, St. Helena argues that compliance is excused, as it would impose an undue burden on the hospital. The regulations implementing the ADA provide that a “public accommodation shall furnish appropriate auxiliary aids and services where necessary to ensure effective communication with individuals with disabilities.” 28 C.F.R. §36.303(c) (1993). This requirement is tempered by the general qualification that a public accommodation may treat disabled individuals in need of auxiliary aids and services differently from other individuals if “the public accommodation can demonstrate that [ensuring equality of treatment] would ... result in an undue burden, i.e., significant difficulty or expense.” §36.303(a) (1993).

St. Helena bases its contention that it complied with the ADA as a matter of law on the following evidence and allegations: that its human resources department had in place a policy of providing interpreters to those in need of them; that the hospital posted signs notifying the public that information about T.D.D. services could be obtained by going to the switchboard; that the switchboard operator and the office of human resources maintained lists of interpreters; that Mr. Aikins's medical records contain a statement that “there were interpreters present at all times during the discussion with the patient and the family”; and that “the complaint is replete with descriptions of instances where information was exchanged between plaintiff Aikins and members of the St. Helena hospital staff.” Defendant argues alternatively that provision of an interpreter on a twenty-four hour a day basis would impose an undue burden on the hospital.

The record does not reveal that St. Helena complied with the ADA as a matter of law. St. Helena has not demonstrated that it communicated effectively with plaintiff Aikins during her husband's stay in the hospital. Indeed, the hospital's allegations that communication was effective are undercut not only by plaintiff's own account of the episode but also by the fact that, for between twenty-four to thirty-six hours, Dr. Lies was under the concededly mistaken impression that Mr. Aikins had been without CPR for only four minutes following his heart attack, a critical fact. Furthermore, although the regulations provide that the hospital “shall furnish” appropriate auxiliary aids and services for non-hearing individuals, §36.303(c), it appears that St. Helena relied almost exclusively on Mrs. Aikins to provide her own interpreters. There exists a genuine dispute as to the issue of St. Helena's compliance with the ADA.

Finally, the Court cannot say as a matter of law that provision of interpreters would have imposed an undue burden on the hospital. The regulations set out criteria for determining whether a proposed accommodation imposes an undue burden within the meaning of section 36.303(a). Section 36.104 provides, in pertinent part:

In determining whether an action would result in an undue burden, factors to be considered include—(1) The nature and cost of the action needed under this part; (2) The overall financial resources of the site or sites involved in the action; the number of persons employed at the site; the effect on expenses and resources; legitimate safety requirements that are necessary for safe operation ...; or the impact otherwise of the action upon the operation of the site; (3) The geographic separateness, and the administrative or fiscal relationship of the site or sites in question to any parent corporation or entity; (4) If applicable, the overall financial resources of any parent corporation or entity; the overall size of the parent corporation or entity with respect to the number of its employees; the number, type, and location of its facilities; and (5) If applicable, the type of operation or operations of any parent corporation or entity, including the composition, structure, and functions of the workforce of the parent corporation or entity.

§36.104 (1993). The question whether provision of interpreter services on some basis would pose an undue burden on St. Helena raises material issues of fact.

Dobard v. San Francisco Bay Area Rapid Transit District, 1993 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 13677, 3 Am. Disabilities Cas. (BNA) 203 (N.D. Cal. Sept. 7, 1993), cited by defendant, does not warrant a different conclusion. In that case defendant transit authority provided plaintiff with both a sign language interpreter and a sound amplification device in connection with his attendance at a public board meeting. Plaintiff argued that defendant nonetheless violated the ADA by refusing to provide plaintiff with a computer aided transcription device, the auxiliary aid of his choice. The court in Dobard found that plaintiff had failed to state a claim for violation of the ADA, as defendant was not required to employ the most advanced technology but only to ensure that communication was effective. Plaintiffs herein are not arguing for an absolute right to a particular auxiliary aid. Rather, they claim a right to effective communication with the hospital. St. Helena, unlike the defendant in Dobard, allegedly made no effort to provide Mrs. Aikins with auxiliary aids, relying upon Mrs. Aikins to marshal her own communication resources.

III. Plaintiffs' Claims under the Rehabilitation Act

A. Mrs. Aikins is an “Otherwise Qualified” Individual Within the Meaning of the Act

[Dr. Lies apparently concedes that he is subject to Section 504 by receiving Medicare and Medicaid reimbursements.]

Defendant Lies argues that plaintiffs' claims under section 504 should be dismissed because plaintiff Aikins is not an “otherwise qualified” individual within the meaning of the Act.

[In another decision] the Second Circuit concluded that the Act applies to all services offered by a covered entity, not just those relating to the entity's central function. “The fact that a particular recipient institution is primarily engaged in the provision of one category of service does not exempt it from Regulation 104.3(k) in its provision of other services.”

Although [that decision] is not binding upon this Court, its reasoning is sound. That Mrs. Aikins was not a patient at St. Helena should not preclude her from raising claims under the Rehabilitation Act based on the hospital's failure to communicate effectively with her in connection with its treatment of her husband. Mrs. Aikins was “otherwise qualified” to discuss her husband's condition with hospital officials, including Dr. Lies.

Defendant Lies next argues that California law precludes Mrs. Aikins from being “otherwise qualified” in the circumstances presented by this case. He submits that Mrs. Aikins's consent to the procedures performed on her husband was not necessary; as a consequence she was not required to be consulted or kept informed of her husband's condition. Defendant attempts to analogize from Bowen v. American Hospital Association, 476 U.S. 610 (1986), wherein a plurality of the Court stated that a “hospital's withholding of treatment when no parental consent has been given cannot violate §504.” The plurality reasoned that, in the absence of the required parental consent, the infant is neither “otherwise qualified” within the meaning of the Act, nor denied treatment “solely because of his handicap.” Defendant maintains that Mrs. Aikins is not “otherwise qualified” because her consent to her husband's treatment was not required.

Defendant's argument is unavailing. Dr. Lies's argument that emergency circumstances vitiated the requirement of informed consent is undercut by his own statement that, “[t]hough it was clear to me that Mr. Aikins presented an immediate medical emergency, thus making informed consent unnecessary, I had time to, and so did seek to, advise Mrs. Aikins and obtain her consent.” Having undertaken to obtain Mrs. Aikins's consent, defendant was obligated to do so in a nondiscriminatory manner. More important, Mrs. Aikins's claims relating to inadequate communication span a period of almost seventy-two hours, from the time of her husband's admission to the hospital until the time that his life support was disconnected. Whatever emergency existed at the time of Mr. Aikins's admission to the hospital had subsided by the time the decision was made to discontinue his life support. Finally Bowen is distinguishable. That case essentially involved a failure of causation. It was the parents' refusal of consent, not the infant's disability, that would have resulted in the denial of treatment. By contrast, it was precisely Mrs. Aikins's disability that caused defendants to communicate with her in an allegedly inadequate manner.

B. Defendants Have Not Shown That They Complied with the Act as a Matter of Law

Defendants finally argue that they complied with the Rehabilitation Act as a matter of law. Defendant Lies argues that Mr. Aikins received precisely the same treatment that he would have received had Mrs. Aikins not been deaf. Defendant St. Helena maintains that it provided all that it was required to provide under the Act.

Both arguments are without merit. Even if Mr. Aikins received exactly the care that he would have received had Mrs. Aikins not been deaf, Dr. Lies misses the point. Mrs. Aikins's claims relate to her exclusion from meaningful participation in the decisions affecting her husband's treatment, not to the appropriateness of the treatment itself. As to the hospital's argument, the Court cannot infer from defendant's reference to its policies on interpreters and its own self-serving statements that it communicated effectively with plaintiff at all times that it complied with the Rehabilitation Act as a matter of law.

IV. Availability of Damages under the Federal Statutes

Defendants argue that Mrs. Aikins is not entitled to compensatory relief under either the ADA or the Rehabilitation Act. They are correct about the ADA. In cases involving claims under subchapter three of the ADA, the Act provides only for injunctive relief. Section 12188(a)(1) states that the remedies available to persons subjected to discrimination in violation of that subchapter are those set forth in 42 U.S.C. §2000a-3(a). 42 U.S.C. §12188(a)(1). §2000a-3(a) provides:

Whenever any person has engaged or there are reasonable grounds to believe that any person is about to engage in any act or practice prohibited by section 2000a-2 of this title, a civil action for preventive relief ... may be instituted by the person aggrieved....

42 U.S.C. §2000a-3(a). [T]he Supreme Court [has] held that a plaintiff suing under section 2000a-3(a) cannot recover damages. Plaintiffs appear to concede the unavailability of compensatory relief under the ADA in their opposition papers.

Because plaintiffs lack standing on the present record to assert claims for injunctive relief, the unavailability of damages under the ADA requires dismissal of all claims under the ADA. Such dismissal is without prejudice to plaintiffs' reinstating the ADA claims for injunctive relief upon a proper showing of standing.

As to Mrs. Aikins's claims under the Rehabilitation Act, the Ninth Circuit has held that damages are available for violations of the Act. Section 794a provides, in pertinent part: “The remedies, procedures, and rights set forth in title VI of the Civil Rights Act of 1964 [codified at 42 U.S.C. section 2000d et seq.] shall be available to any person aggrieved by any act or failure to act by any recipient of Federal assistance ... under section 794 of this title.” 29 U.S.C. §794a(a)(2). The settled interpretation of section 794a in the Ninth Circuit is that money damages are available for violations of section 504 of the Rehabilitation Act.

V. Plaintiffs' State Law Claims

[Discussion of state law claims omitted.]

Questions

1. What would Mrs. Aikins' damages be? Suppose the hospital billed Mrs. Aikins for procedures that she would not have approved had there been adequate communication? Would she and/or her insurance provider be able to recover the costs of those procedures?

2. If this were a state or local governmental hospital, would Mrs. Aikins be entitled to damages under Title II of the ADA?

3. In Part IV of Aikins, the court dismissed the plaintiffs' claims for injunctive relief under the ADA for lack of standing, but made clear that dismissal was without prejudice of reinstating the ADA claim for injunctive relief “upon a proper showing of standing.” Considering the entire Aikins opinion, what would constitute a proper showing of standing that would permit reinstatement of the ADA claim for injunctive relief?

Mayberry v. Von Valtier

843 F. Supp. 1160 (E.D. Mich. 1994)

WOODS, DISTRICT JUDGE:

Defendant, Cheryl C. Von Valtier, is a physician licensed to practice medicine in the State of Michigan. Plaintiff, Shirley Mayberry, is a 67 year-old deaf woman. Since 1987, Dr. Von Valtier has treated Ms. Mayberry as her family physician. Ms. Mayberry testified that she was able to lipread until she completely lost her hearing in 1990, and that she is able to understand simple notes. Ms. Mayberry and Dr. Von Valtier communicated during physical examinations by passing notes back and forth, or by using a signor. The signor was often one of Ms. Mayberry's children, and on three occasions a professional interpreter had been used. Dr. Von Valtier testified that visits with Ms. Mayberry took twice as long with an interpreter than when they passed notes, but that she did not mind spending the extra time.

On March 15, 1991, Ms. Mayberry brought her daughter Claudia Langston to her appointment with Dr. Von Valtier. Ms. Langston told Dr. Von Valtier that her mother's hearing had gotten progressively worse. During that visit, Dr. Von Valtier discovered that the back pain Ms. Mayberry had earlier complained of was higher than she had originally understood. Dr. Von Valtier wrote the following note on her chart: “[Ms. Mayberry] [s]tates pain has not moved, but this is higher than I had understood her to say. Probably due to poor communication.” Ms. Langston swears in her affidavit that Dr. Von Valtier told her that an interpreter made communication with Ms. Mayberry clearer and easier than writing notes. In addition, Dr. Von Valtier told her that she wanted Ms. Mayberry to have an interpreter when she was seen at her medical office.

On three occasions, Ms. Mayberry had an interpreter from Deaf, Hearing and Speech Services—Senior Citizens present during appointments with Dr. Von Valtier. On two of those occasions, once in 1989 and once in 1990, Dr. Von Valtier did not have to pay for the interpreter. On the third occasion, December 18, 1992, Ms. Mayberry was due to have a general examination, and she requested an interpreter because she felt she needed one. Dr. Von Valtier's office consented to pay for the interpreter's services pursuant to its duty under the Americans with Disabilities Act. Dr. Von Valtier wrote to Ms. Mayberry on January 7, 1993, summarizing the results of her examination.

Dr. Von Valtier was billed $28.00 by Monalee Ferrero for her interpreting services. Dr. Von Valtier paid the bill, and sent the following letter to Ms. Ferrero.

Enclosed is payment for your services to Shirley Mayberry in this office 12/18/92. The Medicare payment for Mrs. Mayberry's office visit has been received, and I would now like to explain why I won't be able to utilize your services in the future, or indeed why I really can't afford to take care of Mrs. Mayberry at all. My regular fee for a 15 minute office visit is $40.00. I spent about 45 minutes with Mrs. Mayberry on December 12, 1992, for this I was paid $37.17 by Medicare and (hopefully) $9.29 by Mrs. Mayberry. My office overhead expense rate is a rather steady 70% of my gross receipts, which means that for that 45 minutes I was able to “pocket” $13.94, that is, until I paid your bill for $28.00. I certainly hope that the Federal Government does not further slash this outrageous profit margin. A copy of this letter was also sent to Ms. Mayberry.

After Ms. Mayberry received the letter addressed to Ms. Ferrero, she became angry and called Dr. Von Valtier's office to ask for her records. Ms. Mayberry admits that she did not ask Dr. Von Valtier what she intended by the letter. Ms. Mayberry interpreted the letter to mean that Dr. Von Valtier would not hire an interpreter for her again, and that she had been discharged as a patient. At her deposition, Dr. Von Valtier explained that the letter was poorly written and ambiguous, and it was not her intention to discharge Ms. Mayberry from her practice, nor did she intend to refuse to pay for an interpreter in the future. Dr. Von Valtier claims to have a specific protocol for discharging patients, and that protocol was not initiated in this case. Dr. Von Valtier sums up the purpose of her letter as a protest of the Americans with Disabilities Act, saying:

I felt that although this ADA is the law of the land, and I have to obey it, I don't think it's fair. I wanted to protest it. I feel that I have a right to protest it even though I have to obey it. And this was one protest that I could make because of the fact that for six years, Shirley Mayberry and I successfully communicated with each other with pencil and paper.

Plaintiff's complaint alleges that she has been denied future treatment by defendant because she is deaf. Plaintiff alleges that defendant's actions in refusing to provide interpreter services in the future, and in terminating her medical care, amounts to discrimination in violation of the Americans with Disabilities Act of 1990 (ADA), Section 504 of the Federal Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and the Michigan Handicappers' Civil Rights Act.

A. Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA)

The ADA defines discrimination as including a failure to take necessary steps to ensure that no individual with a disability is denied services because of the absence of auxiliary aids and services. The Department of Justice has promulgated regulations to implement the ADA, and states in its commentary on the final regulations: The auxiliary aid requirement is a flexible one. A public accommodation can choose among various alternatives as long as the result is effective communication. The regulations include examples of auxiliary aids and services required to be furnished where necessary to ensure effective communication. The examples given for persons with hearing losses include qualified interpreters and notetakers. 28 CFR §36.303(b)(1). The effective communication requirement of the ADA has been interpreted such that Congress expects places of public accommodation to consult with disabled persons when it comes to auxiliary aids for effective communication, but Congress does not mandate primary consideration of their expressed choices. 28 CFR 36.303, App. B.

The construction provision of the ADA states that the standards of title V of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973, and its regulations, are to apply, except where the ADA has explicitly adopted a different standard. 42 U.S.C. §12201(a). In order to make out a prima facie case under title III of the ADA, the plaintiff must prove (1) that she has a disability; (2) that defendant's office is a place of public accommodation; and (3) that she was discriminated against by being refused full and equal enjoyment of medical treatment because of her disability. Defendant maintains that intent to discriminate is a fourth element of plaintiff's prima facie case, relying on traditional disparate-treatment/disparate-impact and burden-shifting analyses used in discrimination cases.

Federal courts have struggled with the issue of whether intent to discriminate is an element to stating a prima facie case under the Rehabilitation Act. This Court will look to the cases interpreting the Rehabilitation Act for guidance, as there are no reported cases analyzing the requirements for sustaining a claim under the effective communication by a public accommodation provisions of the ADA. The [Supreme] Court [has] refused to hold that all showings of disparate impact on the handicapped constitute prima facie cases under §504, nor would it hold that proof of discriminatory intent was necessary in every case.

A disparate impact case is one in which a facially neutral practice impacts more harshly on one group of people than on others. For example, if defendant Von Valtier had announced a policy not to hire sign language interpreters for any patient, the impact would obviously be more profound on deaf patients. Such a policy, however, is not facially neutral in the same manner as the policy to reduce the number of annual inpatient hospital days that state Medicaid would pay for, which was the issue in Alexander v. Choate. The case presently before the Court does not involve a disparate impact, as plaintiff alleges that defendant specifically declined to provide her with an interpreter because she was disabled. Even though the Supreme Court addressed the issue of intent in a case where the discrimination complained of was in the form of a policy's impact rather than specific treatment, other courts have come to the same conclusion.

One of the stated purposes of the ADA is “to provide a clear and comprehensive national mandate for the elimination of discrimination against individuals with disabilities.” 42 U.S.C. §12101(b)(1). Congress specifically found that “individuals with disabilities continually encounter various forms of discrimination, including outright intentional exclusion [and] the discriminatory effects of ... communication barriers....” 42 U.S.C. §12101(a)(5). Given that statement, Congress appears to have intended the ADA to address the discriminatory effects of benign actions or inaction, as well as intentional discrimination. Based on the cases analyzing alleged violations of §504, the Court concludes that the Rehabilitation Act does not require a plaintiff to prove discriminatory intent in order to make out a prima facie case of handicap discrimination. The Court will apply the modified burden-shifting analysis developed in cases under the Rehabilitation Act to the ADA.

In order to set forth a prima facie case under title III of the ADA, plaintiff must prove that she has a disability, that defendant's office is a place of public accommodation, and that she was denied full and equal medical treatment because of her disability. Plaintiff must additionally show that she was denied treatment under circumstances which give rise to the inference that such denial was based solely on her handicap. If plaintiff succeeds in stating a prima facie case, the burden shifts to defendant to prove either that plaintiff was not denied medical treatment, or that such denial was not unlawful. The burden then shifts back to plaintiff to rebut defendant's reasons as pretext for unlawful discrimination.

In her attempt to make out a prima facie case under title III of the ADA, plaintiff has clearly proven that she has a disability and that defendant's office is a place of public accommodation. Plaintiff has also produced evidence giving rise to an inference that she was unlawfully discriminated against by being refused full and equal enjoyment of medical treatment because of her disability. As proof that defendant intended to refuse to hire an interpreter in the future, and to discharge plaintiff, plaintiff submits defendant's own words in the February 22, 1993 letter to Ms. Ferrero. In addition, plaintiff provides the affidavit of her daughter Ms. Langston which states that defendant wanted plaintiff to bring an interpreter to future appointments. Plaintiff also points to a note written by defendant on plaintiff's chart, that defendant misunderstood the exact location of plaintiff's pain due to poor communication. Finally, plaintiff submits a note written by defendant which instructs plaintiff to see an ophthalmologist, and suggests that she “take someone with her who signs so you can explain problem & answer their questions completely.”

The burden of proof shifts to defendant to prove that she did not refuse to hire an interpreter for plaintiff, nor did she refuse to treat plaintiff in the future. Defendant may attempt to show that an interpreter was not necessary to ensure effective communication with plaintiff during her medical appointments. Furthermore, places of public accommodation are exempt from complying with the ADA if they can demonstrate that taking such steps would fundamentally alter the nature of the services being offered, or would result in an undue burden. 42 U.S.C. §12182(b)(2)(A)(iii). Defendant, however, admitted at her deposition that she could afford to pay Ms. Ferrero's fee for interpreter services.

Defendant maintains that her letter to Ms. Ferrero was a protest of the ADA, and that she could adequately communicate with plaintiff by passing notes back and forth. The issue is how far defendant was willing to take her protest. It is true that plaintiff did not ask defendant what she intended by her letter, but it is not implausible for plaintiff to believe that defendant meant her words literally. Plaintiff has submitted evidence which would tend to show that passing notes did not result in effective communication with defendant. Commentary by the Department of Justice states that “[i]t is not difficult to imagine a wide range of communications involving areas such as health, legal matters, and finances that would be sufficiently lengthy or complex to require an interpreter for effective communication.” 28 CFR §36.303, App. B.

Plaintiff has come forth with enough evidence to survive summary judgment on her ADA claim. Plaintiff, however, is not entitled to money damages under the ADA, which limits the remedies available to private individuals to those set forth in the Civil Rights Act of 1964, 42 U.S.C. §2000a-3(a). 42 U.S.C. §12188(a)(1). Such remedies include permanent or temporary injunctions and restraining orders. Only when the Attorney General becomes involved in the matter may the Court award monetary damages to aggrieved persons. 42 U.S.C. §12188(b)(2)(B). Plaintiff is permitted to seek injunctive relief under the ADA, as well as attorneys fees. 42 U.S.C. §12188(b)(2), 12205.

[Rehabilitation Act and state law claims discussion is omitted.]

Defendant's motion for summary judgment is Denied in its entirety.

Questions

1. Does the fact that Dr. Von Valtier could “afford to pay” for the interpreter mean that it is not an undue burden?

2. Would it make a difference in the analysis of undue burden if the accommodation needed were a ramp to permit access to individuals with a mobility impairment instead of an interpreter?

3. Would it matter if Dr. Von Valtier had a large number of patients with hearing impairments who needed interpreter service?

Notes

1. The ADAAA states that auxiliary aids and services include “qualified interpreters or other effective methods of making aurally delivered materials available to individuals with hearing impairments.” 42 U.S.C. §12103 (1)(A).

On July 23, 2010, the Department of Justice issued final regulations effective March 15, 2011. 75 Fed. Reg. 56,164–236 (September 15, 2010) (Title II) and 75 Fed. Reg. 56,236–358 (September 15, 2010) (Title III). The new regulations amend both Title II and Title III regulations. One of the issues addressed in the revised regulations is the obligation regarding effective communication with persons with hearing impairments. The new regulations provide that the obligation extends to companions of individuals with disabilities. The guidance addressed the need to make an individualized assessment based on nature, length, and complexity of the communication, and the context. Individuals with disabilities should generally be consulted about the type of aid, but the public accommodation ultimately makes the decision so long as it is effective. The regulations clarify that an individual is not required to bring another individual to interpret nor to rely on an adult accompanying the individual to interpret. Exceptions are allowed in appropriate emergency situations. 28 C.F.R. §35.160 and §36.303(c). The Title II regulations further specify requirements regarding public entities using video remote interpreting services including quality of the equipment and interpreters and qualifications of users of the technology. 28 C.F.R. §35.160(d).

2. Mental Health Counseling Services for Individuals with Hearing Impairments. When the health care treatment in question involves psychological or psychiatric counseling where confidentiality is an important issue, are recipients of the treatment or counseling who are deaf entitled to have counselors who themselves sign and who understand the needs of the deaf community? The following excerpt from Tugg v. Towey, 864 F. Supp. 1201 (S.D. Fla. 1994), notes the court's response to several individuals with hearing impairments seeking counseling following Hurricane Andrew in Florida in 1993. The court granted a preliminary injunction, noting the following:

Section 35.164 [of Title II, ADA regulations] also places a limit on the lengths a public entity must go to provide auxiliary aids. It states that a public entity is not required to take any action if “it can demonstrate [the action] would result in a fundamental alteration in the nature of a device, program or activity or [create] an undue financial and administration burden.” ... Under those circumstances the public entity has the burden of demonstrating that providing the auxiliary aid for the disabled individual would create such a hardship. This determination must be made by the head of the public entity, who must set forth in writing the reasons why the entity cannot comply with the wishes of the disabled individual, after considering all available resources.

At the hearing, the Court invited the Defendants to address the issue of the harm they will suffer if the injunction is entered. Specifically, the Court asked for a cost benefit analysis the Defendants had conducted concluding that (1) providing the Plaintiffs with mental health counselors who possessed sign language ability and experience working with the deaf was too expensive to fit within the HRS budget and (2) that HRS's chosen alternative of providing qualified interpreters would cost the Defendants less money or create a lesser burden.

The Defendants replied that no such cost benefit analysis had been conducted. The evidence produced at the hearing indicated that under HRS's intended plan, it will cost an HRS contracting mental health provider a minimum of $35 per hour to provide a sign language interpreter in addition to the cost of the mental health counselor. Without the benefit of any accurate figures, logic would indicate that it would cost less to employ one individual to perform two tasks (signing and counseling) than two individuals to perform those same tasks. Counsel for the Defendants disputed this at the hearing, stating that because the pool of individuals meeting these qualifications is so small [estimating that the number in Dade and Monroe counties is four] the cost of securing their services would be higher. The Defendants, however, did not produce evidence to support this argument. The Defendants also did not demonstrate that they had complied with the requirements ... which [mandate] that the public entity set forth its findings as to why it rejected the auxiliary aid sought by a disabled individual after considering all available resources.

What if the plaintiffs seeking such services were in a small rural area of North Dakota? Is it likely that defendants would be more likely to ultimately succeed in demonstrating both undue financial and undue administrative burden?

3. In Aikins, it was the wife of the patient, not the patient himself, seeking the accommodation. In another case involving accommodation of someone other than the patient, a visitor to a hospital patient requested that she be able to hook up her breathing apparatus to the hospital's oxygen port when visiting her husband's room. The court held that the hospital was not required to provide this accommodation. Dryer v. Flower Hospital, 383 F. Supp. 2d 934 (N.D. Ohio 2005).

In 2013, the Justice Department reached five settlements to remedy alleged violations of the ADA. The agreements resolve allegations that five health care providers—including a hospital, skilled nursing facilities, a rehabilitation center, and a doctor's office—violated the ADA by failing to provide effective communication to people who are deaf or have hearing loss in the provision of medical services. For information on these settlements see the Department of Justice's Barrier-Free Health Care Initiative, a partnership of the Civil Rights Division and U.S. Attorney's offices across the nation, to target enforcement efforts on a critical area for individuals with disabilities, by accessing the Department of Justice ADA website at ADA.gov.

4. Department of Justice ADA regulations, effective March 15, 2011, amend both Title II and Title III regulations. Included in the revised regulations are provisions relating to physical design generally and specifically to dispersal of accessible patient bedrooms in medical care facilities, 28 C.F.R. §36.406(g). 75 Fed. Reg. 56,164–236 (September 15, 2010) (Title II) and 75 Fed. Reg. 56,236–358 (September 15, 2010) (Title III).

Other provisions give guidance regarding use of automated-attendant systems (such as voice mail and messaging) and require that systems must provide effective real-time communication with individuals using auxiliary aids and services, including TTYs or other FCC-approved relay systems. 28 C.F.R. §35.161.

D. Health Insurance

The previous sections addressed the challenges of discrimination, environmental barriers, and the need for reasonable accommodations as barriers to health care for individuals with disabilities. While these barriers are significant, the major barrier is having health insurance to pay for health care services. Because much health insurance is tied to the workplace, individuals with disabilities face two problems.

First, they must be able to obtain and keep a job to access employer-provided health insurance. Employers concerned about the high cost of health care for individuals with disabilities have a disincentive in many cases to hire such individuals even though it violates disability discrimination laws to do so. And as health insurance costs rise, employers may increasingly decide not to provide health insurance to any of their employees. In doing so, however, employers would face penalties under the ACA. Whether such penalties are sufficient to deter employers from foregoing offering health insurance benefits is unclear. Individuals with disabilities may be able to receive health care insurance, however, through Medicare (if they are permanently and totally disabled) or Medicaid (if they are disabled and with very limited income), or through the ACA, which now provides for health care exchanges for persons who do not work or do not get their health insurance at work.

Second, some individuals with disabilities, because of the limitations of their conditions, may not be able to work. The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act (HIPAA), 42 U.S.C. §300gg, passed in 1996, prohibits disability-based discrimination in health insurance only with regard to employer-sponsored group health plans. HIPAA is important because it prohibits treating health conditions as a preexisting condition for purposes of limiting or excluding benefits. Thus, a person who changes employment becomes eligible for health insurance with the new employer, and, if unemployed, may continue his health insurance at an increased cost.

While previously obtaining health care coverage through an individual health insurance policy was not a viable option for many individuals with disabilities who were not employed because it was extremely expensive to purchase individual health insurance, some of these concerns have been ameliorated by the ACA. The ACA does not permit insurers to exclude coverage of preexisting conditions or to use health status when considering eligibility. In theory and in practice, the ACA has made it much more possible and affordable for persons with disabilities to get access to health insurance. See Jessica L. Roberts, Health Law as Disability Rights Law, 97 MINN. L. REV. 1963 (2013) (demonstrating how facilitating access to private insurance through state exchanges and abolition of preexisting condition consideration broadens access); Michael R. Ulrich, JD, MPH, Health Affairs Blog Post: Challenges for People with Disabilities Within the Health Care Safety Net, 15 YALE J. HEALTH POL'Y, L. & ETHICS 247, 250 (2015) (ACA has taken important steps toward filling the gaps in our insurance system). Nonetheless, Medicaid remains the source for long-term home and community-based services, and individuals with disabilities who do not qualify for Medicaid may face costly insurance plans to get these services. See Silvia Yee, The Affordable Care Act and People with Disabilities, GPSolo, Mar/Apr./2015, at 16. Moreover, there are increasing reports that many health care providers—doctors and hospitals—are refusing to accept insurance provided by the ACA, and that insurance companies are refusing to write policies or are raising their premiums. See Kimberly Leonard, Doctors, Hospitals Say “No” to Obamacare Plans, http://www.usnews.com/news/articles/2015/11/04/doctors-hospitals-wont-accept-obamacare-marketplace-plans; Elisabeth Rosenthal, Sorry, We Don't Take Obamacare, N.Y. TIMES, May 15, 2016, at SR1, available at http://nyti.ms/27nbtw8; Reed Abelson & Margot Sanger-Katz, Obamacare Premiums Are Rising, Not a Little, N.Y. TIMES, June 16, 2016, at B1, available at http://nyti.ms/1UzHojD; Carolyn Y. Johnson, UnitedHealth Group to Exit Obamacare Exchanges in All but a “Handful” of States, WASHINGTON POST WONKBLOG. Apr. 19, 2016, https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/wonk/wp/2016/04/19/unitedhealth-group-to-exit-obamacare-exchanges-in-all-but-a-handful-of-states/.

With respect to insurance providers, there are a number of issues under the ADA, the Rehabilitation Act, and even some state laws. The first question is whether the ADA was intended to exempt health insurance programs from Title III application because traditionally health insurance has been regulated by the states. Most courts have not found there to be an exemption.

With respect to all insurance (health, life, and other insurance) there is an additional issue—whether Title III would apply only to accessing the service and not to distinctions related to the coverage itself. There is no question that insurance offices are public accommodations covered by Title III. There is, however, an unresolved question as to whether Title III regulates the content of the insurance policy. The majority and dissenting opinions in the next case illustrate the reasoning behind the two views.

John Doe and Richard Smith v. Mutual of Omaha Insurance Company

179 F.3d 557 (7th Cir. 1999)

OPINION BY: JUDGE RICHARD POSNER

Mutual of Omaha appeals from a judgment that the AIDS caps in two of its health insurance policies violate the public accommodations provision of the Americans with Disabilities Act. One policy limits lifetime benefits for AIDS or AIDS-related conditions (ARC) to $25,000, the other limits them to $100,000, while for other conditions the limit in both policies is $1 million. Mutual of Omaha has stipulated that it “has not shown and cannot show that its AIDS Caps are or ever have been consistent with sound actuarial principles, actual or reasonably anticipated experience, bona fide risk classification, or state law.” It also concedes that AIDS is a disabling condition within the meaning of the Americans with Disabilities Act. Since the Supreme Court held in Bragdon that infection with the AIDS virus (HIV) is a disabling condition from the onset of the infection before any symptoms appear, it is apparent that both ARC and AIDS are disabilities. Mutual of Omaha does not question this, but argues only that the Americans with Disabilities Act does not regulate the content of insurance policies.

Title III of the Act, in section 302(a), provides that “no individual shall be discriminated against on the basis of disability in the full and equal enjoyment of the goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, or accommodations of any place of public accommodation” by the owner, lessee, or operator of such a place. The core meaning of this provision, plainly enough, is that the owner or operator of a store, hotel, restaurant, dentist's office, travel agency, theater, Web site, or other facility (whether in physical space or in electronic space) that is open to the public cannot exclude disabled persons from entering the facility and, once in, from using the facility in the same way that the nondisabled do. The owner or operator of, say, a camera store can neither bar the door to the disabled nor let them in but then refuse to sell its cameras to them on the same terms as to other customers.

Mutual of Omaha does not refuse to sell insurance policies to such persons—it was happy to sell health insurance policies to the two plaintiffs. But because of the AIDS caps, the policies have less value to persons with AIDS than they would have to persons with other, equally expensive diseases or disabilities. This does not make the offer to sell illusory, for people with AIDS have medical needs unrelated to AIDS, and the policies give such people as much coverage for those needs as the policies give people who don't have AIDS. If all the medical needs of people with AIDS were AIDS-related and thus excluded by the policies, this might support an inference that Mutual of Omaha was trying to exclude such people, and such exclusion, as we shall see, might violate the Act. But that is not argued.

Since most health-insurance policies contain caps, the position urged by the plaintiffs would discriminate among diseases. Diseases that happened to be classified as disabilities could not be capped, but equally or more serious diseases that are generally not disabling, such as heart disease, could be. Moreover, the plaintiffs acknowledge the right of an insurance company to exclude coverage for an applicant's pre-existing medical conditions. If the applicant is already HIV-positive when he applies for a health-insurance policy, the insurer can in effect cap his AIDS-related coverage at $0. This “discrimination” is not limited to AIDS or for that matter to disabilities, which is why the plaintiffs do not challenge it; but it suggests that the rule for which they contend is at once arbitrary and unlikely to do much for people with AIDS.

The insurance company asks us to compare this case to one in which a person with one leg complains of a shoestore's refusal to sell shoes other than by the pair, or in which a blind person complains of a bookstore's refusal to stock books printed in Braille. We do not understand the plaintiffs to be contending that such complaints are actionable under section 302(a), even though there is a sense in which the disabled individual would be denied the full and equal enjoyment of the services that the store offers. In fact, it is apparent that a store is not required to alter its inventory in order to stock goods such as Braille books that are especially designed for disabled people. But it is apparent as a matter of interpretation rather than compelled by a simple reading which would place the present case on the other side of the line; and so the case cannot be resolved by reference simply to the language of section 302(a).

The common sense of the statute is that the content of the goods or services offered by a place of public accommodation is not regulated. A camera store may not refuse to sell cameras to a disabled person, but it is not required to stock cameras specially designed for such persons. Had Congress purposed to impose so enormous a burden on the retail sector of the economy and so vast a supervisory responsibility on the federal courts, we think it would have made its intention clearer and would at least have imposed some standards. It is hardly a feasible judicial function to decide whether shoestores should sell single shoes to one-legged persons and if so at what price, or how many Braille books the Borders or Barnes and Noble bookstore chains should stock in each of their stores. There are defenses to a prima facie case of public-accommodation discrimination, but they would do little to alleviate the judicial burden of making standardless decisions about the composition of retail inventories. The only defense that might apply to the Braille case or the pair of shoes case is that the modification of a seller's existing practices that is necessary to provide equal access to the disabled “would fundamentally alter the nature of ... [the seller's] services,” and it probably would not apply to either case and certainly not to the Braille one.

The plaintiffs might be able to distinguish the shoestore hypothetical by pointing out that a nondisabled person might be in the market for one shoe simply because he had lost a shoe; in refusing to sell single shoes the store thus would not be refusing to adapt its service to a class of customers limited to disabled people. But the Braille case, and many others that we can imagine (such as a furniture store's decision not to stock wheelchairs, or a psychiatrist's refusal to treat schizophrenia, as distinct from his refusing to treat schizophrenics for the psychiatric disorders in which he specializes, or a movie theater's refusal to provide a running translation into sign language of the movie's soundtrack), cannot be so distinguished, although some of them might find shelter in the “fundamental alteration” defense. All are cases of refusing to configure a service to make it as valuable to a disabled as to a nondisabled customer.

It might seem that the AIDS caps could be distinguished from the “refusal to stock” cases because the caps include complications of AIDS. If being infected by HIV leads one to contract pneumonia, the cost of treating the pneumonia is subject to the AIDS cap; if a person not infected by HIV contracts pneumonia, the costs of treating his pneumonia are fully covered. It looks, therefore, like a difference in treatment referable solely to the fact that one person is disabled and the other not.

But this is not correct. The essential point to understand is that HIV doesn't cause illness directly. What it does is weaken and eventually destroy the body's immune system. As the immune system falters, the body becomes prey to diseases that the system protects us against. These “opportunistic” diseases that HIV allows, as it were, to ravage the body are exotic cancers and rare forms of pneumonia and other infectious diseases. To refer to them as “complications” of HIV or AIDS is not incorrect, but it is misleading, because they are the chief worry of anyone who has the misfortune to be afflicted with AIDS. An AIDS cap would be meaningless if it excluded the opportunistic diseases that are the most harmful consequences of being infected by the AIDS virus.

What the AIDS caps in the challenged insurance policies cover, therefore, is the cost of fighting the AIDS virus itself and trying to keep the immune system intact plus the cost of treating the opportunistic diseases to which the body becomes prey when the immune system has eroded to the point at which one is classified as having AIDS. The principal opportunistic diseases of AIDS, such as Kaposi's sarcoma, Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia, AIDS wasting, and esophageal candidiasis, are rarely encountered among people who are not infected by HIV—so rarely as to be described frequently as “AIDS-defining opportunistic infections.” The frequency of Pneumocystis carinii pneumonia, for example, “among patients infected with human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) far exceeds that among other immuno-compromised hosts” and is “a leading cause of opportunistic infection and death among AIDS patients in industrialized countries.” It is these distinctive diseases that are the target (along with the costs of directly treating infection by HIV) of the AIDS caps. This is not a case of refusing, for example, to provide the same coverage for a broken leg, or other afflictions not peculiar to people with AIDS, to such people, which would be a good example of discrimination by reason of disability.

It is true that as the immune system collapses because of infection by HIV, the patient becomes subject to opportunistic infection not only by the distinctive AIDS-defining diseases but also by a host of diseases to which people not infected with HIV are subject. Even when they are the same disease, however, they are far more lethal when they hit a person who does not have an immune system to fight back with. Which means they are not really the same disease. This is not a point that is peculiar to AIDS. The end stage of many diseases is an illness different from the one that brought the patient to that stage; nowadays when a person dies of pneumonia, it is usually because his body has been gravely weakened by some other ailment. If a health insurance policy that excluded coverage for cancer was interpreted not to cover the pneumonia that killed a patient terminally ill with cancer, this would not be “discrimination” against cancer.

To summarize the discussion to this point, we cannot find anything in the Americans with Disabilities Act or its background, or the nature of AIDS and AIDS caps, to justify so radically expansive an interpretation as would be required to bring these cases under section 302(a) without making an unprincipled distinction between AIDS caps and other product alterations—unless it is section 501(c)(1) of the Act. That section provides that Title I (employment discrimination against the disabled) and Title III (public accommodations, the title involved in this case) “shall not be construed to prohibit or restrict an insurer ... from underwriting risks, classifying risks, or administering such risks that are based on or not inconsistent with State law,” unless the prohibition or restriction is “a subterfuge to evade the purposes” of either title. §12201(c). Even with the “subterfuge” qualification, section 501(c) is obviously intended for the benefit of insurance companies rather than plaintiffs and it may seem odd therefore to find the plaintiffs placing such heavy weight on what is in effect a defense to liability. But a defense can cast light on what is to be defended against, that is, what the prima facie case of a violation is. Suppose, for example, that a statute regulated the sale of “animals” but it was unclear whether the legislature had meant to include fish. Were there a statutory exclusion for goldfish, it would be pretty clear that “animals” included fish, since otherwise there would be no occasion for such an exclusion. And, with that clarified, the advocate of regulating the sale of a particular goldfish would have to show only that the exclusion was somehow inapplicable to him. That is the plaintiffs' strategy here. They use the insurance provision to show that section 302(a) regulates content, then argue that the excluding provision is narrow enough to allow them to challenge the coverage limits in Mutual of Omaha's policies. There is even some legislative history, which the plaintiffs hopefully call “definitive,” to section 501(c) that suggests that an insurance company can limit coverage on the basis of a disability only if the limitation is based either on claims experience or on sound actuarial methods for classifying risks. And Mutual of Omaha conceded itself out of relying on section 501(c)'s safe harbor by stipulating that it cannot show that its AIDS caps are based on sound actuarial principles or claims experience or are consistent with state law.

The plaintiffs argue, consistent with our goldfish example, that the insurance exemption has no function if section 302(a) does not regulate the content of insurance policies, and so we should infer that the section does not regulate that content. But this reasoning is not correct. If it were, it would imply that section 302(a) regulates the content not only of insurance policies but also of all other products and services, since the section is not limited to insurance. The insurance industry may have worried that the section would be given just the expansive interpretation that the district court gave it in this case, and so the industry may have obtained the rule of construction in section 501(c) just to backstop its argument that section 302(a) regulates only access and not content. Or it may have worried about being sued under section 302(a) for refusing to sell an insurance policy to a disabled person. Remember that the right of full and equal enjoyment as we interpret it includes the right to buy on equal terms and not just the right to enter the store. For Mutual of Omaha to take the position that people with AIDS are so unhealthy that it won't sell them health insurance would be a prima facie violation of section 302(a). But the insurance company just might be able to steer into the safe harbor provided by section 501(c), provided it didn't run afoul of the “subterfuge” limitation, as it would do if, for example, it had adopted the AIDS caps to deter people who know they are HIV positive from buying the policies at all.

The legislative history is consistent with this interpretation. Both committee reports on which the plaintiffs rely give the example of refusing to sell an insurance policy to a blind person, as does the gloss placed on section 501(c) by the Department of Justice. A refusal to sell insurance to a blind person is not the same thing as a provision in the policy that if the insured becomes blind, the insurer will not pay the expense of his learning Braille. We find nothing in the language or history of the statute to suggest that the latter refusal would be unlawful. The Department's Technical Assistance Manual, supra, §III-3.11000, contains somewhat broader language than either the statute or the regulation or the committee reports, language about insurers' being forbidden to discriminate on the basis of disability in the sale, terms, or conditions of insurance contracts; but basically this just parrots the statute and the regulation and does not indicate a focused attention to coverage limits. There is, as we have pointed out, a difference between refusing to sell a health-insurance policy at all to a person with AIDS, or charging him a higher price for such a policy, or attaching a condition obviously designed to deter people with AIDS from buying the policy (such as refusing to cover such a person for a broken leg), on the one hand, and, on the other, offering insurance policies that contain caps for various diseases some of which may also be disabilities within the meaning of the Americans with Disabilities Act.

We conclude that section 302(a) does not require a seller to alter his product to make it equally valuable to the disabled and to the nondisabled, even if the product is insurance. This conclusion is consistent with all the appellate cases to consider this or cognate issues.

EVANS, CIRCUIT JUDGE, dissenting.

The Americans with Disabilities Act is a broad, sweeping, protective statute requiring the elimination of discrimination against individuals with disabilities. Because I believe the insurance policies challenged in this case discriminate against people with AIDS in violation of the ADA, I dissent.

The majority believes we are being asked to regulate the content of insurance policies—something we should not do under the ADA. But as I see it we are not being asked to regulate content; we are being asked to decide whether an insurer can discriminate against people with AIDS, refusing to pay for them the same expenses it would pay if they did not have AIDS. The ADA assigns to courts the task of passing judgment on such conduct. And to me, the Mutual of Omaha policies at issue violate the Act.

Chief Judge Posner's opinion likens the insurance company here to a camera store forced to stock cameras specially designed for disabled persons. While I agree that the ADA would not require a store owner to alter its inventory, I think the analogy misses the mark. The better analogy would be that of a store which lets disabled customers in the door, but then refuses to sell them anything but inferior cameras. To pick up on another analogy raised at oral argument, we are not being asked to force a restaurant to alter its menu to accommodate disabled diners; we are being asked to stop a restaurant that is offering to its nondisabled diners a menu containing a variety of entrees while offering a menu with only limited selections to its disabled patrons. Section 501(c)'s “safe harbor” would allow Mutual of Omaha to treat insureds with AIDS differently than those without AIDS if the discrimination were consistent with Illinois law or could be justified by actuarial principles or claims experience. But Mutual of Omaha conceded that its AIDS and ARC caps do not fall under the ADA's safe harbor protection.

The parties stipulated that the very same affliction (e.g., pneumonia) may be both AIDS-related and not AIDS-related and that, in such cases, coverage depends solely on whether the patient has AIDS. In my view that is more than enough to trigger an ADA violation. Chief Judge Posner reasons that, although the policies appear to discriminate solely based on an insured's HIV status, they really don't, when you consider the nature of AIDS. He suggests that the phrase “AIDS related conditions” embodies a unique set of symptoms and afflictions that would make it easy for the insurance company to determine with certainty whether an expense incurred for a particular illness is “AIDS-related” and therefore subject to the cap. His analysis—charitable to Mutual of Omaha to be sure—may very well be medically sound. But it doesn't come from the insurance policies. The policies don't even hint at what illnesses or afflictions might fall within the ARC exclusion. Nor has the medical community embraced an accepted definition for what “conditions” are “AIDS-related.” The practical effect of all this, as Mutual of Omaha concedes, is that coverage for certain expenses would be approved or denied based solely on whether the insured had AIDS. Given that the ADA is supposed to signal a “clear and comprehensive national mandate for the elimination of discrimination against individuals with disabilities,” I would use the statute to right the wrong committed by Mutual of Omaha.

Notes and Questions

1. Which arguments are more convincing? Those of Judge Posner in the majority opinion in Mutual of Omaha or those of Judge Evans' dissent? Why? For other cases deciding this issue, see Sirva Relocation, LLC v. Richie, 794 F.3d 185, 199 (1st Cir. 2015) (noting that many circuits permit “an employer to offer disparate benefits based on the type of disability that may afflict an employee,” but that the issue is not resolved given a split among the districts within the First Circuit); Baron v. Dulinski, 928 F. Supp. 2d 38, 43 (D.D.C. 2013) (“Title III does not reach the terms of the policies offered by an insurer”). Compare Chabner v. United of Omaha Life Insurance Co., 225 F.3d 1042 (9th Cir. 2000) (holding that Title III does not permit individuals to challenge the substantive provisions of insurance contracts), and Carparts Distrib. Ctr., Inc. v. Automotive Wholesaler's Ass'n, 37 F.3d 12 (1st Cir. 1994) (Title III not limited to physical structure). The issue has not yet been resolved by the Supreme Court.

2. In a preliminary order in the case of Carparts Distrib. Ctr., Inc. v. Automotive Wholesaler's Ass'n, 37 F.3d 12 (1st Cir. 1994), the court overruled the lower court, and held that Title III (Public Accommodations) was not limited to actual physical structures with definite physical boundaries in which an individual would physically enter to use the facilities or obtain services. This decision means that a health benefit plan provided through an employer might be considered to be a Title III public accommodation. The case involves a health benefit plan offered to auto parts distributor members. The plan placed a cap on AIDS-related illnesses. The case also was brought under Title I. The First Circuit held that a health care plan that acts as an agent of an employer or is controlled by the employer may be subject to Title I of the ADA. For a more recent decision in this issue, review Parker, in Chapter 4[B], supra.

3. For an argument that Doe was wrongly decided, see Jeffrey W. Stempel, An Inconsistently Sensitive Mind: Richard Posner's Cerebration of Insurance Law and Continuing Blind Spots of Econominalism, 7 CONN. INS. L.J. 7, 65–68 (2000–2001) (arguing that Judge Posner should not have equated the situation present in Doe in which the plaintiff was already a policyholder with a decision to deny coverage to someone who has AIDS as a pre-existing condition).

4. There was a second reason upon which Judge Posner relied to find no violation of Title III. He concluded that if Title III regulates the content of an insurance policy, it would violate the McCarran-Ferguson Act, which prohibits courts from construing any federal act that does not directly regulate insurance to impair state insurance law. This is likely the strongest argument for finding that the ADA does not apply to the content of insurance policies, see Jeffrey W. Stempel, 7 CONN. INS. L.J. 7, 69 (2000–2001), but, at least according to Professor Stempel, is still insufficient for finding for the insurance company.

5. 42 U.S.C. §12201(c) (Section 501(c)) creates an exception to Title III. It states:

(c) Insurance. Subchapters I through III of this chapter [Titles I through III] and Title IV of this Act shall not be construed to prohibit or restrict—

1. an insurer, hospital, or medical service company, health maintenance organization, or any agent or entity that administers benefit plans, or similar organizations from underwriting risks, classifying risks, or administering such risks that are based on or not inconsistent with State law; or

2. a person or organization covered by this chapter from establishing, sponsoring, observing or administering the terms of a bona fide benefit plan that are based on underwriting risks, classifying risks, or administering such risks that are based on or not inconsistent with State law; or

3. a person or organization covered by this chapter from establishing, sponsoring, observing, or administering the terms of a bona fide benefit plan that is not subject to State laws that regulate insurance.

Paragraphs (1), (2) and (3) shall not be used as a subterfuge to evade the purposes of subchapter I and III of this chapter. [titles I and III].

Why did the plaintiffs in Mutual of Omaha raise this section to support their claim? Why did Mutual of Omaha not use this section as a defense? Explain. For a discussion of Section 501(c) and its legislative history, see H. Miriam Farber, Note, Subterfuge: Do Coverage Limitations and Exclusions in Employer-Provided Health Care Plans Violate the Americans with Disabilities Act? 69 N.Y.U. L. REV. 850 (1994).

—————

Assuming that health insurance programs are subject to the ADA, either as an employment benefit under Title I or as a public accommodation under Title III, there are a number of other issues that arise with respect to individuals with disabilities. One major issue is whether caps on benefits or denial of benefits for certain conditions is permissible. Related to that issue is whether insurers must provide parity for mental and physical conditions. The ADA expects that distinctions be based on legitimate actuarial data or reasonable experience.

Finally, employees may not be terminated to deprive them of employment benefits, including insurance. The Employee Retirement Income Security Act (ERISA), 29 U.S.C. §§1000–1461 prohibits that directly, and the ADA may also apply in some cases to prohibit such action.

For case citations and further discussion related these issues, see LAURA ROTHSTEIN & JULIA IRZYK, DISABILITIES AND THE LAW §10.02 (2012 and cumulative supplement).

Access to health insurance is a complex matter for individuals with disabilities. The issues to be addressed in this area include whether health insurance is even covered under the ADA, whether differential treatment for different conditions is permissible, and whether discrimination in health insurance in other respects is permitted.

Notes

1. Caps on Fertility Treatment: As was noted above, insurance plans that deny coverage for certain diseases may be found to violate the ADA. Would a cap on fertility treatment or a denial of benefits for fertility treatment violate the ADA? Is this issue affected by the decision in Bragdon v. Abbott, earlier in this Chapter. Would an insurance company's decision not to fund Viagra be affected by the ADA?

2. Mental Health Parity. Historically, one of the most contentious issues about discriminatory treatment involved the distinction between benefits for treating physical conditions and mental health conditions. Most courts dealing with this issue have held that the ADA does not prohibit an employer under Title I from offering a plan that grants differential benefits for physical and mental illnesses. See, e.g., Fuller v. J.P. Morgan Chase & Co., 423 F.3d (2d Cir. 2005) (holding that it is not a violation of the ADA for an employer-provided long term disability plan to distinguish between physical and mental illness and even though the plaintiff's bipolar disease may have a biological cause, the disorder was still caused by a mental illness). This controversy ultimately resulted in the passage of mental health parity legislation in 2008.

The Paul Wellstone and Pete Domenici Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008 (MHPAEA), 29 U.S.C. §1185a and 42 U.S.C. §300gg-5, took effect in January 2009. Its purpose was to assure parity in the insurance coverage of mental health and addiction related treatments with coverage of other non-mental health and addiction treatments. The MHPAEA applies to group health plans or health insurance coverage offered in connection with group plans that provide both medical and surgical benefits and new mental health or substance use disorder benefits. It states that:

1. financial requirements such as deductibles, copayments, co-insurance and out-of-pocket expenses that are applicable to the mental health or substance use disorder benefits may not be more restrictive than those applied to medical and surgical benefits;

2. there can be no separate cost sharing requirements that are applicable only with respect to mental health or substance use disorder benefits; and

3. limits on frequency of treatment, number of visits, days of coverage or other similar limits on the scope of duration of treatment applicable to mental health or substance use disorders may not be more restrictive than those for other medical and surgical benefits.

The MHPAEA does not apply to group health plans of small employers with fewer than 50 employees, and it has cost exemptions for plans whose costs rise as a result of compliance with the Act 2% or more in the first plan year and 1% in any subsequent year. The cost exemption allows the plan not to adhere to the MHPAEA for one plan year.

While the MHPAEA contains these exceptions and exemptions, it improves insurance parity for mental health and addiction disorder services over the previous Mental Health Parity Act of 1996. The Mental Health Parity Act of 1996 regulated only spending caps, and required that plans offering mental health coverage have the same caps for mental and physical health. Insurers were able to side-step these requirements by converting spending caps to inpatient-day and outpatient-visit limits. The MHPAEA does not permit this behavior. Nonetheless, it applies only when the group plans offer mental health benefits or substance use benefits. It does not mandate coverage of mental illnesses or illnesses related to substance abuse. Besides the federal restrictions on insurance coverage, there are at least 46 states that provide some form of mental health parity legislation.

Of course, the Patient Protection and Affordable Care Act (“Obamacare” or the “ACA”) has made inroads into the problems that had not been solved by the MHPA and the MHPAEA. Here is an outline of the coverage by all three of these acts, and an explanation of the problems still existing:^1

Coverage and Existing Problems of the MHPA, MHPAEA, and ACA

1.1 MHPA (1996) This statute regulated only large group health plans that voluntarily offered mental health benefits in addition to physical health benefits.

1.2 The regulated large group health plans mentioned in 1.1 were required to ensure parity in terms of lifetime and annual spending limits between those voluntarily offered physical health benefits and voluntarily offered mental health benefits. Thus, it would be a violation of MHPA for a large group health plan, for example, to have a $1 million lifetime spending cap on voluntarily covered cancer care, and a $10,000 lifetime spending cap on voluntarily covered major depression care.

1.3 The MHPA did not regulate small group health plans or individual health plans or any other health plans. Therefore, it would be perfectly legal for a coffee shop with 10 employees to have good (high) physical health insurance benefits and bad (low) or no mental health benefits.

1.4 The MHPA did not require regulated large group health plans to offer any mental health benefits. (Since it doesn't regulate small group plans or individual plans, it also therefore did not require small group plans or individual plans to offer any mental health benefits.) Thus, it would be legal under the MHPA for a regulated large group plan (and of course a non-regulated small group plan or individual plan, that isn't regulated at all under the statute) to only offer physical health insurance benefits (e.g., cancer, pregnancy) but no mental health insurance benefits (e.g., depression, addiction).

2.1 MHPAEA (2008) This statute was an improvement on the MPHA, but, like the MPHA, it only regulated large group health plans that voluntarily offered mental health benefits in addition to physical health benefits.

2.2 Regulated large group health plans under the MHPAEA had to ensure parity in terms of financial requirements (e.g., deductibles, copayments, co-insurance amounts) and treatment limitations (e.g., inpatient day limitations, outpatient visit limitations) between offered physical health insurance benefits and offered mental health insurance benefits. Therefore, it would be a violation of MHPAEA for a regulated large group health plan to have a $500 deductible for cancer care but a $1,000 deductible for depression care. It would also be a violation of MHPAEA for a regulated large group health plan, for example, to cover 365 inpatient hospital days for cancer care but only 10 inpatient hospital days for suicide prevention.

2.3 The MHPAEA, like the MHPA, did not regulate small group health plans or individual health plans or any other health plans. Therefore, it would be legal, for example, for a coffee shop with 10 employees to have good (high) physical health insurance benefits and bad (low) or no mental health benefits.

2.4 The MPHAEA, like the MHPA, did not even require regulated large group health plans to offer any mental health benefits. (Since it doesn't regulate small group plans or individual plans, it also, therefore, did not require small group plans or individual plans to offer any mental health benefits.) Therefore, it would be legal under the MHPAEA for a regulated large group plan (and of course a non-regulated small group plan or individual plan) to offer only physical health insurance benefits (e.g., cancer, pregnancy) and no mental health insurance benefits (e.g., depression, addiction).

3.1 ACA (2010) The ACA was designed to fill the gaps in coverage under the MHPA and the MHPAEA. The ACA extended the parity requirements in the MHPA and the MHPAEA to individual and small group plans.

3.2 In addition, the ACA requires individual and small group plans to offer mental health and substance use disorder benefits. This is extremely important because it is the first time in history that these benefits were required by federal law. Under the ACA, this is called a “mandatory insurance benefit.”

3.3 Unfortunately, the provision that makes mental health and substance use disorder benefits mandatory in individual and small group plans does not apply to large group health plans (e.g, the health plans of Target, Walmart, and other large corporations etc.) self-insured health plans, and grandfathered health plans (i.e., health plans that were in effect as of March 23, 2010, and that have not substantially increased cost sharing or substantially lowered insurance benefits). In the state of Nevada, for example, less than 10% of individuals have their insurance through an individual or small group health plan. Therefore, only 10% of Nevadans receive the new mandatory mental health and substance use disorder insurance benefits and other essential health benefits (EHBs). Of course, large employers may voluntarily offer these benefits, and many do, but they are not required to do so. For further explanation and an argument for the extension of the ACA provision requiring mental health and substance abuse coverage to large group health plan market, the grandfathered health plan market, and the self insured health market, see Stacey A. Tovino, A Proposal for Comprehensive and Specific Essential Mental Health and Substance Use Disorder Benefits, 38 American J.L. & Med. 471 (2012); Stacey A. Tovino, All Illnesses Are (Not) Created Equal: Reforming Federal Mental Health Insurance Law, 49 Harvard J. Legis. 1 (2012).

3. Applicability of the ADA to Employer Provided Insurance. Health benefits provided directly by the employer might be covered under Title I of the ADA. While the ADA is a broad non-discrimination mandate, it offers a safe harbor to insurance companies and employers whose risk assessment leads to more expensive insurance to persons with disabilities so long as the purpose of the assessment is not a subterfuge to evade the purposes of the Act.

4. National Health Care Reform. President Obama's national health care reform envisioned that most of the uninsured Americans would have coverage through their employers, Medicare or Medicaid, a private insurer, a publicly funded insurance program (the “public option”), or non-profit co-operatives. The ACA was passed and enacted into law. It is currently the law, and it has survived two challenges in the Supreme Court.

5. Genetic Information Non-Discrimination Act (GINA). GINA applies both to employers who provide insurance and to health insurance providers. See Chapter 3 for a discussion of GINA and employers' responsibilities. For health insurers, the Act amended the Employee Retirement Income Security Act of 1974 (ERISA), the Public Health Service Act, the Internal Revenue Code of 1986, and the Social Security Act (medigap provisions). For group insurance plans, GINA prohibits the use of genetic information to increase group rates. It also prohibits the group health plan or a health insurer offering insurance in connection with a group plan from requiring genetic tests of individuals or family members, or from using the results of such genetic tests to set premiums. A “research exception” permits insurers to request, but not require, genetic testing under certain conditions, including that taking a genetic test must be voluntary, that non-compliance may not affect insurance premiums, and that the information gleaned from a genetic test may not be used for underwriting purposes. The Act also prohibits group health insurers from requesting, requiring or purchasing genetic information for underwriting purposes.

With reference to individual health insurance plans, the Act prohibits insurers from using genetic information for establishing rules for eligibility, and for setting premium rates. It also prohibits using the manifestation of a disease in a family member of the applicant for insurance for eligibility or premium rates, and prohibits use of genetic information as a “pre-existing condition” for the individual. It does not prohibit the use of the manifestation of disease of the individual seeking insurance for purposes of defining eligibility or rates, or of a family member if the family member is covered by the policy in question.

E. Summary

This chapter deals with the protections afforded by the ADA, the Rehabilitation Act, and other federal statutes to persons with disabilities in the context of receiving health care. Those protections include the right of access to health care in a health care setting that is the equal to that for persons without disabilities, the right of access to newly constructed or altered health care facilities without architectural barriers, and the right of reasonable accommodations in health care settings such as auxiliary aids and services. It may also include a right to substantive parity in health insurance, but most courts have held that Title III of the ADA does not apply to the substance of health insurance policies.

Besides the ADA and the Rehabilitation Act, a number of recently-enacted federal statutes promote access to health care through insurance and payment of medical expenses for persons with disabilities. The Mental Health Parity and Addiction Equity Act of 2008 (MHPAEA) and the Affordable Care Act attempt to guarantee more equitable insurance coverage of impairments of mental and physical health. Another statute, the Genetic Information Nondiscrimination Act, protects against discrimination in insurance based on a person's or his family's genetic makeup.

1. Two other Supreme Court decisions have addressed health care issues indirectly, but these decisions do not have the significant precedential application that is found in the three decisions discussed in this chapter. Irving Indep. Sch. Dist. v. Tatro, 468 U.S. 883 (1984), excerpted in Chapter 7[B][2], supra, was not a Rehabilitation Act case. It addressed the question of whether catheterization is a “related service” rather than a “medical service” to determine whether schools are obligated to provide this service within the mandates of the Individuals with Disabilities Education Act (formerly the Education for All Handicapped Children Act). Traynor v. Turnage, 485 U.S. 535 (1988), discussed in Chapter 2[B][6], supra, involved a Veterans' Administration policy against providing educational benefits for primary alcoholics (alcoholism based on willful misconduct). The decision is not a health care access case, but since the same reasoning could apply to health care benefits, it should be mentioned at this point. The Court held that this policy does not violate Section 504. This decision was based on an assessment that congressional intent was clear when Congress indicated that these benefits should not be made available to veterans whose delay in requesting them was a result of their own willful misconduct. The regulations implementing this legislation distinguish between primary alcoholism and secondary alcoholism which relates to organic diseases and disabilities resulting from the chronic use of alcohol. 38 C.F.R. §3.301(c)(2).

2. In subsection (a) the Department “encourages each recipient health care provider that provides health care services to infants” to establish an “Infant Care Review Committee (ICRC)” to assist in the development of treatment standards for handicapped infants and to provide assistance in making individual treatment decisions. In subsection (f), the Department describes its version of a model ICRC. Subsection (f) also provides that “[t]he activities of the ICRC will be guided by ... [t]he interpretative guidelines of the Department.” These guidelines, which are “illustrative” and “do not independently establish rules of conduct,” set forth the Department's interpretation of §504. Although they do not contain any definition of “discrimination,” they do state that §504 is not applicable to parents and that the regulation applies to only two categories of activities of hospitals: (1) refusals to provide treatment or nourishment to handicapped infants whose parents have consented to, or requested, such treatment; and (2) the failure or refusal to take action to override a parental decision to withhold consent for medically beneficial treatment or nourishment. With respect to the second category, the guidelines state that the hospital may not “solely on the basis of the infant's present or anticipated future mental or physical impairments, fail to follow applicable procedures on reporting such incidents to the child protective services agency or to seek judicial review.” With respect to the first category, the guidelines do not state that §504 categorically prohibits a hospital from withholding requested treatment or nourishment “solely on the basis of present or anticipated physical or mental impairments of an infant.” Rather, the substantive guidelines and two of the illustrative examples recognize that the etiology of and prognosis for particular handicapping conditions may justify “a refusal to treat solely on the basis of those handicapping conditions.” (§504 does not require “futile treatment”); (§504 does not require treatment of anencephaly because it would “do no more than temporarily prolong the act of dying”); (same with severely premature and low birth weight infants). In general, the guidelines seem to make a hospital's liability under §504 dependent on proof that (1) it refused to provide requested treatment or nourishment solely on the basis of an infant's handicapping condition, and (2) the treatment or nourishment would have been medically beneficial. The guidelines also describe how HHS will respond to “complaints of suspected life threatening noncompliance” with §504 in this context, progressing from telephone inquiries to the hospital to obtain information about the condition of the infant, to requests for access to records, and finally to onsite investigations and litigation in appropriate cases. The guidelines do not draw any distinction between cases in which parental consent has been withheld and those in which it has been given. Nor do they draw any distinction between cases in which hospitals have made a report of parental refusal to consent to treatment and those in which no report to a state agency has been made. They do announce that the “Department will also seek to coordinate its investigation with any related investigations by the state child protective services agency so as to minimize potential disruption,” indicating that the Department's investigations may continue even in cases that have previously been referred to a state agency.

1. Thank you to Stacey Tovino, Lehman Professor of Law and Director of the Health Law Program at William S. Boyd School of Law, UNLV, for explaining this complicated subject and for creating this outline.